<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister des ersten Festessens für Damien Hugo von Virmont in der Villa 
                    am Wasser von dem verstorbenen Amcazade Hüseyin Pascha, Istanbul, 18. September 1719 </title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of the first banquet organized for Damien Hugo von Virmont at the 
                    waterfront mansion of the deceased Amcazade Hüseyin Pasha, Istanbul, September 18, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont için merhum Amcazade Hüseyin Paşa’nın 
                    yalısında düzenlenen ilk ziyafet, İstanbul, 18 Eylül 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName> Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi </persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>

                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17190918</idno>
                <!-- PID: o:[context].[genre].[language].[date-iso](.[nr])
    # context: 
        vipa for Virmont/Ibrahim Paşa 1719-1720
        qhod ıs outdated, it’s only used for the meta context that aggregates the different edition subparts.
# genres:
ad. administrative document
ch. chronicle
in. instruction
l. letter
mh. mühimme
np. newspaper
pr. protocol register
pp. pamphlet
pt. petition
rc. record (Urkunde)
re. receipt
rp. report (Bericht, Relation)
tr. travelogue
# languages:
osm. ottoman source
hbg. habsburg source
# date:
yyyy-mm-dd or yyyy
we use the first known date of creation for handwritten texts 
and for printed ones the date of publication
# nr:
ONLY if a PID would duplicate (e.g. two habsburg letters on the same date) -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <!-- Archive, Library,… -->
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 60-64</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="scribe1">
                                <persName ref="#mpr13114">Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi</persName>
                                <desc><!-- e.g. Written in red ink --></desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1719-09-18"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Encoding guidelines -->
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister des ersten Festessens für Damien Hugo von Virmont in der Villa am Wasser von dem verstorbenen Amcazade Hüseyin Pascha, Istanbul, 18. September 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG01">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00029a2.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG02">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00029b.jpg" xml:id="IMG02"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG03">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00030a.jpg" xml:id="IMG03"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG04">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00030b.jpg" xml:id="IMG04"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG05">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00031a1.jpg" xml:id="IMG05"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190918">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
            <ab>
            <lb/><hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisi</rs>ne 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14709">[Amcazade] Ḥüseyin Paşa</rs> merḥūmuñ yalısında olan ż iyāfeti
                müşʿirdür. Fī <date type="Hijri" when="1719-09-18">4 Z̠iʾl-ḳaʿade
                    1131</date></hi></ab>
                
                <ab><lb/>Māh-ı mezbūruñ dördünci is̠ neyn güni <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūra</rs> <rs type="person" resp="#14709">ʿAmcazā de Ḥüseyin Paşa</rs>
                <lb/>merḥ ūmuñ yalısında ż iyāfet olunmaġ la z̠ ikr olunur.</ab>
                
            <ab>Yalı-yı mezbūrda deryā <lb/>üzerinde vāḳiʿ ḳaṣr-ı kebīr ve ḳurbında olan küçük oṭa
                ve ṭaşrasında <lb/>vāḳiʿ ṣuffa ve eṭrāfında
                iki üç oṭa daḫı meḥterḫāne-i ʿāmireden <lb/>bir iki gün muḳaddem döşendürilüb ve
                bir gün muḳaddem ketḫüdā beg ḥażretleri daḫı <lb/>gidüb mühimmāt-ı ż iyāfete ḳıyām ve
                köşküñ derūnında olan fısḳiyenüñ <lb/>eṭrāfına dāiren-mā dār sepetler ile meyveler ve
                ḳaṣrıñ üç ṣuffasını daḫı <lb/>şükūfeler ile tezyīn itdirmiş-idi.</ab>
            
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> ṭaşrada Ḥazinedār Çiftliginde olmaġ la <lb/>etbāʿı içün kifāyet
                miḳdārı mükārī bārgīri irsāl olunub lākin <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ve begzādegānı 
                
                <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>
                <lb/>kendü atlarıyla Defterdār İskelesine gelüb ve şıḳḳ-ı evvel efendinüñ yedi çifte
                <lb/>ḳayıġ ına ve etbāʿı daḫı irsāl olunan on beş yigirmiḳadar ḳayıḳlara süvār
                <lb/>olub sāʿat ikiye ḳarīb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devletüñ</rs> Beşiktaş ḳurbında vāḳiʿ <lb/>yalısı
                öñine geldiler.</ab>
            
                <ab>Ż iyāfet olunacaḳ yalıda ḫalḳ cemʿ olunca bir miḳdār <lb/>maḥabbetce ṣoḥbet olunmaḳ
                üzere daʿvet olunmaġ la <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ile ṭoḳuz nefer begzādegānı <lb/>ve ser-kātibi ve kendü
                tercümānı ve dīvān <add type="superlinear">tercümānı</add> yalıya çıḳub ḳ uṣ ūr-i etbāʿı
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> içün <lb/>yalı-yı mezbūr öniñde ḥāẓır olan İsmāʿīl Paşa çekdiri sefīnesine
                <lb/>çıkarıldı.</ab>
            
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> yalı-yı meẕkūrda vākiʿ bāġ çeye oturdılub <lb/>ve begzādegān ḳıyāmen
                durdılar. Baʿdehū ṣāḥ ib devlet ḥażretleri bāġ çe-i mezbūrıñ <lb/>ḥarem ḳapusından
                çıḳduḳlarında <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ve ̣çavuş başı aġ a öñine düşüb <lb/>geldüklerinde 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ḳıyām idüb ṣadra ḳuʿūd eylediler. 
                Bu es̠ nāda vezīr-i aʿẓam efendimüz <lb/>serḥaddī ṣofa ḳaplu semūr kürk giymişleridi.
                Baʿdehū ṭatlu ve ḳahve virildikden ṣoñra <lb/>ḥalvet olunmışdur.</ab>
            
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendimiz</rs> teşrīf eyledigi es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ve çavuşbaşı <lb/>ve
                teẕkireci efendiler ve muhż ır aġ a ve bostāncı oṭa başısı ve bu ḥaḳīr rūzmerre
                <lb/>gidiñiz es̠ vāb ve ṣarıḳlar ile köşküñ ṣuffesi 
                üzerinde selāma durmış-idik. <lb/>Lakin selām aġ ası bu maḥallde selām olmamışdur. 
                Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> yalıya yanaşduġ ında 
                <lb/>selām aġ asıyla ḳapucılar ketḫüdāsı istiḳbāl idüb çavuş başı gitmemişdür.</ab>
                
            <ab><lb/>Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye ḳahve virildügi es̠ nāda begzādegānına daḫı selsebīl ṭarafında olan küçük 
                <lb/>oṭada ṭatlu ve ḳahve virilmişdür. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ile ṣaḥīb devlet maḥfīce ṣoḥbet üzere
                <lb/>iken Dilsiz Ḥasan Aġ ayı ḥavuż a bıraḳdılar. ʿAẓ īm cilve-bahş olmışdur.</ab>
            
            <ab><lb/>Yarım sāʿat miḳdārı ṣoḥbet-i ḫāṣṣdan ṣoñra saʿādetlü vezīr-i aʿẓam ḥażretleri
                <lb/>ḳalḳub içerüye teşrīf buyurduḳlarında fermānları üzere 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi begi</rs>  ṭaşrada mevlevīḫāneye
                <lb/>muttaṣıl deryāya nāẓ ır köşke çıḳarılub yaṣdıḳ üzerine oturdub baʿdehū
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> gelüb şerbet ve buḫūr
                gelinceye degin <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib ṣadr ḥażretleri</rs>bir ikinci kerre
                <lb/>tüfeng atmışdur. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi merḳūmı</rs>
                ḳayıḳ ile çekdiriye götürüb süvār itdirildi.</ab>
                
            <ab><lb/>Bu es̠ nāda çekdiri filāndralar ile ve başdan başa küçük bayraḳlar ile ve cümle cānibinde 
                <lb/>olan pāyzenlerüñ birkaç ḳatı ḳırmızı paġ uryalıklar ile müzeyyen olmışlar idi. 
                <lb/>Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> çekdiriye bindigi gibi bir
                ḳalḳma ṭ opı atdılar. Ve żiyāfet maḥalline ʿazimet itdiler.</ab>
                
                
            <ab><lb/>Bir sāʿatden ṣoñra vezīr-i aʿẓ am daḫı ṣ andala süvār olub rūzgār ziyāde 
                <lb/>olduġ ından <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>nüñ çekdirisi tiziyye gidememekle
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>den evvel ż iyāfet
                <lb/>maḥalline gelüb çıḳduḳda yalı-yı mezbūrda müctemiʿ olan kürklü zuʿamā ve müteferriḳa başı vezīr
                <lb/>aġ aları ve hācegān ve aġ avātdan mesṭūrüʾl-esāmī olanlar biʾl-cümle ferāce semūr kürk
                <lb/>ve sarıḳlarıyla köşküñ ḫāricinde selāma ve çavuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī daḫı tellileriyle
                 
            <pb n="3" facs="#IMG03"/>
                
                <lb/>zuʿamānıñ verāsında olan sedd üzerinde selāma ṭurmışlar idi.</ab>
                
            <ab><lb/>Bu günde mevcūd olan ricālden eks̠ eri bi-lā daʿvet gelmişlerdür. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>, yalı-yı mezbūra
                <lb/>gelmezden muḳaddem baʿżı begzādegānı gelmiş bulunmaġ la vezīr-i aʿżam ṣandaldan çıḳduḳda
                <lb/>çavuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī alḳış eylemişlerdür. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">Ṣāḥib devlet</rs> köşke gelüb ḳuʿūd
                <lb/>eyledikleründe derūn-i ḳaṣrda olan meyve ve şükūfeden bir miḳdārı intiḫāb olunub 
                <lb/>veliyüʾl-niʿam-ı ʿālem olan şevketlü mehābetlü padişāhımız ṭarafına irsāl olundu.</ab>
                
            <ab><lb/>Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs> 
                çekdirisi aḳ ındıya güzer itmekde ṣuʿūbeti olduġ ından geç
                <lb/>ḳalmaġ la tiziyye gelmesi içün ḫaber gönderilmekle Bebek Bāġ çesi öñini tecāvüz iderek
                <lb/>çekdiriden çıḳarub yedi çifte ḳayıḳ ile yalıya getürilmişdür. Ḳuṣūr etbāʿı 
                <lb/>yine çekdiri ile gelmişdür.</ab> 
                
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> yalıya dāḫl olmazdan aḳdem vezīr-i aʿẓam küçük
                <lb/>oṭaya girüb baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> geldükde
                derūn-i ḳaṣrda ḳapuya nāẓır ṣofaya vażʿ olunan
                <lb/>iskemleye ḳuʿūd itdirildi. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
                efendimüz beyāż ferāce ṣofa ḳaplu
                <lb/>semūr kürk ile teşrīf eyledüklerinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>
                ḳıyām idüb muʿtād üzere ḥāżirūna 
                <lb/>selām-dāde olduḳda selām aġ ası ṣavt-ı bülend
                ile selām alub maḳām-ı ʿālīlerine 
                <lb/>oturduḳlarında ṭātlu ve ḳahve virildi.</ab> 
                
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>nüñ geldigi zamān sāʿat 
                <lb/>beşi tecāvüz itmekle der-ʿaḳab ṭaʿām döşenüb dībā sofra ve gümüş sini ḳonmışdur.
                <lb/>Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> içün bir
                ṭabaġ ın içine bir altūn kāfirī ḳaşıḳ ve bir çatal ve bir bıçaḳ 
                <lb/>ḳonmışdur. Vezīr-i aʿẓam ve dāmādları vezīr-i mükerrem Nişāncı Muṣṭafā Paşa
                <lb/>ve İmām-ı Evvel Şehriyārī <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ʿArabzāde Efendi</rs>
                ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> biʾl-cümle vezīr-i aʿẓamuñ 
                <lb/>ṣol ṭarafına oturub ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ṣaġ  ṭarafı semtine māʾilce yaṣdıḳ üzerine
                <lb/>oturub ṭaʿām tenāvül olundı. Ṭaʿāmuñ ḳabları biʾl-cümle mertabānī 
                <lb/>ve faġ fūr idi.</ab> 
                
            <ab>Ve begzādegānı içün daḫı köşküñ ḫāricinde bāġ çeye
                <lb/>ḳarşu ṣofada üç ʿaded peşgūn ve ḳuʿūdları içün ṭūlānī iskemleler
                <lb/>ḳonub ve etbāʿ-ı sāʾiresi içün daḫı aşaġ ı deñiz ṭarafında olan
                <lb/>meydānda beş altı yerde ṣofralara ḳonmışdur. Baʿdeʾl-ṭaʿām mevcūd olan meyve
                <lb/>ve şükūfeyi <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye inʿām idüb ḳaldırılmışdur. Baʿdehū ḫānendeler gelüb
                <lb/>köşküñ iç ṭarafında ṣaġ  cānibde vāḳiʿ ṣofa üzerine oturub faṣıl 
                <lb/>eylemişlerdür.</ab>
                
                
                <list type="musicians">
                <item rend="column1">ḫānende, nefer 13</item>
                <item rend="column2">neyzen, nefer 8</item>
                <item rend="column3">ṭanbūrī, nefer 4</item>
                <item rend="column4">ṣanṭūrī, nefer 2</item>
                <item rend="column5">kemānī, nefer 3</item>
                <item rend="column1">düdük, nefer 1</item>
                <item rend="column2">nefīrī, nefer 2</item>
                <item rend="column3">çeng, nefer 1</item>
                <item rend="column4">mis̠ ḳāl, nefer 1</item>
                </list>

            <ab><lb/>Faṣıl olunur iken <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
                efendimüz deryāda gezen ḳuşlara birkaç defʿa tüfeng
                <lb/>atub ḥattā bir martı ḳuşını urdı. Bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı şevḳe gelüb tüfengüñ
                <lb/>birini eline alub nişāna baḳar ve atar gūne ḥareket eyledi. Lākin atmadı. Bu es̠ nāda nişāncı
                
                <pb n="4" facs="#IMG04"/>
                
                <lb/>paşa ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">imām-ı evvel efendi</rs> daḫı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> ṭarafında otururlardı.</ab>
                
            <ab>Bu hengāmede
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> 
                ḥażretlerinüñ engüşt-i şerīflerinde bir kebīr elmās yüzük ve bir vasaṭ elmās
                <lb/>yüzük ve ṣol engüşt-i şerīflerinde daḫı bir kebīr zümrüd yüzük ve miyān-ı saʿādetlerinde
                <lb/>cevāhir ḳuşaḳ ve elmās ile muraṣṣaʿ hançeri
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> temāşā iderek bī-ṭāḳat
                <lb/>olmaġ la lisāna getirüb vāfir reşk eylemişdür. Bugünde hidmetde olan Enderūn
                <lb/>aġ aları biʾl-cümle mücevher hançer ile ve pāk libās ile müzeyyen idiler.</ab>
                
            <ab>Ḫānende faṣlı temām olduḳdan
                <lb/>ṣoñra iç aġ aları sāde neḳāre ile cerīd oynadılar. Baʿdehū pehlivānlar güreşdiler.
                <lb/>Baʿdehū ḥoḳḳa-bāzlar oynadılar. Baʿdehū Anaṭolu ve Rūmili ḥiṣārlarından Ḳaradeñiz
                <lb/>Boġ azına ṭoġ rı üçer defʿa sekdirme ṭoplar atıldı. Baʿdehū yine ḫānende
                <lb/>faṣıl itmişlerdür. Ve baʿdehū deryāya desti ḳonmaġ la <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> efendimüz tüfeng ile
                <lb/>birkaç desti şikest itmişdür. Baʿdehū yeñiçeri tüfengcileri atdılar.</ab> 
                
                
            <ab>Baʿdehū ikindi ṭaʿāmı 
                <lb/>tenāvül olunub baʿdehū bir miḳdār ṣoḥbet olunduḳdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>nüñ begzādegān etbāʿından
                <lb/>otuz miḳdārı keferenüñ boġ azlarına birer telli çekme baġ lanmışdur. Baʿdehū çekdiri başına
                <lb/>ve üzerine meʾmūr yeñiçeri ḫaṣekisine ve üzerine meʾmūr 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">Ḳapucıbaşı Meḥ med Aġ a</rs>ya ve çorbacıya
                <lb/>ve dīvān tercümānına ve kendü tercümānına birer hilʿat giydirilmişdür. 
                
                <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">
                    This Mehmed Agha, a <foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳapucıbaşı</foreign> (chief steward or <foreign xml:lang="de">Kämmerer</foreign>)
                    was appointed as the chief of guard and guide for the Austrian ambassador
                    and his entourage <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_85">during the Austrian
                        mission’s journey from Belgrade to Istanbul and their stay in the city in 1719-20.</ref>
                    It appears that the ambassador and Mehmed Agha cultivated a cautious
                    friendship: They <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_122"> had conversations about religion, faith,
                        and even the end of the world and apocalypse during the journey.</ref>
                    Once the convoy arrived in Istanbul, Mehmed Agha delivered the ambassador a welcome 
                    letter from the grand vizier. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_122">The same day in the evening, the agha 
                        introduced his four sons to the ambassador.</ref></note>
                On August 16, the last day of the month of Ramadan that year,
                Virmont was invited to the house of the agha for a festive meeting of several embassy members
                and numerous Ottoman officials. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_218">The
                    Austrian delegation spent the night at Mehmed Agha’s house.</ref> 
                
                
                Ḥattā çekdiri paşasına ibtidā
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> yalısı öñinde iken sālyānesine bir yük aḳçe żamm olunmaḳ üzere defterdār 
                <lb/>efendiye lisānen fermān buyurulmış.</ab>
                
                
            <ab>vech-i meşrūḥ üzere ḫilʿatler ilbās olunduḳdan ṣoñra
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye daḫı gül penbe çuḳa ferāceye ḳaplu semūr kürk ilbās olunmaġ la kürk ilbās
                <lb/>olunmazdan muḳaddem <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣaḥib devlet efendimüz</rs> ḳıyām idüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı ḳıyām eyledükde kürk
                <lb/>ilbās olunmışdur. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ḳıyām ile çekdiriye binüb ʿavdet eylemişdür. Baʿdehū herkese iz̠ n 
                <lb/>virilmişdür. Ḥattā begzādeniñ bir muʿteberine iki telli çekme virilmişdür. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> 
                <lb/>efendimüz ḫānendelerden birkaç neferin intiḫāb itdirüb hāṣṣaten ḥużūr-i
                <lb/>şerīflerinde faṣla āġ āz idüb</ab>
                
            <ab>aḫşām daḫı ḳarīb olmaġ la faḳ īr daḫı 
                <lb/>iş ḳalmadı mülāḥaẓ asıyla ḳayıġ a binüb ʿaẓīmet üzere iken
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">devletlü ṣadr-ı ʿālī efendimizüñ</rs> nażar-ı keremkārīlerine dūş olduġ umda deryā-yı 
                <lb/>mürüvvetleri temevvüc ve girü yalı-yı mezbūra ʿavdetimiz fermān buyurulub ve ḥużūr-i ʿālīlerine 
                <lb/>varduḳda bir ḫilʿat-ı ḫāṣṣüʾl-<corr>ḫ</corr><sic>h</sic>āṣ ilbās ve beyneʾl-aʿyān maḥsūdüʾl-aḳrān
                <lb/>buyurmışlardur. Ḥaḳḳ sübḥānehū ve teʿālā ʿömr ü devletlerin dāʿim eyleye bir ż īyāfet olmışdur ki
                <lb/>eslāfını birkaç fersaḥ geçmişdür. Rab teʿālā devlet-i ʿaliyeyi ilā yevmiʾl-ḳıyāme
                <lb/>dāyim eyleye. Āmīn.</ab>
                
            <ab>Bu hal üzere żabṭ olunmışdur ki bizden ṣoñra gelenlere iḳtiżā 
                <lb/>itdikde zaḥmet çekmeyeler ve bizi duʿā-yı ḫayr ile yād ideler.</ab>
                
                <pb n="5" facs="#IMG05"/>
                
                <ab><lb/><hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye żiyāfet olunduġ ı gün yalıya gelen ricāl-i aʿyāndur gelmeleri bilā daʿvetdür.</hi></ab>
                
                <list type="Ottoman_grandees">
                    <item rend="column1">nişāncı paşa</item>
                    <item rend="column2">imām-ı evvel efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column3">defterdār efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column4">def<supplied>t</supplied>er emīni efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column1">başmuḥāsebeci efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column2">fermān muhāsebecisi efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column3">maṭba<corr>ḫ</corr><sic>h</sic> emīni efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column4">arpa emīni efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column1">ż arbḫāne nāẓırı efendi</item> 
                    <item rend="column2">İstanbul bārūtḫāne nāẓırı aġ a</item>
                    <item rend="column3">sermehterān-ı ḫayme</item>
                    <item rend="column4">silāḥdār kātibi efendi</item>
                    <item rend="column1">tersāne emīni efendi</item> 
                    <item rend="column2">ḳapu ketḫüdālarından Mühür Yūsuf Aġ a</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Silāḥdār Aġ a-yı sābıḳ Mehmed Aġ a</item>
                    <item rend="column4">Ordu Ḳāżısı Fażallāh Efendi </item>
               </list>
                
            <ab><lb/>Bostāncıbaşı Aġ a daḫı geçerken uġ rayub dāmenbūs-i āṣafī ile müşerref olub
                <lb/>ḳahve virilüb yarım sāʿat miḳdārı celseden ṣoñra gitmişdür.</ab>
                            
        </div>
        <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190918-transl">
        <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
        
        <ab><hi rend="#red">The report on the banquet organized for  
             <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the Austrian ambassador</rs> at the waterfront mansion of the
            deceased <rs type="person" resp="#14709">[Amcazade] Hüseyin Pasha</rs>.</hi> September 18, 1719.</ab>
        
            <ab>The following relates the banquet that was organized for the said <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> at 
                the mansion of the deceased <rs type="person" resp="#14709">Amcazade Hüseyin Pasha</rs>, <date type="Hijri" when="1719-09-18">on the fourth day of the aforementioned
                month, which was a Monday.</date></ab>
            
            <ab>The large pavilion which is situated by the seaside at the said waterfront mansion,
                the small room in the pavilion’s vicinity, and an exterior bench together with surrounding rooms
                were richly furnished several days prior with items supplied from the inventory of the sultan’s
                tent pitchers. On the previous day, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s chief steward 
                set about the preparations for the banquet. 
                He had the entire circumference of fountain inside the kiosk adorned with baskets full of fruits 
                and had the three benches outside the pavilion adorned with flowers.</ab>
            
            <ab>Since the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was at that time residing at Hazinedar Farm outside the city, a sufficient number of
                packhorses were dispatched to accommodate his entourage. However, he and his inner circle 
                <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/> came to the Treasurer’s Pier mounted on their own horses
                and embarked on the chief treasurer’s caique equipped with
                seven pairs of oarsmen, while his entourage embarked on fifteen to twenty
                caiques. At about two o’clock, they arrived in front of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s 
                waterfront mansion in the vicinity of Beşiktaş.</ab>
                
            <ab>When people had gathered at the mansion where the banquet was to take place, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                was invited for a friendly conversation together with the nine members of his inner circle
                joined by his chief secretary, his personal interpreter, and the interpreter of the Ottoman imperial council,
                they went to the waterfront mansion. The remainder of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s entourage were boarded onto İsmail Pasha’s
                oar-powered ship (<foreign xml:lang="tr">çekdiri</foreign>) which was in front of the seaside mansion.</ab>
            
            <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was offered a seat inside the garden at the mansion and his close entourage remained
                standing. When his excellency, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, came inside through the garden’s harem gate –
                preceded by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">chief of the scribes</rs> and the agha of palace ushers – the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                rose to his feet and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> sat at his post. At that time,
                our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> had on him a sable fur lined with mohair (made in 
                or designed after the style of the frontier regions). After coffee 
                and sweets had been served, a private assembly took place.</ab>
            
            <ab>When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> had honored the room with his entrance, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">chief of the scribes</rs>, 
                the agha of the palace ushers, the grand vizier’s secretary (<foreign xml:lang="tr">tezkireci efendi</foreign>), the agha of the grand vizier’s guard,
                the chief gardener, and this poor recorder of daily affairs have stood greeting at the antechamber
                of the kiosk with our uniforms and turbans on [us]. However, the master of ceremonies
                did not performed a salutation at this occasion. When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came by the waterfront mansion, 
                the master of ceremonies and the aghas of the palace gatekeepers 
                went to receive him, but the agha of palace ushers did not go.</ab>
            
            <ab>As the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was being served coffee, his inner circle had also been
                served coffee and desert in the room located on the side of the ornamental fountain.
                As the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> were having a private conversation, Dilsiz (Mute) Hasan Agha
                was thrown in the pool. It was a [moment of] great amusement.</ab>
            
            <ab>Following a half-hour private conversation, our lord the felicitous <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>,
                stood up and honored the room with his entry. As per his command, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                was taken outside to the waterfront kiosk next to the Mevlevi lodge and was seated
                on a cushion. Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> came and, until sorbet and frankincense were served,
                he shot with a musket for a second time. After that, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was brought
                with a caique to the oar-powered ship and he was given a tour.</ab>
            
            <ab>The ship was adorned with pennants and small flags from one end to the other and the hulls
                of the ship were adorned with [images of] red crabs. When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came on deck,
                a departure cannon was fired and they advanced to the location of the banquet.</ab>
            
            <ab>An hour later, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> also embarked on a <foreign xml:lang="tr">ṣandal</foreign> (a European style row-boat).
                However, due to excessive winds, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s ship could not swiftly go and
                the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> came to the location of the banquet first. At that moment, 
                the holders of large military fiefs (<foreign xml:lang="tr">zuʿamā</foreign>) with their furs and turbans 
                on them, the head of the court
                officials, the aghas of viziers, the elders and aghas – whose names were written [on a list] –
                were standing in order to greet (them) outside the pavilion together. 
                They were wearing sable furs covered on a ceremonial cloak and their turbans. 
                The palace ushers, wearing their <foreign xml:lang="tr">telli</foreign>s [a ceremonial turban decorated with 
                gold or silver wire or threads],
                <pb n="3" facs="#IMG03"/>
                were standing on top of the barrier located behind the holders
                of large military fiefs (<foreign xml:lang="tr">zuʿamā</foreign>).</ab>
                
            <ab>The majority of the state officials who were present on this day came without an invitation.
                Before the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> had come to the mansion, some [members] of his inner circle had arrived, on which grounds
                the aghas of the palace ushers applauded when the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> disembarked
                the boat. When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> came to the kiosk and
                sat on his post, a certain amount of fruits and flowers that were present inside the kiosk
                were selected and dispatched to our gracious, majestic, awe-inspiring sultan.</ab>
                
            <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s ship had difficulty overcoming the current and, therefore, was late.
                As news was sent for the ship to dock swiftly, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was transferred
                past the Garden of Bebek to a caique powered with seven pairs of oars and was taken 
                to the waterfront mansion. Yet the rest of his entourage still came by ship.</ab>
                
            <ab>Before the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came inside the mansion, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> entered the small room.
                Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came and he was seated on the stool that was located 
                across the bench inside the pavilion. After that, as our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> honored 
                the room wearing a sable fur lined with a white mohair ceremonial cloak, the
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> rose to his feet and, as per custom, saluted those who were present. The master of
                ceremonies saluted back with a loud voice and, when [the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>] had sat down on his exalted post, 
                sweets and coffee were served.</ab>
                
            <ab>When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> arrived, it was past five o’clock. A meal was then spread out.
                A brocade meal cloth and a silver tray had been placed. For the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, an infidel-style
                gold spoon, fork, and knife were placed on a plate. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and his son-in-law,
                the esteemed vizier <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">Chancellor Mustafa Pasha</rs>, 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">the sultan’s private senior imam</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">Arabzade [Abdurrahman Bahir] Efendi</rs>,
                and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">chief of the scribes</rs> sat together on the left of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                sat on a cushion slightly leaning towards the right side of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and the meal
                was eaten. The entire tableware consisted of Martaban style dishes and Chinese porcelain.</ab>
                
            <ab>For the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s inner circle, three benches and long stools had been placed 
                on the porch outside the kiosk across the garden. For the rest of his entourage, meals
                were spread on five or six different locations down on the maidan by the sea.
                After the meal, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> offered the fruits and flowers that were present 
                to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, after which they were removed. Then, vocalists
                came, sat on the bench on the right side inside the kiosk, and performed.</ab>
                
                <list type="musicians">
                    <item rend="column1">vocalist, 13 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column2">ney player, 8 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column3">tanbur player, 4 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column4">santur player, 2 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column5">violin player, 3 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column1">düdük player, 1 person</item>
                    <item rend="column2">nefir player, 2 persons</item>
                    <item rend="column3">çeng player, 1 person</item>
                    <item rend="column4">miskal player, 1 person</item></list>
            
                            
            <ab>During the performance, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> shot a few times
                at the birds swimming on the sea and he hit a seagull. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>,
                carried away by the moment, took hold of a musket, aimed, and pretended to shoot but 
                he did not shoot. At this moment, the chancellor <pb n="4" facs="#IMG04"/> and the sultan’s private personal
                imam were sitting next to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>.</ab>
             
            <ab>In the meantime, on [the right hand] fingers of his highness the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>
                there was a large diamond ring and a small diamond ring, while on his left [hand] finger
                there was a large emerald ring. On his waist, there was a jeweled sash and a dagger
                adorned with diamonds. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> looked at them with admiration and he 
                could not overcome his desire to verbalize [how he felt], and he greatly envied [the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>]. On this day,
                the aghas of the inner court were all adorned with jeweled daggers and bright uniforms.</ab>
                
            <ab>After the performance of the vocalists was over, the aghas of the inner court 
                played the game of javelins as a single kettledrum played. After that, wrestlers wrestled.
                Next, jugglers performed. Then, from the Anatolian and Rumelian fortresses, 
                bouncing cannonballs were fired three times in the direction of the Black Sea.
                After that, the vocalists performed again. Next, jugs were placed on the sea
                and his highness the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> hit several jugs with a musket. Then,
                the janissary musketeers shot.</ab>
            
            <ab>Then, the mid-afternoon meal was eaten. After that, from among the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s inner circle,
                each one of about thirty infidels was presented with an embroidered fabric bound around their necks.
                Then, the palace janissaries, who were commissioned with service on and outside the ship,
                the head of the imperial gatekeepers <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">Mehmed Agha</rs> who
                supervised them, the janissary agha,
                the imperial council interpreter as well as the Austrian interpreter were
                dressed with robes of honor.<ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/> 
                
                <!--<note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                    This Mehmed Agha, a <foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳapucıbaşı</foreign> (chief steward or <foreign xml:lang="de">Kämmerer</foreign>)
                    was appointed as the chief of guard and guide for the Austrian ambassador
                    and his entourage <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_85">during the Austrian
                    mission’s journey from Belgrade to Istanbul and their stay in the city in 1719-20.</ref>
                    It appears that the ambassador and Mehmed Agha cultivated a cautious
                    friendship: They <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_122"> had conversations about religion, faith,
                    and even the end of the world and apocalypse during the journey.</ref>
                    Once the convoy arrived in Istanbul, Mehmed Agha delivered the ambassador a welcome 
                    letter from the grand vizier. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_122">The same day in the evening, the agha 
                    introduced his four sons to the ambassador.</ref></note>
                    On August 16, the last day of the month of Ramadan that year,
                    Virmont was invited to the house of the agha for a festive meeting of several embassy members
                    and numerous Ottoman officials. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_218">The
                    Austrian delegation spent the night at Mehmed Agha’s house.</ref> !-->
                
                Moreover, on the verbal orders of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> to the
                chief treasurer while in front of the waterfront mansion, the yearly salary of the agha of the ship
                was increased by a load(?) of akçe.</ab>
            
            <ab>After they had been dressed with robes of honor in this way, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> himself
                was dressed with a sable fur on a broadcloth ceremonial cloak. Before the 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was dressed
                with the fur, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and the
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> got up and the 
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was dressed with the fur in this way. 
                Next, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> embarked on the oar-powered ship 
                and returned. After that, everyone was dismissed. Furthermore, a man of good reputation
                from among the inner circle of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was presented with a [piece of] embroidered fabric. 
                Next, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> had a few of the vocalists chosen and they started 
                a private concert in his presence.</ab>
            
            <ab>As the evening was drawing near, assuming that there were left no tasks to be fulfilled, this humble servant
                was about to leave by embarking on a caique. When I happened to
                come across the benevolent sight of our lord the most excellent <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>,
                his sea of generosity surged and my return back to the waterfront mansion was
                commanded. When I arrived in his presence, he had me dressed with a robe of honor of the best kind
                that clearly made me envied among my peers. May God the exalted, may he be praised,
                perpetuate his life and government; this was such a feast that it outshined by far those that had been
                organized by the predecessors. Amen.</ab>
            
            <ab>[What happened] has been recorded in this way so that the posterity,
                if need be, (may read it) without any toil and may remember us with a prayer of benediction.</ab>
            
            <pb n="5" facs="#IMG05"/>
            
            <ab><hi rend="#red">The list of the grandees who have come to the waterfront mansion 
                on the day the banquet was organized. They came without invitation.</hi></ab>
            
            <list type="Ottoman_grandees">
                <item rend="column1">chancellor</item>
                <item rend="column2">sultan’s private senior imam</item>
                <item rend="column3">the chief treasurer</item>
                <item rend="column4">the superintendent of the (cadastral) register</item>
                <item rend="column1">the chief accountant</item>
                <item rend="column2">the accountant of the imperial edicts</item>
                <item rend="column3">the superintendent of the imperial kitchens</item>
                <item rend="column4">the superintendent of grains</item>
                <item rend="column1">the minister of the imperial mints</item> 
                <item rend="column2">the minister agha of the Istanbul arsenal</item>
                <item rend="column3">the chief of the imperial military barracks</item>
                <item rend="column4">the secretary of the swordkeepers</item>
                <item rend="column1">the superintendent of the navy yard</item> 
                <item rend="column2">Yusuf Agha, one of the aghas of the palace gatekeepers</item>
                <item rend="column3">Mehmed Agha, the former agha of the swordkeepers</item>
                <item rend="column4">Fazallah Efendi, army judge</item>
            </list>
                
        <ab>The chief gardener agha had also stopped by and was honored by the kissing the skirts of 
            the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s robe; he was served coffee and, after staying for half an hours, 
            left.</ab>
        
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>