<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <!-- title of the source -->
            <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über zweites Festessen organisiert für Damian Hugo von Virmont
                vor seiner Abreise, Istanbul, 11. April, 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of the second banquet organized for Damian Hugo von Virmont
                before his departure, Istanbul, April 11, 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un İstanbul’dan ayrılışından önce
                düzenlenen (ikinci) ziyafet, 11 Nisan 1720</title>
            <!-- author of the source -->
            <author>
                <persName>Teşrifati Salman Efendi</persName>
            </author>
            <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
            <respStmt>
                <!-- editor -->
                <resp>Edition</resp>
                <persName xml:id="yy">
                    <forename>Yasir</forename>
                    <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <!-- data modelling-->
                <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Stephan</forename>
                    <surname>Kurz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
                <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/">
                    Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan Studies
                </orgName>
            </publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at">
                    GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset Management System
                </orgName>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
                    Creative Commons BY 4.0
                </licence>
            </availability>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            
            <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200411</idno>
       </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title>
            <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Arno</forename>
                    <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                    <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                    <idno>no. 347, p. 84-86</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                
                <physDesc>
                  
                </physDesc>
                <history>
                    <origin>
                        <origDate when="1720-04-11"/>
                    </origin>
                </history>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document --> 
        </editorialDecl>
        <projectDesc>
            <ab>
                <ref target="context:vipa" type="context">
                    Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20)
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context">
                    Protokollbücher
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:qhod" type="context">
                    Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918
                </ref>
            </ab>
            <!-- Project description -->
            <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
        </projectDesc>
        <refsDecl>
            <p>
                Protokollregister über zweites Festessen organisiert für Damian Hugo von Virmont vor seiner Abreise, Istanbul, 11. April, 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
            </p>
        </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
        </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
    
    <surface start="#IMG1">
        <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00041a.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
    </surface>
    <surface start="#IMG2">
        <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00041b.jpg" xml:id="IMG02"/>
    </surface>
    <surface start="#IMG3">
        <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00042a1.jpg" xml:id="IMG03"/>
    </surface>
    
</facsimile>
                   
<text type="protocol">
<body>
    <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200411">
    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/> 
    <ab>
        <lb/><hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe çāsārınıñ</rs> ṣulḥnāme ile gelen
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">büyükilçisine</rs> defʿa-i
        ̱sānīyede żiyāfet olunduġ ı keyfiyyeti müşʿirdür. <date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-11">2 
            C<supplied resp="#yy">emaziyülahir</supplied> 1132</date></hi></ab>
        
        <ab><lb/>Fermān-ı Rabb-i müsteʿān her ānda bir gūne ẓuhūr ve nümāyān olmaḳ mahż-ı ḥikmet-i yezdān olmaġ la biñ yüz otuz bir 
            <lb/>senesi Ramażān-ı Şerīfinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roma İmparaṭorı</rs>
            ṭarafından ṣulḥnāme ile Āsitāneye gelen kebīr <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiye</rs>
        <lb/>nāmesi virildikden ṣoñra ʿavdetine ḳarīb biñ <add place="superlinear">yüz</add>
            otuz iki senesi Cemāẕīyeʾl-āḫirinüñ ikinci Cehārşenbe
        <lb/>güni devletlü saʿādetlü ʿāṭıfetlü dāmād-ı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">fahriyārī</rs>
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam-ı cihānbānī İbrāhīm Paşa ḥażretleri</rs> 
            <lb/>Kāġ ıdḫāne cānibinde Ṭaşlıca Burnı taʿbīr olunur maḥallde vezīr-i aʿẓam-ı sābıḳ 
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr11014">Ḳara Muṣṭafa Paşa</rs>
        <lb/>merḥūmuñ yalısında żiyāfet eylemekle ẕikr olunur.</ab> <space quantity="2" unit="chars"/> 
        
    <ab>Yevm-i mezbūrdan bir gün muḳaddem çadır mehter 
        <lb/>başısı aġ a gidüb yalı-yi mezbūrda ḥavuża ve deryāya nāẓır köşkü sūzenī maḳʿadlar ile ve aġ ır
        <lb/>yasdıḳlar ile döşeyüb ve köşküñ ḳurbında olan odayı daḫı döşeyüb ve bāġ çe içine bir çadır
        <lb/>ve bir çerke ḳurılub ve bāġ çe yolına ẕuḳāḳlar çaḳılub ve yalı-yı mezbūrda olan sāyir odalar ve köşkleri daḫı  
        <lb/>dāʾire-i ʿalīye içün döşeyüb ḥāżır ve müheyyā eylemişdi.</ab>
        
    <ab>Ve saʿādetlü ketḫüdā beg ḥażretleri daḫı bir gün
        <lb/>muḳaddem gidüb mühimmāt-ı żiyāfeti ve sāʾir levāzımātı görmişlerdir. Ve żiyāfet güni ʿaleʾs-seḥer kürklü 
        <lb/>müteferriḳagān vezīr aġ aları ferāce semūr kürkleriyle ve çāvuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī ḳollarıyla yalı-yı mezbūra
        <lb/>varub mevcūd bulunmışlar idi. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
        ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">nişāncı paşa ḥażretleri</rs> teşrīf ve ḳaṣr-ı
        <lb/>mezbūra ḳuʿūd eylemişlerdi. Ve köşküñ muḳābelesinde olan ḥavuż daʾiren-mā-dār şukūfe ve meyve ile
        <lb/>zeyn olunmış-idi. Baʿdehū köşküñ ḥavuż semti muḳābelesinde olan bayıra dest-yār ḳonılub 
        <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> ve sāʾiri ḳurşun atmışlardur.</ab>
        
    <ab>Sāʿat bire varacaḳ vaḳitde semāḥatlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">şeyḫüʾl-islām
        <lb/>efendi</rs> ve saʿādetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">ḳapūdān paşa</rs> ḥażretleri teşrīf buyurdılar. Baʿdehū sāʿat ikiye ḳarīb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs>
        <lb/>ẓ uhūru ḫaber virilmekle ḳaṣr-ı mezbūruñ ḫāricinde kenār-ı yalıda selām aġ ası ve çavuşlar kātibi ve çavuşlar
        <lb/>emīni ve çavuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī ṣaff-beste ve bunlaruñ nihāyetinde muḳābeleden yalı ḳapusına gelince vezīr aġ aları 
        <lb/>ve yine ḳaṣr-ı mezbūruñ kenārında dīvār ṣırasıyla ḳapuya gelince kürklü müteferriḳagān ṣaff-beste ve yeñiçeri 
        <lb/>tüfengcileri daḫı vezīr aġ alarınuñ verāsında ellerinde tüfengler ile ṣaff-keşīde olub</ab>
        
    <ab>müḥeyyā olduḳları 
        <lb/>ḫalālde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs>
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">defterdār efendinüñ</rs> yedi çifte ḳayıġ ı ile köşküñ altında olan iskeleye yanaşduḳda
        <lb/>çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve bu ḥaḳīr varub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiyi</rs>
        alub ve köşke götirüb ṣadruñ öñinde olan ṣırmalı 
        <lb/>iskemleye oturdub bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
        ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">şeyḫüʾl-islām</rs> ve vüzerā-yı ʿiẓām içerü oṭada olmaġ la
        <lb/>bu ḥaḳīr varub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> gelüb oturduġ ını
        saʿādetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet ḥażretlerine</rs> ḫaber virüb</ab>
        
    <ab>ṭaşra 
        <lb/>teşrīf eyledüklerinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>
        ḳıyām idüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">devletlü efendimüz</rs>
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ve çavuş paşa aġ a ṭarafına selām-dāde 
    <lb/>olduḳda aşaġ ıdan selām aġ ası ṣavt-ı bülend ile selām alub ṣadra ḳuʿūd eyledüklerinde çāvuşān-ı 
    <lb/>dergāh-ı ʿālī alḳış eylediler. Bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendīmüz</rs> ḳırmızı ferāce çuḳaya ḳaplu
    semūr kürk 
    <lb/>giymişlerdi. Ve miyān-ı saʿādetlerine cevāhir ḳuşaḳ ve elmās ile muraṣṣaʿ ḫancer ṭaḳmışlardı ve ṣaġ 
    <lb/>ṣerçe parmaġ ına bir kebīr elmās ve bir zümrüd yüzük ṭaḳmışlardı ve ṣol ṣırça parmaġ ına daḫı Anāṭolı 
        <lb/>Ḥiṣārı semtinde vezīr-i sābıḳ <rs type="person" resp="#14709">ʿAmcazāde Ḥüseyin Paşa</rs> yalısında żiyāfet olundıġ ı gün
    <lb/>ṭaḳındıġ ı yüzüğüñ muġ āyiri bir kebīr elmās yüzük ṭaḳmışlardı</ab>
        
    <ab>ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> oturacaġ ı ṭarafda 
        <lb/>yaṣdıḳ üzerine cevāhir ḳabżalu bir pala ḳonub ve yine <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ṭarafında olan direge elmās ile muraṣṣaʿ 
        <lb/>bir ḳılıç eviḫte olunub ve enderūn aġ aları daḫı biʾl-cümle elvān reng cedīd ḫāre ve ḥilālī ḳaftānlar 
        <lb/>mülebbes ve mücevher ḫancerler ile müzeyyen idiler.</ab>
        
    <ab>Ḥāṣıl-ı kelām <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendimüz</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūrı</rs> nevāzīşden ṣoñra 
        <lb/>maḳām-ı ʿālīlerine ḳuʿūd eylediler. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">şeyḫüʾl-islām</rs> efendī
        ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">ḳapūdān paşa</rs> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">nişāncı paşa ḥażretleri</rs> içerüden
        <lb/>ṭaşra daʿvet buyurulub müşārün ileyhim ḥażerātı gelüb oturduḳları gibi germīyet ṣoḥbet içün muḳaddemā
        <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> maḳṣūdı olan işlerden iki māddenüñ kāġ ıdları
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> yedine virilüb baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçize</rs>        
        <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/> 
        
        <lb/>ve sāʾire ṭatlu ve ḳahve virilüb ḥattā <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> benefşe <sic>ḥamīresi</sic> 
        tenāvül eyledükden ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendimüz</rs> 
        <lb/>muḥabbeten kendileri tenāvül eyledikleri cevāhir maʿcūnından daḫı virdürdiler baʿdehū ḳahveler içildükden ṣoñra
        <lb/>ṭaʿām gelmekle <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓamuñ</rs> ṣāġ  ṭarafında
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">şeyḫüʾl-islām efendi</rs> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">ḳapūdān paşa</rs> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">nişāncı paşa</rs>
        <lb/>ve ṣol ṭarafında yaṣdıḳ üzerinde yalñız <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> oturmışdur.</ab>
        
    <ab>Baʿdeʾt-ṭaʿām deryā ṭarafında olan
        <lb/>meydāna bir ṣıradan üç destī ḳonub Enderūn aġ aları ve yeñiçeri tüfengcileri ḳurşun atmışlardur.
        <lb/>Bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendimüz</rs> birbiri ardınca sekiz defʿa nişānı vurub destīleri şikest
        <lb/>itmişlerdür. Ḥattā devletlü efendimizüñ eñ ṣoñra āteşlerinde muḥżır aġ a ṭāʾifesinden destī götüren çorbacı
        <lb/>yeñiçerinüñ ḳurşun iki ayaġ ı arasından güz̠ er idüb destīyi şikest itmişdür. Ḥaḳḳ bu ki
        <lb/>bu vech ile nişān-zed olduḳlarına ḥāżır-ı cemʿiyyet olan müslimīn ve müşrikīn taḥsīn ve engüşt ber dehān
        <lb/>olmışlardur.</ab>
        
    <ab>Baʿdehū sāde naḳḳāre ile iç aġ aları atlu cirīdi ile oynamışlardur. Bugünde
        <lb/>maḥall-i mezbūra nāẓır olan bayırda ve aşaġ ıda vāfir seyirciler cemʿ olmışlar idi. Ḥattā ṣābūncı
        <lb/>başı aġ a daḥı neferātıyla kendi ferāce semūr kürk ile yeñiçeri tüfengcilerinüñ öñinde durmış idi.</ab>
        
    <ab><lb/>Tüfeng atılduġ ı es̠ nāda aġ alardan birisi seksen beş dirhem tüfengi ḳoldan nişāna atmaġ ıyla
        <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi beg</rs> tüfeng-i mezbūru getürdüb ve eline alub yaṣdıḳ üzerine ḳoyub nişāna baḳdı.
        <lb/>Ve mezkūr tüfengüñ ḳurşunından bir iki dānesin aldı. Baʿdehū tüfengüñ ṣāḥibi baʿdeʾt-temāşā
        <lb/>yine nişāna ḳurşun attıġgı gibi ḥikmet-i ḫüdā żarb-ı tüfengden ser-nigūn ve elinden tüfengi düşüb
        <lb/>ḳonaraḳ ṭabanı ḳırılmışdur. Bu gūne keyfiyyet ẓuhūrı naẓara ḥaml olunmışdur.</ab>
        
    <ab>Bālāda ẕikr olundıġ ı üzere
        <lb/>baʿdeʾl-cirīd ḫānende ve sāzende kāmil altmış nefer mevcūd olmaġ la köşküñ aşaġ ısında yalı iskelesi
        <lb/>üzerinde oturub faṣl eylemişlerdür. Bu es̠ nāda kisveli pehlivānlar güreşdiler. Baʿdehū bir ādem başı
        <lb/>üzerinde direk götürmek üzere üç defʿa murād eyledi. Lākin icrāsına muvaffaḳ olamadı. Baʿdehū
        <lb/>şīşebāzlar baʿdehū maṭraḳçılar baʿdehū gürzbāzlar baʿdehū baġ çevān ḳolı ve Aḥmed ḳolu muṭrıbları
        <lb/>ḳaṣr-ı mezbūruñ muḳābelesinde oturub mez̠ kūr ḳullar başḳa başḳa raḳṣ oġ ̇lanlarıyla kendilerine
        <lb/>maḫṣūṣ olan luʿbların icrā eylediler.</ab>
        
        <ab>Bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib-i devlet efendimüz</rs> içerü oṭaya gidüb
        <lb/>ferāce kürki çıkarub ḳırmızı çuḳa ḳontoş semūr kürk ile çıḳub oturmışlardur.
        <lb/>Bu es̠ nāda rüzgār bir miḳdār bürūdet üzere vezān olmaġ la dizlerine zemīni teftī aġ ır ṣırma
        <lb/>işleme yorgan vażʿ itmişler idi. Baʿdehū ḥoḳḳabāzlar baʿdehū ḳūḳlabāzlar köşküñ        
        <lb/>muḳābelesinde perde ḳurub ḳūḳla oynatdılar.</ab>
        
    <ab>Bu esnāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet efendimüze</rs> nevm ̣ġalaba itmekle
        <lb/>içerü oṭaya teşrīf ve yarım sāʿat miḳdārı ser-nihāde-i bālīn-i rāḥat olub bīdār-ı ḫābları
        <lb/>vaḳt-i ʿaṣra müṣādafe itmekle ikindi ṭaʾāmı yine köşke döşetüb içerüden teşrīf buyurduḳlarında
        <lb/>ḳırmızı çuḳa ḳonṭoş çılḳafa kürk giymişlerdi. Ḳūḳlabāzlardan ṣoñra ḫānende ve sāzende
        <lb/>faṣla āgāz itmeleriyle ṭaʿām tenāvüli tekmīline deġ in faṣl itmişlerdür. 
        Bu vaḳtıñ ṭaʿāmında <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">imām-ı evvel-i
        <lb/>şehriyārī</rs> efendi daḫı dāḫil olmışlar idi.</ab>
        
    <ab> Baʿdeʾt-ṭaʿām tekrār şerbet ve buḥūr virildikden ṣoñra
        <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">şeyḫüʾl-islām efendi</rs> ḥareket 
        eylemekle ḳaṣr-ı mezbūr iskeleye ġāyet ḳarīb iken <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet
            <lb/>efendimüz</rs> ikrāmen iskeleye piyāde gitmesünler diyü
        ḥavuż kenārından ata bindürilüb ber-ḳāʿide ketḫüdā beg
        <lb/>ve çavuşbaşı aġ a ve sāʾiri öñince iskeleye götürmişler idi. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> bege gülpenbe
        <lb/>ferāce çuḳaya ḳaplu semūr kürk ilbās ve üzerine meʾmūr <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">ḳapucı Meḥmed Aġ āya</rs> ve yeñiçeri
        
        <pb n="3" facs="#IMG03"/>
        
        <lb/>ḥāṣekīsine ve çorbacıya ve dīvān tercümānına ve kendi iki nefer tercümānına ḫilʿatler ilbās
        <lb/>ve on beş yigirmi nefer begzādegānına daḫı telli boyamalar virilmişdir.</ab>
        
    <ab>Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> beye siyāh çuḳa üzerine
        <lb/>ṣırma işleme kesmeli ve sīm rikābla mīnākārī raḫt ile müzeyyen bir ṭoru ṭay at
        <lb/>ve bir ḳır ṭay at yılkı-zer virilmişdür. Mezkūr atlar ṭay olmaḳ  üzere virildügi <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> begüñ
        <lb/>ṭāy ata ziyāde raġ beti olduġ ından velīyüʾl-niʿam efendimiz maḥẓūẓīyeti içün böylece kerem buyurmışlardur.
        <lb/>Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> beg hedīye olan ata bindürilüb iskeleye gönderilmişdür. Baʿdehū kenār-ı ḥavużda olan
        <lb/>meyve ve şukūfe biʾl-cümle <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> begiñ ḫānesine gönderilmişdir.</ab>
        
        <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">The Austrian secretary C. Driesch summarized this banquet in
            <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page406">his travelogue</ref>. Driesch was not impressed by the 
        festivities and recorded negative observations. He was nauseated by the persons around him who ate the food with their hands.
        He found the Ottoman entertainments banal and unsophisticated. He described the comedy play of boy dancers 
        as "<ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page410">sodomitical</ref>."</note>
        
    <ab>Baʿdehū mehterḫāne çalmaġla
        <lb/>bu es̠ nāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib-i devlet efendīmüz ḥażretleri</rs> bu ḥaḳīre ve mehter başı aġ aya ḥilʿatler iḥsān
        <lb/>buyurmışlardur. Mehterḫāneden ṣoñra ḫānende ve sāzendeden baʿżıları intiḫāb olunub
        <lb/>ḳaṣr-ı mezbūruñ dehlīzinde bir faṣl itdürilüb ve ḫānende başı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14720">Burnaz Ḥasan Çelebi’ye</rs> daḫı
        <lb/>ḫilʿat iḥsān buyurmışlardur. Ve sāʾirine daḫı sikke-i ḥasene inʿām buyurmışlardur. Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">devletlü
        <lb/>efendimizüñ</rs> bugünde ʿiṭā ve iḥsān eyledügi altunuñ ḥadd ve ḥesābı nā-maʿlūmdur.</ab>
        
    <ab>Ve żiyāfet-i 
        <lb/>mezbūrede mevcūd görilen ricāl daḫı bunlardur ki ẕikr olunur: defterdār efendi, Defter Emīni-yi 
        <lb/>sābıḳ El-ḥāc ʿAbduʾl-ḳādir Efendi ve tersāne emīni efendi ve maṭbaḫ-ı ʿāmire emīni efendi ve atlu 
        <lb/>muḳābelecisi ʿAbdullāh beg ve sipāhīler aġ ası ve Ḫazīne Muḥāsebecisi <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">Dürrī efendi</rs> ve Arpa Emīni
        <lb/>Süleymān Efendi ve Silāḥdār Aġ ası sābıḳ Boşnaḳ Meḥmed Aġ a ve ḥaremeyn muḥāsebecisi ve maliye teẕkirecisi 
        <lb/>ve bāşbāḳī ḳulı aġ a ve ḥaremeyn muḳāṭaʿacısı efendi.</ab>
    
    </div>
    
    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190411-transl">    
    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/> 
    
    <ab><hi rend="#red">Informs about the circumstances of the second banquet organized for the grand ambassadaor 
        of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Austrian emperor</rs> who came with a peace settlement.</hi> 11 April 1720.</ab>
        
    <ab>As a reflection of the fact that the decrees of God the benefactor are evident 
        and they manifest themselves in one way or another at all times is the pure wisdom of God, 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">grand ambassador</rs>, who had come from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman Emperor</rs> to Istanbul in the blessed (month of) Ramadan
        of the year one-thousand one-hundred and thirty-one (July 18 – August 16, 1719) with a peace settlement, was given his
        sultanic letter. Then, shortly before his departure, his highness, the prosperous, kind,
        honorable son-in-law of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">sultan</rs>, the keeper of the world, 
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier İbrahim Pasha</rs>, organized a banquet on <date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-11">the second Wednesday of the month of 
        <foreign xml:lang="tr">Cemāẕīyeʾl-āḫir</foreign> in the year one-thousand one-hundred and thirty-one</date> at the waterfront mansion of the
        deceased former <rs type="person" ref="#mpr11014">Grand Vizier Kara Mustafa Pasha</rs>, which is located next to Kağıdhane in the 
        area known as the Cape of Taşlıca. What follows is a report of that event.</ab>
        
    <ab>A day before the banquet, the chief of the sultan’s tent pitchers went to the said waterfront
        mansion and had the pool and the pavilion facing the sea furnished with seats and heavy cushions.
        He also had the room next to the pavilion furnished and set up a large tent in the garden 
        as well as a makeshift tent. Markers were pounded around the passage to the garden and a variety of
        rooms inside the mansion and its pavilions were furnished and made ready for the court members.</ab>
        
    <ab>His highness the prosperous chief steward also went a day before and took care of the 
        supplies of the banquet and other requirements. At dawn on the day of the banquet, the court officials,
        with their furs on them, the aghas of viziers, with their sable furs on ceremonial cloaks, and 
        the palace ushers, with their units, arrived at the mansion and were present there. Then, 
        his highness the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">chancellor</rs>, honoring [those in attendance] with their presence, sat at
        the pavilion. The pool, located across from the pavilion, was adorned all around with flowers and fruits.
        Then, a target was erected on the slope situated across the area where the pool was located
        and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and others shot [at the target].</ab>
        
        <ab>Shortly before it was one o’clock, his highness the generous <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs> and the prosperous
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">admiral</rs> honored [the gathering] with their presence. After that, shortly before two o’clock, the arrival of 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was reported [to the meeting]. Therefore, outside the aforementioned pavilion by the mansion,
        the master of ceremonies, the secretary and the intendant of the palace ushers and palace ushers themselves stood
        in line. Beyond them, from across where they were standing to the gate of the mansion, there were
        the aghas of the viziers and the court officials with their furs were standing on the side of the pavilion along the wall
        stretching till the door. The janissary musketeers stood in line with their muskets in their hands
        behind the aghas of the viziers.</ab> 
        
        <ab>As they were all standing disposed in order, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came by the
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">chief treasurer’s</rs> caique
        powered by seven pairs of oars that docked at the pier. Then, the secretary and the intendant of the palace ushers
        and this humble servant received the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and brought him to the pavilion and had him
        sitting on [a] stool worked with gold and silver embroideries. At that moment, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, 
            the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs>, and the viziers of the imperial council were inside the inner room. This humble
        servant entered there and reported to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> the arrival and sitting down of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>.</ab>
        
    <ab>When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> honored the outside area with his presence, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> stood up and saluted 
        in the direction of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">the chief of the scribes</rs>, and the agha of palace ushers.
        The master of ceremonies responded to the salutation with a loud voice. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> sat on his
        post, upon which the palace ushers applauded. Our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> was wearing 
        a sable fur claok lined with red broadcloth. On his fortunate waist, there was a jeweled
        sash and a dagger adorned with diamonds. He had put on his right little finger a large diamond ring and
        a large emerald ring, while he had on his left little finger a large diamond ring similar
        to the one he had put on the day of the banquet at the mansion of the former 
        <rs type="person" resp="#14709">grand vizier Amcazade Hüseyin Pasha</rs> in the Anadolu Fortress quarter.</ab>
    
    <ab>And, on the side of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, where the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> would sit, a machete with a jeweled grip had been placed
        on a cushion. Moreover, on the column located on the side of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, a sword adorned
        with diamonds had been hung. The aghas of the inner court were all wearing caftans with
        colorful moiré patterns and crescent designs and they were accessorized with jeweled daggers.</ab>
        
    <ab>To summarize, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> sat on his exalted post after displaying
        courtesy to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>. Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs>,
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs>&gt; <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">admiral pasha</rs>, and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">chancellor</rs> pasha
        were invited from inside to the outside. As they came and sat down two papers about
        two [separate] matters that had been requested by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> were handed to him so that a cordial
        conversation could take place. After that the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was 
        
        <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/> 
        
        served sweets and coffee. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> also ate violet dough (<foreign xml:lang="tr">benefşe ḥamīresi</foreign>). After that, 
        our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, out of friendship, had precious and costly opiates (<foreign xml:lang="tr">cevāhir maʿcūnu</foreign>) that
        he himself ate presented also to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>. After coffee was drunk, the meal arrived. On the right
        side of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> sat the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs>, 
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14728">the admiral</rs>, and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">the chancellor</rs> and on his 
        left the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat by himself on a cushion.</ab>
        
    <ab>After the meal, jugs were placed [as targets] in a line on the arena by the sea. The aghas of the inner court
        and the janissary muskeeters shot bullets [at the targets]. At that moment, our lord 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> hit the target eight times consecutively and broke the jars. Moreover, 
        in the last shooting of our most exalted lord, the bullet hit the jar, 
        going through between the two legs of the janissary captain who was a 
        member of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s guard and was carrying jugs. Thus, all the Muslims
        and non-Muslims present applauded and put their fingers to their mouths 
        at [the way] he hit the target.</ab> 
        
        <note xml:id="ftn2" type="editorial" resp="#yy">Putting fingers into mouth was an expression of astonishment, 
        similar to biting one’s nails. There are depictions of this expression in miniatures.</note>
        
    <ab>After that, the aghas of the inner court played the game of javelins on horses as a single kettle-drum
        was beaten. That day, too, a large number of onlookers had gathered on the slopes overseeing 
        the location of the banquet as well as on the lower side [of our location]. 
        Even the master of soap makers (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ṣābūncıbaşı aġa</foreign>), who had a sable fur on a ceremonial cloak on him,
        stood with his men in front of the janissary musketeers.</ab>
        
    <ab>As muskets were being fired, one of the aghas shot with a musket of
        eighty-five dirhams aiming on his arm. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> had the musket brought to him, took it in his hand,
        put it on a cushion, and then aimed it. Then he took a few of the bullets of the musket.
        After the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> took a look at the musket, the owner of it again aimed at the target and shot.
        As soon as he shot at the target, by the wisdom of God, due to the recoiling of the musket, he lost his balance
        and dropped the musket, breaking its stock. This kind of an occurrence was ascribed to the evil eye.</ab>
        
        <ab>As mentioned above, following the game of javelins, vocalists and musicians – all together sixty persons –
        sat on the mansion’s pier below the pavilion and performed. Then the wrestlers wearing leather trousers
        wrestled. Then, a performer wanted to carry a stick on his head and attempted it three times. However,
        he could not succeed. Next, performers of cups and bowls(<foreign xml:lang="tr">şīşebāzlar</foreign>),
        sword masters (<foreign xml:lang="tr">maṭraḳçılar</foreign>), maze fighters (<foreign xml:lang="tr">gürzbāzlar</foreign>),
        then the gardeners and the singers of the Ahmed branch of entertainers sat across
        the pavilion and these men, along with other boy dancers, performed the peculiar games.</ab>
        
    <ab>In the meantime, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> entered the inner room, took off the ceremonial cloak,
        put on a sable fur on red broadcloth <foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳontoş</foreign> (a richly embroidered robe worn by Crimean Tatars),
        and came out and sat. At that moment, as the wind blew a bit cool, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> spread
        a warm quilt on his knees worked on its surface with heavy gold and silver threads. Then, jugglers performed, followed
        by puppeteers who set up a curtain across the pavilion and performed a puppet show.</ab>
        
    <ab>Meanwhile, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> was overwhelmed by sleep and entered the inner room to sleep. For half an hour, he rested
        putting his head on a pillow. As his awakening from sleep coincided with the mid-afternoon time, the
        mid-afternoon meal was laid out at the pavilion. When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> came from inside and honored 
        the room by his presence, he was wearing a <foreign xml:lang="tr">çılkafa</foreign> (a fur made of pieces from the back of the
        neck of wolves or foxes) on a red broadcloth <foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳontoş</foreign>. After the puppeteers, vocalists and
        musicians began their musical performance and performed until the end of the meal.
        The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">sultan’s private senior imam</rs> also joined the mid-afternoon meal.</ab>
        
    <ab>After the meal, sorbet and frankinsence were served. Then, as the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs> was leaving,
        although the pavilion was close to the pier, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, as a favor, told him not to
        walk to the pier, upon which the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs> was mounted on a horse by the pool and, as per custom,
        the chief steward, the agha of the palace ushers and others preceded the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14719">chief müfti</rs> 
        when they brought him to the pier. After that, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was presented with a sable fur on a
        rose-pink broadcloth ceremonial cloak. Also, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">gatekeeper Mehmed Agha</rs>, who was  
        commissioned to accompany the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, the janissary
        <pb n="3" facs="#IMG03"/> and the janissary captain, the imperial council interpreter, and 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s two interpreters were dressed in robes of honor. 
        Fifteen to twenty members of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s inner circle
        were presented with colored and embroidered kerchiefs.</ab>
    
    <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was presented with a chestnut yearling(?) adorned with a horse blanket 
        made of black broadcloth worked with silver and gold threads, silver stirrups, and a harness worked with enamels.
        He was also presented with a grey yearling colt. That these young horses were given was 
        because the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> had a strong liking for young horses. Thus, our lord the benefactor
        acted so kindly for his [the ambassador’s] rejoicement. Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> mounted on the horse
        presented to him and was sent to the pier. After that, all of the flowers and fruits
        around the pool were sent to the residence of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>.
        <ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/></ab>
        
        
        
    <ab>Afterwards, as the military band was playing, our lord the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> granted this
        humble servant and the agha of the military band robes of honor. After the military band performance,
        some of the vocalists and musicians were selected and performed at the hall of
        the pavilion. The chief vocalist, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14720">Burnaz Hasan Çelebi</rs>, was granted a robe of honor. The 
        other (vocalists and musicians) were granted gold coins. The amount and limit of the gold
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">our fortunate lord</rs> presented and granted today is unknown.</ab>
        
    <ab>Here are the men who were present at the banquet: the chief treasurer, the former superintendent of
        the cadastral register, Abdu’l-kadir efendi, the superintendent of the navy yard, the
        superintendent of the imperial kitchens, mounted treasury officer (<foreign xml:lang="tr">atlu muḳābelecisi</foreign>)
        Abdullah Bey, the agha of the palace cavalry, treasury accountant, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">Dürrī efendi</rs>,
        superintendent of grains, Süleyman efendi, former agha of the sword keepers Boşnak Mehmed Agha,
        the accountant of the sacred cities, the secretary of the treasury, the tax inspector agha,
        and the tax farmer of the sacred cities.</ab>   
            
    </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>