<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <!-- title of the source -->
            <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über Damien Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsbesuch beim Stellvertreter des Großwesirs,
                Istanbul, 16. April 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of Damien Hugo von Virmont’s farewell visit to the Grand Vizier’s Chief Steward,
                Istanbul, April 16, 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damien Hugo von Virmont’un Sadaret Kethüdası’na veda ziyareti,
                İstanbul, 16 Nisan 1720</title>
            <!-- author of the source -->
            <author>
                <persName>Teşrifati Salman Efendi</persName>
            </author>
            <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
            <respStmt>
                <!-- editor -->
                <resp>Edition</resp>
                <persName xml:id="yy">
                    <forename>Yasir</forename>
                    <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <!-- data modelling-->
                <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Stephan</forename>
                    <surname>Kurz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
                <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/">
                    Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan Studies
                </orgName>
            </publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at">
                    GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset Management System
                </orgName>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
                    Creative Commons BY 4.0
                </licence>
            </availability>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            
            <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200416</idno>
       </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> 
            <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> 
            <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Arno</forename>
                    <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                    <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                    <idno>no. 347, p. 88</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                
                <physDesc>
                  
                </physDesc>
                <history>
                    <origin>
                        <origDate when="1720-04-16"/>
                    </origin>
                </history>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document --> 
        </editorialDecl>
        <projectDesc>
            <ab>
                <ref target="context:vipa" type="context">
                    Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20)
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context">
                    Protokollbücher
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:qhod" type="context">
                    Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918
                </ref>
            </ab>
            <!-- Project description -->
            <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
        </projectDesc>
        <refsDecl>
            <p>
                Protokollregister über Damien Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsbesuch beim Stellvertreter des Großwesirs, Istanbul, 16. April 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
            </p>
        </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
        </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
    
   <surface start="#IMG1">
        <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00043a1.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
    </surface>
    
</facsimile>
                   
<text type="protocol">
<body>
    <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200416">
    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>  
    <ab>
        <hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisinüñ</rs> ketḫüdā beg ḥażretlerine geldigini müşʿirdür.</hi></ab>
        
        <ab>
        <lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-16">Māh-ı mezbūruñ yedinci is̠ neyn güni</date> 
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> saʿādetlü ketḫüdā beg ḥażretlerine gelmekle
            <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs> 
        <lb/>rükūbı içün aġ ır bir raḫt ile müzeyyen bir at ve begzādegānı içün daḫı yigirmi ḳadar 
            <choice><corr>eyer</corr> <sic>eger</sic></choice> kuşanmış atlar
            <lb/>bāġ çe ḳapusına irsāl olunub baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">başdefterdār efendinüñ</rs> yedi çifte ḳayıġ ı ile
        <lb/>iskele-i mezbūra gelüb mevcūd olan atlara süvār, aġ a-yı müşarün ileyhüñ Vālide Ḫānınuñ
        <lb/>alt ṭarafında Boyacılar üzerinde vāḳiʿ ḫānesine sāʿat altıyı tecāvüz iderek nüzūl
        <lb/>idüb</ab>
        
        <ab>
        bāġ çe üzerine nāẓır olan odanuñ ḳapusı ḫāricinde vezīr aġ alarından bir miḳdār
        <lb/>aġ alar ferāce semūr kürkler ile durub ve odanuñ dehlīzine şükūfe ve meyve konub 
        <lb/>ve oṭ anuñ dīvārlarına cā-be-cā āyīneler ve üç ʿaded muṣannaʿ ḳılıç ve bir pala āviḫte olunub
            <lb/>ve bāġ çe cānibinde olan köşenüñ ṣaġ  ṭarafında minder üzerine <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> içün iki iḥrām
            <lb/>ḳonub ḥāżır olmaġ la <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> maḥall-i meẕkūra oturub baʿdehū ketḫüdā beg yeşil çuḳa 
        <lb/>semūr kürk ile <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> daḫı maʿan içerü girdükde</ab>
        
        <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ḳıyām idüb baʿdehū ketḫüdā beg
        <lb/>ṣadra oturub ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ṣol ṭarafına oturub ṭatlu ve ḳahve virildükden ṣoñra
        <lb/>bir miḳdār ṣoḥbet olunub baʿdehū aşaġ ı bāġçedeki fısḳiyeli köşke nüzūl olunub 
        <lb/>ḫānende ve sāzende faṣl eylemişlerdür. Baʿdehū yuḳarı oṭ a-i mezbūra çıḳılub ṭaʿāma 
        <lb/>oturulmışdur. Ketḫüdā beg <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">Dürrī</rs> 
        berāber ekl eylemişlerdür. Baʿdeʾl-ṭaʿām
        <lb/>zīrde defter olunduġ ı üzere hedīyeler virilüb baʿdehū gitmişdür. Begzādegānı muʿtād üzere
        <lb/>iṭʿām olunmışdur.</ab>
        
        <list type="giftlist">
        <item rend="column1">ḳıymetli tüfenk ʿaded 2</item>
        <item rend="column2">aġ ır boyama <supplied resp="#yy">ve</supplied> yaġ lıḳ, ʿaded 2</item>
        <item rend="column3">kemer raḫt ile ve ḳırmızı işleme kesmelü
        ve sīm rikāblu mükemmel ṭaḳımı ile ḳula at, 1</item>
        <item rend="column1">begzādegānına telli çekme, 10</item>
            <item rend="column2"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">Ḳapūcubaşı Meḥmed Aġ aya</rs> ṣof ferāce, libās 1</item> 
        <item rend="column3">teşrīfātçı efendiye çuḳa 1 ḳumāş 1</item>
        <item rend="column4">yeñiçeri ḥāṣekisine çuḳa 1 ḳumāş 1</item>
        <item rend="column1">çorbacıya çuḳa 1 ḳumāş 1</item>
        <item rend="column2">dīvān çavuşlarına altun, ʿaded 6</item></list>  
    </div>
    
    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200416-transl">
    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
        
        <ab>The following relates the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Austrian ambassador’s</rs> visit to the chief steward.</ab>
        
    <ab><date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-16">On the seventh day of the aforementioned month, a Monday</date>, 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> visited his excellency the chief steward.
        For the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> ride,
        a horse equipped with a heavy harness was sent to the garden gate, while for the noblemen
        of the ambassador around twenty saddled horses were dispatched to the garden gate. 
        Embarked on the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">chief treasurer’s</rs> caique powered with seven oarsmen,
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and his noblemen came by the pier where they mounted the horses present there.
        As it was past six o’clock, they entered the agha’s house that was located
        below the Valide Han and above Boyacılar quarter.</ab>

    <ab>Outside the [reception] room’s door overlooking the garden, some aghas
        from among the vizier household were standing, wearing sable furs on
        ceremonial cloaks. Flower and fruit were placed on the passageway leading to the room.
        Mirrors, three jeweled swords, and a machete were hanging in places on the walls
        of the room. On the right-hand side of the corner facing the garden, two covers were
        spread over a cushion for the ambassador. After the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
        had sat down there, the chief steward, wearing a sable
        fur on a green broadcloth cloak, came inside the room together with <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">the chief of the scribes</rs>.</ab>
        
        <ab>Upon their entry to the room, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> rose to his feet and the chief steward
        sat on his seat. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">The chief of the scribes</rs> sat on his left-hand side. After sweets
        and coffee had been served, some conversation took place. 
        Afterwards, the party moved to the fountained pavilion in the lower garden 
        where vocalists and musicians performed. Thereafter, they returned again to
        the upper room where they sat down for a meal.
        The chief steward, <rs type="perosn" ref="#mpr14722">the chief of the scribes</rs>, and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">Dürrī</rs> ate together. 
        After the meal, gifts were presented as recorded below, after which the ambassador left.
        His noblemen was also served a meal according to the custom.</ab>
        
        <list type="giftlist">
            <item rend="column1">precious musket, 2 pieces</item>
            <item rend="column2">colored heavy handkerchief and handkerchief, 2 pieces</item>
            <item rend="column3">A buckskin horse, with a whole set of horse tack, 
                including a leather-strap harness, a red embroidered horse blanket, and silver stirrups
                <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">The ’arched’ saddle or <foreign xml:lang="tr">kemer raḫt</foreign> was likely of lesser value
                than the <foreign xml:lang="tr">dīvān raḫtı</foreign>, the imperial ceremonial saddle that was used as a gear for
                the horses rode by sultans, highest-ranked statesmen, or ambassadors.</note></item>
            <item rend="column1">embroidered fabric to the ambassador’s
                noblemen, 10 pieces</item>
            <item rend="column2">a fine ceremonial cloak to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">Gatekeeper Mehmed Agha</rs>, 1 piece</item> 
            <item rend="column3">a broadcloth and a fabric to the protocol registerer, 1 of each</item>
            <item rend="column4">a broadcloth and a fabric to the janissary lieutenant, 1 of each</item>
            <item rend="column1">a broadcloth and a fabric to the janissary captain, 1 of each</item>
            <item rend="column2">gold coins to the palace ushers, 6 pieces</item></list>
        
    





    </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>