<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Gouverneur von
                    Scutari/Shkodra und an den Richter von Ulcinj/Ulqini, um die
                    Piraterieaktivitäten der Festung Ulcinj zu verhindern; Istanbul, 24. September –
                    4. Oktober 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the governor of the Scutari/Shkodër and to
                    the judge of Ulcinj to prevent the piracy activities of the Ulcinj fortress;
                    Istanbul, September 24 – October 4, 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultan’ın, İşkodra valisi ve Ülgün kadısına hitaben yazılmış,
                    Ülgün kalesi sakinlerinin korsanlık faaliyetlerini engellemeleri hakkında hükmü;
                    İstanbul, 24 Eylül - 4 Ekim, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 68-69, entry 130</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-09-24" notAfter="1719-10-04"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Gouverneur der Scutari/Shkodra und an den
                    Richter von Ulcinj/Ulqini, um die Piraterieaktivitäten der Festung Ulcinj zu
                    verhindern; Istanbul, 24. September – 4. Oktober 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz
                    und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die
                    Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                    habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt
                    1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>about the prevention of piracy in the Adriatic and Mediterranean</item>
                    <item>about the prevention of new ship constructions</item>
                    <item>judge of Scutari / Shkodër</item>
                    <item>judge of Ulcinj</item>
                    <item>piracy</item>
                    <item>corsair</item>
                    <item>korsan</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00033_Page_68_Entry_130_Part1.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG2">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00034_Page_69_Entry_130_Part2.jpg" xml:id="IMG2"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.2">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">130</metamark>

                <ab><lb/>Ber-vech-i arpalıḳ <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15845">İskenderiyye</rs>
                    sancaġına mutaṣarrıf olan dāme iḳbālehūya ve <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15331"
                        >Ülgün</rs> ḳāḍīsına ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile āsitāne-i saʿādetüme gelen <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl <lb/>Ġrūf de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū bi’l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḥāl idüb</ab>

                <ab><rs type="place" ref="#mpr15331">Ülgün</rs> ḳalʿası ahālīsi min baʿd ḳorṣānlıġa
                    <lb/>çıḳmayub tüccār sefīnelerine żarar ve ziyān itmemek içün ellerinde olan
                    firḳate ve sāʾir ḳorṣān <lb/>sefīneleri refʿ ve tüccār sefīnelerine
                    taʿarrużundan külliyyet ile menʿ ve fī mā baʿd inşā itmemek üzere tenbīh olunub
                        <pb n="1" facs="#IMG2"/>
                    <metamark place="margin">69</metamark>
                    <lb/>şöyleki içlerinde ḫilāf-ı fermān-ı hümāyūn ve muġāyir-i ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥ vażʿ
                    u ḥareket ve tüccār sefīnelerine īṣāl-i ḫasārete <lb/>cesāret idenlerüñ nehb ü
                    ġāret eyledükleri emvāl ve eşyā her ne ise girü ṣāḥiblerine istirdāda ve vāḳiʿ
                    olan <lb/>żarar ve ziyān gendülerden tażmīn ve esīr eyledükleri kimesneler daḫī
                    esīrlikden istiḫlāṣ olunub ve bu maḳūle <lb/>eşḳıyānuñ sāʾire mūcib-i ʿibret
                    olmaḳ içün şerʿen lāzım gelen cezāları tertīb oluna diyü müşārün ileyh <lb/><rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafına virilen
                    ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnumuza mesṭūr ve muḳayyed olmaġla mūcebince ʿamel ve ḥareket
                    olunmaḳ içün emr-i <lb/>şerīfüm virilmek bābında istidʿā-yı ʿināyet
                    eylemegin</ab>

                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnum mūcebince şerāʾiṭ-i ṣulḥ u ṣalāḥuñ icrāsı ehemm-i umūr-ı
                    <lb/>devlet-i ʿaliyyemden olmaġla sen ki mīr-i mīrān-ı mūmā ileyh ve mevlānā-yı
                    meẕkūrsın ḥālā <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15331">Ülgün</rs> ḳalʿası ahālīsi min
                    baʿd ḳorsānlıġa <lb/>çıḳmayub tüccār sefīnelerine żarar ve ziyān etmemek içün
                    ellerinde olan firḳat ve sāʾir ḳorsān sefīnelerini <lb/>refʿ ve tüccār
                    sefīnelerinetaʿarrużdan külliyyet ile menʿ ve defʿ ve fī mā baʿd inşā itmemek
                    üzere muḥkem tenbīh ve teʾkīd eyleyesin</ab>

                <ab><lb/>şöyle ki ḫilāf-ı ferman cihān-muṭāʿ ellerinde olan sefīnelerinüñ refʿine
                    muḫālefet ve şerāʾiṭ-i ṣulḥ u ṣalāḥa muġāyir vażʿ <lb/>ve ḥareket iderler ise
                    üzerlerine vüzerā-yı ʿiẓāmumdan biri ʿasker ile taʿyīn ve sāʾire mūcib-i ʿibret
                    olmaḳ içün <gap rend="overstriked"/>
                    <lb/>lāzım gelen cezāları tertīb olunacaġın gendülere geregi gibi tefhīm ve siz
                    daḫī şerāʾiṭ-i ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥuñ mürāʿātında ve fermān-ı <lb/>celīlü l-ʿunvānumuñ
                    tenfīẕ ve icrāsında taḳayyüd-i tāmm eyleyüb tehāvün ve taḳṣīrden be-ġāyet
                    iḥtirāz ve ictīnāb eylemeñüz bābında <lb/>fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur
                    buyurdum ki.</ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">fī evāsıṭ-ı Ẕā
                            [<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied>] sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.2.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>
                <ab>Decree to the person who is the governor of the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15845"
                        >Scutari</rs> district by way of stipend (<foreign xml:lang="ota">arpalıḳ</foreign>) and to the judge of <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15331">Ulcinj</rs>:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my threshold of felicity as grand
                    ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a petition to
                    my felicitious threshold. He made an official request about [the
                    following matter]:</ab>

                <ab>The residents of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15331">Ulcinj</rs> shall not go on
                    maritime raids from now on. The light galleys and other corsair ships in their possession
                    shall be removed so as not to harm and damage merchant ships; they shall be absolutely
                    prohibited from attacking merchant ships, and they shall be warned not to build
                    [ships] henceforward. <pb n="1" facs="#IMG2"/> Now, what assets and goods have
                    been plundered and pillaged by those among them who act and behave in violation
                    of the imperial edict–daring to inflict injuries to merchant ships in opposition
                    to the peace and amity–shall be returned. The damage and loss
                    caused shall be compensated by them and the prisoners they took shall be freed
                    from captivity. It is written and recorded in our imperial letter of agreement
                        (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>) that was given to the
                    aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> that, to
                    make this a lesson for others, these kinds of brigands shall be punished as
                    prescribed by Islamic law. [The grand ambassador requested] the issuance of my
                    blessed order about acting and to go about as required.</ab>

                <ab>The execution of the peace conditions and reconciliation–as required by my
                    imperial letter of agreement–is one of the important matters of my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs>.
                    You are the aforesaid governor of governors and you are the aforesaid
                    judge! You [two] shall warn and reiterate firmly so that henceforward the <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15331">Ulcinj</rs> fortress shall not sail for piracy;
                    the light galleys and other piracy ships in their possession shall be removed so
                    that they may not harm and damage merchant ships; and, from now on, they shall
                    be absolutely prohibited and averted from attacking merchant ships and not to
                    build [new ones].</ab>

                <ab>That is to say, in violation of the edict obeyed by the whole world, if they
                    oppose the removal of the ships in their possession and act and behave contrary
                    to the conditions of peace and reconciliation, one of my grand viziers will be
                    appointed to march on them with troops, and the required punishments will be
                    executed in order to make that a lesson for others. You shall explain that to
                    them as required. My illustrious edict has been issued that you too shall
                    display perfect attention in obeying the conditions of peace and reconciliation
                    and the implementation and execution of my glorious edict. You shall diligently
                    avoid and beware of negligence and shortcomings. So have <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> commanded!</ab>




                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">September 25 to
                        October 4, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
