<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den kommandierenden Vezier von
                    Nissa (Niš) und andere osmanische Verwalter entlang der Route von Istanbul zur
                    österreichischen Grenze über den Schutz und die gute Behandlung von zwei
                    Kapitänleutnants (Kurieren), ihren Dienern und Tieren während ihrer Reise zur
                    Grenze; Istanbul, 14. November – 23. November 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the commander vizier of Nissa (Niš) and
                    other Ottoman administrators situated on the road from Istanbul to the Austrian
                    border about the protection and good treatment of two captain-lieutenants, their
                    servants, and animals during their journey to the border; Istanbul, November 14
                    – November 23, 1719</title>


                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Niş vezirine ve İstanbul’dan Avusturya sınırına kadar
                    yol boyunca bulunan Osmanlı idarecilerine hitaben yazılmış, sınıra seyahat eden
                    iki haberci subayın, adamlarının ve hayvanlarının korunması ve onlara iyi
                    muamele edilmesi hakkında hükmü; İstanbul, 14 Kasım – 23 Kasım, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.1719114-17191123</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 72, entry 143</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-11-14" notAfter="1719-11-23"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p> Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Kommandanten Vezier von Nissa (Niš) und
                    andere osmanische Verwalter entlang der Route von Istanbul zur österreichischen
                    Grenze über über den Schutz und die gute Behandlung von zwei Kapitänleutnants
                    (Kurieren), ihren Dienern und Tieren während ihrer Reise zur Grenze; Istanbul,
                    14. November – 23. November 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu,
                    Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften
                    Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer
                    und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>protection of traveling Austrian merchant according to the conditions of
                        the imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>Asitane-i saadet (Istanbul)</item>
                    <item>Nissa (Niš)</item>
                    <item>Austrian couriers</item>
                    <item>Austrian border</item>
                    <item>protection</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00035_Page_72_Entry_143.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <!--<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı vezīre</rs>Abdullah Pasha
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Wien</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Buda</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9372">Erdel</rs>-->


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.1719114-17191123">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">143</metamark>

                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">vezīr</rs>ine ve <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādetüm</rs>den <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718"
                        >Nemçe</rs> ḥudūdına varınca <lb/>yol üzerinde vāḳiʿ olan ḳāḍīlara ve
                    ketḫüdā yirleri ve yeñiçeri <lb/>serdārları ve aʿyān-ı vilāyet ve iş erlerine
                    ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile <lb/>der-i devlet-medāruma gelen
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū <lb/>bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü mektūb gönderüb</ab>

                <ab>bundan aḳdem <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Beç</rs> ṭarafından <lb/>gelen <rs
                        type="person">Brinc Ḥolerculerñ</rs>(?) nām iki nefer ḳapūdān vekīlleri
                    <lb/>ḥālā girü <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Beç</rs> ṭarafına ʿavdet ve
                    recʿat üzere ādamlarıyla <lb/>mesfūrlar ve yanlarında olan ḫidmetkārları ve
                    iştirā <lb/>eyledükleri on yedi reʾs atlarıyla her ḳangıñuzuñ taḥt-ı
                    <lb/>ḥükūmet ve ḳażāsına varub dāḫil olurlar ise esnā-yı rāhde <lb/>menāzil ve
                    merāḥilde gendülerine ve ḫidmetkārlarına ve esvāb <lb/>ve atlarına daḫl ve
                    taʿarruż ve mürūrlarına mümānaʿat ve sāʾir aḳça muṭālebesiyle <lb/>kimesneye
                    rencīde itdürilmeyüb emīn u sālim birbiriñüze īṣāle <lb/>taḳayyüd ve iḥtimām
                    eylemek bābında ḥükm-i hümāyūnum ricā eylemegin vech-i <lb/>meşrūḥ üzere ʿamel
                    olunmaḳ bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır <lb/>olmışdur buyurdum ki. <note
                        xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">It appears that there was a
                        translation problem on the Ottoman side in the writing of this order or at
                        least a lack of attention to details which is reflected in the wording of
                        the text. The Turkish text reads "two captain-lieutenants named Prinz
                        Holerculer." Obviously, two captain-lieutenants cannot be the same person.
                        Also, a prince would not have traveled to the Ottoman capital without due
                        ceremonies. In reality, as we learn from <ref
                            target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723/sdef:TEI/get?mode=view:read#page279"
                            >the travelogue of Cornelius von den Driesch</ref>, the
                            <foreign>prince</foreign> mentioned here was Friedrich Wilhelm, the
                        Prince of Hohenzollern who was an imperial Field Marshal in the Habsburg
                        army at the time. The two captain-lieutenants were two couriers from his
                        cuirassier regiment. These two men, &gt;whose names the secretary Driesch
                        did not mention, had arrived in Istanbul on between September 6 and 8 and
                        had brought letters from Germany. Driesch noted that one of these
                        lieutenants had spent a long time as a prisoner in the Ottoman lands and
                        could speak very good Turkish. For the note about their departure, see
                        Driesch, <ref
                            target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723/sdef:TEI/get?mode=view:read#page291"
                            >p. 291</ref>.</note></ab>





                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-11-14" notAfter="1719-11-23">fī evāil-i
                        Muḥarrem sene 1132</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.1719114-17191123.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>
                <ab>Decree to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">vizier</rs> of <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14602">Nissa (Niš)</rs> and to the judges, aides-de-camp of
                    janissary commanders, janissary commanders, provincial notables, and
                    functionaries situated on the road from my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055"
                        >threshold of felicity</rs> to the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718"
                        >Austrian</rs> border:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as
                    grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>,
                    the paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my threshold of felicity and requested my imperial decree [about the
                    following matter]:</ab>

                <ab>Two captain-lieutenants [from the prince] named <rs type="person">Brinc
                        Holerculern</rs>(?) who formerly came from <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416"
                        >Vienna</rs> are now going and returning to <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr13416">Vienna</rs> along with their men, their servants, and
                    seventeen horses that they purchased. When they arrive and enter the
                    administrative territory and town of whomever among you, themselves, their
                    servants, garments, and horses shall not be interfered with and attacked during
                    the journey, at stations, and at stages of the journey. Their passing shall not
                    be prevented. No one shall be allowed to injure them with claims of a variety of
                    fees. Each of you shall pay attention and take great care of delivering them
                    safe and sound from one of you to the other. My illustrious edict has been
                    issued for [all] to act in the described way. So have I commanded!<ref
                        target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/></ab>




                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-11-14" notAfter="1719-11-23">November 14 to
                        November 23, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
