<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über die Audienz von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Ahmed III. im Topkapı-Palast
                    und die Liste von Geschenken an Sultan, Istanbul, 8. August, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of the audience of Damian Hugo von Virmont with Ahmed III at Topkapı Palace
                    and the list of gifts presented to the sultan, Istanbul, August 8, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un 3. Ahmed’in huzuruna kabulü ve 
                    sultana sunduğu hediyelerin listesi, İstanbul, 8 Ağustos 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName> Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi </persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>

                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17190808</idno>
                <!-- PID: o:[context].[genre].[language].[date-iso](.[nr])
    # context: 
        vipa for Virmont/Ibrahim Paşa 1719-1720
        qhod ıs outdated, it's only used for the meta context that aggregates the different edition subparts.
# genres:
ad. administrative document
ch. chronicle
in. instruction
l. letter
mh. mühimme
np. newspaper
pr. protocol register
pp. pamphlet
pt. petition
rc. record (Urkunde)
re. receipt
rp. report (Bericht, Relation)
tr. travelogue
# languages:
osm. ottoman source
hbg. habsburg source
# date:
yyyy-mm-dd or yyyy
we use the first known date of creation for handwritten texts 
and for printed ones the date of publication
# nr:
ONLY if a PID would duplicate (e.g. two habsburg letters on the same date) -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title ref="http://gams.uni-graz.at/qhod"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                    habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <!-- Archive, Library,… -->
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 56-57</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="scribe1">
                                <persName ref="#mpr13114">Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi</persName>
                                <desc><!-- e.g. Written in red ink --></desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1719-08-08"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Encoding guidelines -->
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister über die Audienz von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Ahmed III. im Topkapı-Palast und die Liste von Geschenken an Sultan, Istanbul, 8. August, 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG01">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00027a.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG02">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00027b.jpg" xml:id="IMG02"/>
        </surface>
        </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190808">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
            
            <ab><hi rend="#red">Nemçe <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>sinüñ dīvān-ı hümāyūna geldigini müşʿirdür</hi>. 
                Fī <date type="Hijri" when="1719-08-08">22 <supplied resp="#yy">Ramaza</supplied>n sene 1131</date></ab>
                
                <note resp="#yy" place="paragraph" xml:id="ftn1"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page183">
                    The Austrian secretary C. Driesch described the audience with the sultan</ref> in the third chapter of the second book.</note>
                
                <ab><lb/>Yevm-i mezbūrda ġ alebe dīvānı olub ḳul ṭāyifesine iki ḳaṭ
                <lb/>mevācib virilmekle <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe Çāsārı</rs> ṭarafından ṣ ulḥnāme ile gelen
                <lb/>kebīr <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı dīvān-ı hümāyūna gelüb nāme ve hedāyāsın teṣlīm eylemekle
                <lb/>ẕikr olunur.</ab>
                             
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435̄">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs>uñ hedāyāsı 
                    bir gün muḳ addem sarāy-ı hümāyūna
                <lb/>getürilüb dārüʾl-saʿāde aġ asınuñ müsāfir odası cānibinde 
                <lb/>mermer direkler saḳfınıñ altına ḳonub ve eṭrā fına zuḳā ḳ çekilüb 
                <lb/>muḥāfaẓa olunmışdur.</ab> 
            
            <ab>Ve irtesi yevm-i mezbūrda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi begüñ</rs> rükūbı içün 
                <lb/>muʿtād üzere ḫāss āḫurdan dīvān raḫtıyla bir at ve begzādegān
                <lb/>ve etbāʿı içün daḫı yüz otuz ruʾs eġ erlenmiş atlar irsāl ve çavuşbaşı
                <lb/>dīvān-ı hümāyūn üslūbı üzere ve çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve ḳırḳ elli
                <lb/>nefer mücevvezelü çavuşān ile varub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūrı</rs> alay ile sarāy-ı hümāyūna
                <lb/>getürüb dergāh-ı ʿā lī yeñiçerileri şorbaya segirdecekleri zemān içerü ḳoyub
                <lb/>seyr ve temāşā iderek ḳubbe ḳapusına ḳalḳub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> derūn-i ḳubbeye 
                <lb/>dāḫıl olub Nişāncı Paşanuñ alt ṭarafında vażʿ olunan iskemleye
                <lb/>oturduḳdan ṣ oñra</ab>
                    
             <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥ ib devlet</rs> efendimüz daḫı teşrīf buyurduḳlarında vüzerāʾ-i
                 <lb/>ʿiẓām ve sāyirleri ḳıyām <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı ḳıyām idüb maḳām-ı ʿālīlerine
                <lb/>oturdılar.</ab> 
                
            <ab>Bir <choice><corr>cüzʾīce</corr><sic>cüzvʾīce</sic></choice> 
                    teʾḫīrden ṣoñra ṣāhib-i devlet fermānı ile 
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiniñ</rs> iskemlesi bir iki adım daḫı yuḳ aru nişāncıya ḳarīb ḳodılar.
                <lb/>Baʿdehū dīvān ḳurılub meṣāliḥ-i ʿibād görüldükden ṣoñra ʿulūfe kīseleri 
                <lb/>ḳubbe altına yıġ ılmaġ a başladıḳda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> bā-fermān-ı ʿālī iskemleden
                <lb/>ḳaldurılub nişā ncı paşanuñ oturduġ ı ṭūlānī ṣofaya vezīr-i
                <lb/>müşārün ileyhüñ alt ṭarafına oturtdılar.</ab>
                
                <note resp="#yy" type="footnote" xml:id="ftn2"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page207">
                    According to C. Driesch</ref>, a little while after the audience began,
                    the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador Virmont</rs>  made a direct complaint
                    to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs>about the position
                    and height of his seat. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Virmont</rs>, through the Austrian interpreter, asked why his seat was positioned 
                    where it was and argued that, as the imperial ambassador, he was of equal
                    rank to a vizier of three horsetail standards, that is, a minister of first rank,
                    and that he had to sit on the same bench where the ministers of first rank sat. 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">The grand vizier</rs> responded that
                    decreasing the rank of the imperial ambassador was not the intention; the seat was 
                    positioned where it was only for convenience so that the ambassador could observe everything 
                    that was in progress better. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat next to the Ottoman chancellor
                    after this complaint.</note>
                
                <ab>ʿUlūfe tevzīʿ olunub temām
                <lb/>olunduḳdan ṣoñra muʿtād üzere rūznāmeci ve baş bāġ çı ḳulı ve sāyir ḫilʿat
                <lb/>giymesi muʿtād olanlara ḫilʿatler ilbās olunduḳdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi 
                    mezbūr</rs> çavuşbaşı aġ a
                <lb/>ḳaldurub <corr>ḫ</corr><sic>ḥ</sic>azīne öniñe götürdükde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiye</rs>
                    ḳaraca yeñlü serāser ḳaplu kürk semūr 
                <lb/>ve etbāʿına daḫı yüz on altı miḳdārı ḫilʿatler ilbās olunub eski dīvānḫāne 
                <lb/>öñinde vüzerāʾ-i ʿiẓāmıñ ʿarż a girmesine tevaḳḳuf olunmışdur.</ab> 
                
            <ab>Yevm-i mezbūr 
                <lb/>Ramażān-ı şerīf olmaġ la <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> kendisine ṭaʿām virilmeyüb lākin begzādegān
                <lb/>eski dīvānḫānede ve etbāʿı ḳızlar ḳapusı semtinde olan direkler arasında
                
                    <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>
                
                <lb/>iṭʿām olunmışdur. Baʿdehū vüzerā-ʾi ʿiẓām ḥużūr-i hümāyūna varduḳdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi 
                    <lb/>mezbūr</rs> daḫı gitdi ve tercümān ve begzādegānı ile mecmuʿı on altı nefer ādem ʿarż a
                <lb/>ḳonmışdur.</ab>
                
                <note resp="#yy" type="footnote" xml:id="ftn3"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page205">
                    C. Driesch recorded a copy of the speech delivered by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                    in the presence of the sultan.</ref> The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> delivered the emperor’s letter along
                with a Turkish translation made by one of the Austrian interpreters. See Driesch, page 206.</note>
                
            <ab>Baʿdehū çıḳub orta ḳapudan ṭaşra at üzerinde ṭurub erbāb-i
                <lb/>dīvān biʾl-cümle çıḳınca seyr itdürilmişdür. Çavuşbaşı ʿavdetde gitmemişdür. Ancaḳ
                <lb/>çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve çavuşlar ve üzerine meʾmūr olan aġ alar ile
                <lb/>gitmişdür.</ab>
                
               <lb/><ab><hi rend="#red">Nemçe ilçisinüñ rikāb-ı hümāyūn-u şevket-maḳrūna 
                    getürdigi hedāyāsıdur.</hi></ab>
                
               <list type="giftlist">
                    <item rend="column1">İkişer mūm ḳonacaḳ şemʿ-dānlı, on iki aṣma dīvār āyīneleriyle 
                        başları ve kenār ve pervāzları āyīne ḳaplama kebīr endām aynası, ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Sibāḳ-ı mezbūr üzere başları ve kenārları ve pervāzları sīm 
                        ḳaplu kebīr endām āyīnesi, ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Sīm şükūfedān, ʿaded 6</item>
                    <item rend="column2">İkilü lehli sīm muṣluḳ, ʿaded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Ḳahve ve çay ṭabḫ idecek ikilü lehli sīm furun, ʿaded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Yaldızlu sīm maṭara maʿa zincīr, ʿaded 6</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Kebīr yaldızlu sīm legen ibrīk,̣ ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Kebīr sīm buhūrdān, ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Siperleri sīm ḳaplama Dımeşḳī ocaḳ, temūrī ve depeleri 
                        sīm ve kilīdi ve maşa ve kürek, ṭaḳım 1</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Aṣma ḳalḳan resminde sīm sāʿat, ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Ṣofra ṭaḳımı sīm, barca 28</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Yedişer mūm ḳonacaḳ kebīr sīm şemʿ-dān, ʿaded 6</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Sīm legen maʿa ṭas, ʿaded 12</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Sīm ḳahve ibriġi, ʿaded 3</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Kebīr sīm sini, ̣aded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Ḳalaylu sīm <unclear reason="illegible">?</unclear>, ʿaded 2</item>
                    <item rend="column4">Billūr ayna avīzesi yalduzlu sīm şem-dān, ʿaded 12</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Billūr ve sīm şemʿ-dānlı aṣma, billūr şemʿ-dān, ʿaded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Erġ anūn çalar kebīr sīm sāʿat, ʿaded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column3">Servī resminde kebīr sīm sāʿat, ʿaded 1</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Beç zerbaftı ṭob, ʿaded 12</item>
                    <item rend="column2">Altı mūm ḳonacaḳ aṣma sīm şemʿ-dān, ʿaded 1</item>
                </list> 
                <p>
                <note resp="#yy" type="footnote" xml:id="ftn4"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page207">
                    The Austrian secretary C. Driesch noted in his travelogue
                </ref> that, following the audience, these gifts were
                    sold publicly. C. Driesch claimed that
                    the French ambassador purchased some of the items for himself.</note></p>
                
            </div>  
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190808-transl">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
                
            <ab><hi rend="#red">A report of the Austrian ambassador’s audience at the imperial council</hi>
                 on August 8, 1719.<ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/>
            </ab>
                
                <!--<note resp="#yy" place="paragraph"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page183">
                    The Austrian secretary C. Driesch described the audience with the sultan
                </ref> in the third chapter of the second book.</note>-->
                 
                <ab>On this day, a festive imperial council meeting for the payment of janissary salaries (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ġ alebe dīvānı</foreign>)
                was organized and the Janissaries were paid double salary. 
                The following mentions this occasion, when  <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the grand ambassador</rs>, sent by the Austrian emperor
                with a peace settlement, also came to the imperial council and delivered his gifts.</ab>
                
            <ab>The gifts of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> were brought to the palace the previous day and placed under the roof of
                the colonnade next to the guest room of the agha of the abode of felicity (the chief eunuch) and [they] were 
                protected with an enclosure.</ab>
                
            <ab>The next day, a horse from the imperial stables equipped with an imperial ceremonial harness
                was sent–as usual–for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> ride, while one-hundred-and-thirty saddled horses had been sent for his inner circle 
                and [his] entourage. The agha, the secretary, the intendant of the palace ushers,
                and forty to fifty palace ushers wearing <foreign xml:lang="tr">mücevveze</foreign>s (a turban of many plaited folds) went,
                as is the custom of the imperial council, and fetched the aforementioned <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                with a cortege to the imperial palace.
                The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was brought in as the palace janissaries were about <q>to dash to the soup</q>
                (<foreign xml:lang="tr">şorbaya segirdecekleri zemān</foreign>)  which the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                watched and gazed at. Next, he moved to the gate of the dome (imperial council room), entered 
                the council room and sat on the stool arranged below the chancellor.</ab> 
                
            <ab>Then, as our lord the grand vizier, honored the room by his entry, the viziers and the others stood up
                as well as the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, and the grand vizier sat on his exalted post. Following a brief delay, 
                on the orders of the grand vizier, the stool of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was raised a few steps higher
                closer to the chancellor. Next, the imperial council meeting took place and the affairs of the subjects
                were taken care of. As the salary purses were being shared inside the imperial council room,
                on the orders of the grand vizier, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was raised from the stool where he was sitting
                and [he was] offered a seat on the longitudinal sofa to the lower side of the chancellor.
                <ref target="#ftn2" type="note_reference"/>
            </ab>
                
<!--                <note resp="#yy" type="footnote"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page207">
                    According to C. Driesch</ref>, a little while after the audience began,
                    the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador Virmont</rs>  made a direct complaint
                    to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs>about the position
                    and height of his seat. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Virmont</rs>, through the Austrian interpreter, asked why his seat was positioned 
                    where it was and argued that, as the imperial ambassador, he was of equal
                    rank to a vizier of three horsetail standards, that is, a minister of first rank,
                    and that he had to sit on the same bench where the ministers of first rank sat. 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">The grand vizier</rs> responded that
                    decreasing the rank of the imperial ambassador was not the intention; the seat was 
                    positioned where it was only for convenience so that the ambassador could observe everything 
                    that was in progress better. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat next to the Ottoman chancellor
                    after this complaint.</note>
-->                
            <ab>After the salaries had been completely paid, the guilds of bookkeepers and chief viticulturers
                and others that are customarily dressed were dressed with robes of honor. After that, the agha of the palace ushers
                took the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and brought him in front
                of the treasury where the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was dressed with
                a sable fur ornamented with silk, gold, and silver threads and with roe deer sleeves. His entourage
                was dressed with one-hundred-and-sixteen robes of honor. Then, the entry of the viziers of the imperial council
                into the sultan’s presence was sojourned in front of the old imperial council meeting room.</ab>
                
             <ab>Since that day was a day of the glorious Ramadan, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> himself was not served a meal,
                 but his inner circle were given food inside the old reception room while the rest of his entourage
                 were served food under the columns next to the harem gate. <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/> 
                 Then, the viziers entered the sultan’s presence, followed by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, 
                 his interpreter, and his inner circle–who all together made sixteen persons.
                 
                 <note resp="#yy" type="footnote"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page205">
                     C. Driesch recorded a copy of the speech delivered by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                     in the presence of the sultan.</ref> The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> delivered the emperor’s letter along
                     with a Turkish translation made by one of the Austrian interpreters. See Driesch, <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page205">page 206.</ref></note>
                 
                 Then, they came outside and stood still on horseback outside the middle gate and 
                 watched until all the members of the <foreign xml:lang="tr">dīvān</foreign> came outside. The agha of palace ushers
                 did not accompany [them] during the return; yet, the secretary and the intendant of the palace ushers and ushers 
                 along with other aghas commissioned with the duty went.
                 
                 <hi rend="red">The gifts <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the Austrian ambassador</rs> brought to the imperial majestic stirrup:</hi>
                 
                <list type="giftlist">
                    <item rend="column1">full-length cheval mirror with top, edges, and fringes covered in mirror (glass?),
                        together with twelve wall-mounted mirrors, each with an attached chandelier of two candle holders, 
                        2 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">full-length, large mirror of the same style, fringes covered
                    in silver, 2 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column1">flower vase, silver, 6 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">double-headed soldered faucet, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column3">soldered, double silver stove for cooking coffee and tea, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column1">gilded silver flask with chain, 6 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">large, silver lacquered basin [and] pitcher </item>
                    <item rend="column3">large, silver thurible</item>
                    <item rend="column1">Damascus style stove with silver-lacquered fire screens, with silver[-lacquered?] iron and tops,
                    along with lock, log tongs, and shovel, 1 full set</item>
                    <item rend="column2">silver hanging clock with a shield-like shape, 2 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column1">silver tableware set, 28 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">large silver chandelier with seven candle holders, 6 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column3">silver basin and a bowl, 12 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column1">silver coffee pitcher, 3 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">large silver tray, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column3">tinned silver <unclear reason="illegible">?</unclear>, 2 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column4">silver chandelier with crystal, gilded candle holders, 12 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column1">crystal hanging chandelier, with crystal and silver candle holders, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column2">large silver clock playing organ (sound), 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column3">large silver clock with a cypress-tree shape, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column1">rolls of Viennese cloth woven in gold, 12 pieces</item>
                    <item rend="column2">silver hanging chandelier with six candle holders, 1 piece
                        <ref target="#ftn3" type="note_reference"/>
                    </item>
                    
                </list>
                 
                 <!--<note resp="#yy" type="footnote"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page207">
                     The Austrian secretary C. Driesch noted in his travelogue
                 </ref> that, following the audience, these gifts were
                     sold publicly. C. Driesch claimed that
                     the French ambassador purchased some of the items for himself.</note>
               -->
               
            </ab>
                 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>