<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://qhod.acdh-dev.oeaw.ac.at/gamsdev/qhod/schema/qhod_volledition.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Letter of Grand Vizier Ibrahim Pasha to Prince Eugene, confirming the letter of recall 
                    for the imperial grand ambassador Graf von Virmont, Istanbul, April 21, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="de">Großwesir Damad Ibrahim Pascha an Prinz Eugen als Rück-Beglaubigungsschreiben (Rekreditiv) für 
                den kaiserlichen Großbotschafter Graf von Virmont, Konstantinopel, 21. April 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Vezir-i Azam İbrahim Paşa’nın Prens Evgen’e hitaben yazdığı, imparatorluk 
                büyük elçisi Graf von Virmont’un geri çağırılma mektubuna cevabı, İstanbul, 21 Nisan 1720</title>

                <author><persName>Grand Vizier Nevşehirli Ibrahim Pasha</persName></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Jakob</forename>
                        <surname>Sonnberger</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan
                    Studies</publisher>
                <distributor>Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan
                    Studies</distributor>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>CC-BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.l.osm.1720421</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>HHStA, Wien</institution>
                        <collection>Turkische Urkunden 12</collection>
                        <idno>Folio 1720-IV-21, "Damad Ibrahim Pascha an Prinz Eugen"</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 Seite</p>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/1018616411">Grand Vizier Nevşehirli Ibrahim Pasha</persName>
                    <date when="1720-04-21">1720-04-21</date>
                    <placeName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://sws.geonames.org/745044/">Istanbul</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118605941">Prinz Eugen</persName>
                    <placeName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://sws.geonames.org/2761369/ https://sws.geonames.org/2761369/">Vienna</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Osmanisches Türkisch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Once we have a serious documentation of our encoding guidelines, we have to
                    reference them here.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.l" type="context"> Briefe </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Großwesir Damad Ibrahim Pascha an Prinz Eugen als Rück-Beglaubigungsschreiben (Rekreditiv) für den kaiserlichen Großbotschafter Graf von Virmont, Konstantinopel, 21. April 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.</p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="IMG_20200921_114124.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div type="transcription" xml:id="vipa.l.osm.1720421">
            <pb facs="#IMG1" n="00241"/>
                <metamark function="archival"><lb/>468</metamark>
            
                <ab type="Inscriptio/Elkab">
                    <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">İftiḫārü’l-ümerāʾi’l-ʿiẓāmi’l-ʿĪseviyye, mümtāzü’l-küberāʾi’l-fiḫāmi’l-mesīḥiyye,
                     ḥürmetlü, haşmetlü Romā İmparāṭorınuñ
                     <lb/>başvekīli riʿāyetlü, raġbetlü, meveddetlü dostumuz 
                    Prenc Evgīnūs dö Ṣāvūye</rs></ab> 
                
                    <ab type="Salutatio/Dua">ṣavb-ı raġbet-medār-ı bāhirü’l-iʿtibārlarına                    
                        <lb/>müʾekked-esās-ı meveddet  ve müsālemet ve müşeyyed-bünyān-ı muṣāfāt ve müʾāneset olan
                    ḫülāṣā-ı kelām ḫātır-nevāz
                    <lb/>meveddet-üslūb ve nakāve-i peyām-ı dostāne-i müṣādaḳat-maṣḥūb iblāġıyla ḥāl ve 
                    ḫāṭırları suʾāl olunub
                    <lb/>dāʾīmā iyilik ve ṣaġlıḳları mesʾūlümüz idügi ifāde olunduḳdan ṣoñra</ab> 
                        
                    <ab type="Notificatio">muḥibbāne inhā 
                    olunan budur ki:
                    </ab> 
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">Benüm
                    <lb/>mezīd-i raġbetlü ve ḥürmetlü dostum <gap unit="char" extent="2"/>
                    ifti<supplied resp="#yy">ḫā</supplied>ru mülūk-ı naṣārā ve efḫamu ḥükümdārān-ı mülk-ārā
                    olan ulu dostumuz
                    <lb/>ḥaşmetlü ḥürmetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">çāsār-ı bā-vaḳār</rs> ḥażretleri ṭarafından nāme-i ṣadāḳat-ʿalāmeleriyle
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet-āşiyāne-i
                    <lb/>şehinşāhīye</rs> teşyīd-i ḳavāʿid-i muṣālaḥat ve teʾkīd-i muʿāḳıd-ı muʾāneset
                    içün resm-i ḳadīm üzere baʿs̱  ve irsāl 
                    <lb/>olunan piyādegānbaşı mümtāz ve münteḫab ve müsteşār ve muʿteber büyükilçileri ḳıdvetü
                    ümerāʾ-i’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye 
                    <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf dö Virmond</rs> ḫayr-ḫᵛāhıñuz yediyle ṭarafıñuzdan 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">cānib-i ṣadīḳuñuza</rs> 
                    irsāl olunan mektūb-ı merġūbıñuz 
                    <lb/>gelüb vāṣıl olub </ab> 
                
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">mażmūn-ı müṣādaḳat-nümūnında bu iki devlet arasında müceddeden münʿaḳid
                    olub ṭarafeynden
                    <lb/>ʿahdnāmeler ile taṣdīk ve ʿuhūd ve mevās̱īḳ ile teʾkīd ḳılınan ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥuñ şerāyiṭine
                    ḳoñşuluḳ
                    <lb/>ve hemcivārlıḳ ḥuḳūḳına riʿāyet ve ḥürmet aḳṣā-yı maḳāṣıdıñuz olmaġla </ab><ab>gerek dostluḳ ve
                    müsāleme şerāyiṭine
                    <lb/>müteʿallıḳ ve gerek berren ve baḥren ve nehren ticāret umūrına müterettib şürūṭ ve ḳuyūda
                    bilā-taġyīr mürāʿāt ve ḫilāf ve şiḳāḳdan 
                    <lb/>ictināb olunmaḳ içün memālik-i çāṣāriyye ve serḥaddlar żābıṭānına muḥkem tenbīh ve teʾkīd
                    olunduġın derc                    
                    <lb/>ve işʿār</ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"> ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mūmā ileyh</rs>
                    daḫı biʾl-cümle taḥrīrātıñuzı taṣdīk ve ḥüsn-i sülūk ve bu mübārek muṣāfaḥanuñ
                    <lb/>şerāyiṭine riʿāyet ile reʿāyā-yı ṭarafeynüñ emn ve rāḥatına ihtimāmıñuzı taḳrīr itmekle
                    fevḳe’l-ḥadd maḥẓūẓ olunub
                    <lb/>ṭaraf-ı iḫlāṣ-kārıñuzdan daḫı dostluḳ ve ḫayır-ḫᵛāhlıġıñuza muvāfıḳ ve muṣāfāt ve müsāleme
                    <lb/>merāsimine şürūṭ ve ḳuyūdı ile icrāda diḳḳat olunub ve 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mūmā ileyh</rs> teblīġine meʾmūr
                    olduġı 
                    <lb/>nāme-i muṣādaḳat-ʿalāme ve pīşkeş ve hedāyāyı ḳāʿide-i ḳadīme-i ʿos̱mānī ve 
                    dīr<supplied resp="#yy">ī</supplied>ne-i müstedīme-i cihānbānī 
                    <lb/>üzere <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14841">rikāb-ı müsteṭāb-ı şehinşāhīye</rs> teblīġ ve teslīm ve teşrīfāt-ı pādişāhāne ile
                    <lb/>ikrām ve talṭīf olundıġından māʿadā der-i devlet-medārda meks̱ ve iḳāmeti eyyāmında
                    izdiyād-ı dostluġıñuza
                    <lb/>raġbeten <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">bu ḫayr-endīşiñüz ṭarafından</rs> daḫı merāsim-i müḥimm-sāzī ve ḫāṭır-nevāzīlerine ihtimām
                    olunub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mūmā ileyḥiñ</rs>
                    <lb/>daḫı eṭvār-ı pesendīde ve her vech ile ʿāḳılāne ve muʾeddebāne ḥarekāt ve revişi ve ṭarafeynüñ
                    ḥüsn-i rıżāsı
                    <lb/>celbine saʿy ve kūşişi nümāyān ve izdiyād-ı müvālāt cānibine ihtimām ve ḫayır-ḫᵛāhlıġı ẓāhir
                    ve ʿayān
                    <lb/>olmaḳdan nāşī eslāfından ziyāde merʿī ve mükerrem ve ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnda olan mevāddan 
                    fażla
                    <lb/>nice mültemesine müsāʿade ile muṭayyeb ve muhterem ḳılınub </ab> 
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">ve umūr-i risāleti daḫı ke-mā yenbaġī
                    edā ve tetmīm ve ʿuhde-i ihtimāmına
                    <lb/>iḥāle ḳılınan dostluḳ ve müṣāfāt merāsimini iki devletüñ şānına lāyıḳ ve ʿahdnāmelere 
                    muvāfıḳ
                    <lb/>vech üzere mürāʿāt ve tekmīl idüb ʿavd ve inṣirāfına iẕn ve ruḫṣat ṭaleb itmegin tekrār 
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14984">dīvān-ı
                    <lb/>bülend-eyvān-ı şehriyārī</rs> ve ḥużūr-i lāmiʿu’nūr-ı tācdārīde teşrīfāt-ı fāḫire-i muʿtāde ile 
                    iktisāb-ı 
                    <lb/>müfāḫeret </ab> <ab>ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">cānib-i cenāb-ı meʿālīmdār-ı cihāndāriden</rs>
                        ḥaşmetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">çāsār-ı bā-vaḳār</rs> ḥażretleri ṭarafına şeref-i ṣüdūr
                    <lb/>bulan name-i hümāyūn-ı meveddet-meşhūn ve musālemet-maḳrūn ile ʿavdet ve ricʿate iẕn ve
                    ruḫṣat-ı cihānbānī
                        <lb/>erzānī ve ʿināyet ḳılınmaġla mektūb-ı meveddet taḥrīr ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mūmā</rs> ileyh ile 
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">ṭarafıñuza</rs> firistāde ḳılınmışdur.</ab>
                  
                        
                <ab type="Dispositio/Hüküm"><lb/>Lede’l-vuṣūl bi-ḥamdi’llāhi teʿālā <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">sizüñ</rs> 
                        ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">bizüm</rs> saʿy ve ihtimāmımuz ile bu iki devlet
                    miyānında tecdīd<cb/>
                    
                    <lb/>ve kemāl-i istiḥkām ile teʾkīd ve teşyīd olunan ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥ ile ṭarafeynüñ reʿāyāsına 
                    <lb/>emniyet ḥāṣıl ve ʿasākir-i devleteyne daḫı istirāḥat şāmil olmaġla bu ḫayırlu muṣālāḥanuñ
                    <lb/>şürūṭına ve dostluḳ ve hemcivārlıḳ ḥuḳūḳınuñ riʿāyet ve ḥürmetine ve ʿale’l-ḫuṣūṣ
                    s̱emere-i ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥ
                    <lb/>olan berren ve baḥren ve nehren ticāret umūrınuñ şerāyiṭine bi-lā-taġyīr ʿahdnāmeler 
                    mūcebince mürāʿāt 
                    <lb/>olunmaġa ṭarafıñuzdan taḳayyud ve ihtimām olundıġı gibi bu ṭarafdan daḫı ke-mā yenbaġī mürāʿāt
                    ve ḫilāfı üzere
                    <lb/>ḥareketden ictināb olunmaḳ içün memālik-i maḥrūse ve serhad-i islāmiyyede olan żābıṭāna 
                    <lb/>evāmīr-i ̣aliyye-i ciḥān-muṭāʿla tenbīh ve teʾkīd olundıġı maʿlūmıñuz olub
                    ve ḫuṣūṣan sizüñ
                    ḥüsn-i sülūkıñuza
                    <lb/>meveddeten mükātebe ve mürāsele ile muʾāneset ve izdiyād-ı müʾālefetiñüze meyl ve raġbetimüz
                    olduġında iştibāh
                    <lb/>olunmayub bu ṭarafa ādemleriñüz gelür olduḳda bāʿis̱ -i tezāyüd-i meveddet olur mektūb-ı
                    cālibu’l-ḳulūbıñuz ile
                    <lb/>ḫaber-i ṣıḥḥat ve ʿāfiyetiñüzi iʿlām ve işʿārdan ẖālī olmamaları meʾmūldür.</ab>
                   </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.l.osm.1720421-transl">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                
                
                <ab type="Inscriptio/Elkab"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">Laudable pride of the great commanders of Christendom, 
                    distinguished among the illustrious greats of the community of the Messiah,
                    the chief deputy of the venerable, majestic Roman emperor,
                    our honorable, esteemed, affectionate friend Prince Eugene of Savoy</rs>:</ab>   
                
                <ab type="Salutatio/Dua"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">We</rs> inquire after your health and general situation while sending to your profoundly
                    dignified quarter which is a center of esteeem—to shortly summarize—[our] affable,
                    friendly wishes and the news of pure, amicable, mutual sincere friendship that are
                    fortified foundations of affection and reconciliation and steadfast edifice of
                    cultivating intimacy and true sincerity. Having expressed that we wish your perpetual
                    goodness and health</ab> 
                
                <ab type="Notificatio">we notify you affectionately of the following:
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">My</rs> esteemed and revered friend; your desirable letter that was dispatched to the direction
                    of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">your faithful</rs> through the assistance of the infantry chief, distinguished, chosen, councillor,
                    and esteemed grand ambassador, your well-wisher, 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General Graf von Virmont</rs>—laudable pride of the
                    commanders of the community of the Messiah who was sent and dispatched, as per the old ceremony,
                    by our friend the laudable pride of Christian kings,
                    the illustrious among the dominion-adorning sovereigns, his excellencies the majestic, revered, 
                    dignified <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">caesar</rs>-along with a letter of faithfulness, to
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">the capital of the king of the
                    kings that is a nest of felicity</rs> in order to strengthen the rules of the reconciliation and reinforce the
                    cultivation of intimacy between the two parties who mutually made a contract—came and was delivered.
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">In its content that displays sincere friendship 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">you</rs> wrote that it is your ultimate goal to 
                    abide by and respect the conditions of the peace and reconciliation—that was once again agreed
                    on between these two states and confirmed through written pacts and reinforced with agreements and pledges- 
                    and to observe and respect the law of neighborliness and sharing an adjacent border.
                    It is [also] written and reported that firm monitions and reiterations are dispatched to the
                   officers across the lands of the empire and frontiers to avoid violations of and divergence from,
                   without modification, the terms and recorded matters concerning friendship and
                   the conditions of reconciliation and [matters] regarding commerce over sea, land, and rivers.
               </ab>
               
                <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">aforesaid ambassador</rs> validated and confirmed all of 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">your</rs> written communication and he expressed
                   your upright conduct and your diligence for the security and comfort of the subjects of both sides
                   through observance of the conditions of this blessed covenant (<foreign xml:lang="tr">muṣāfaḥa</foreign>)
                    which made [us] extraordinarily satisfied. Also, on the side of 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">your sincere friend</rs>, in congruence with 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">your</rs>
                    friendship and benevolence, attention is paid to the execution of true friendship and
                    the ceremonies of the state of being mutually at peace. As per the old Ottoman
                    principles and time-honored, continuous [practices] of the protector of the world, 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the aforesaid ambassador</rs>
                    delivered and presented to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14841">the admirable stirrup of the king of the kings</rs> the letter
                    of mutual sincere friendship, gifts, and presents that he was commissioned to deliver and [thus]
                    he is honored with sultanic protocols and treated with kindness.
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">Besides, during the days of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">his</rs>
                    stay and residence in the capital, in recognition of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">your</rs> 
                    growing friendship, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">this well-wisher of yours</rs> paid attention to the important ceremonies
                    and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">his</rs> good treatment. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The aforesaid ambassador’s </rs>
                    admired conduct and his unquestionably admirable manner, reasonable and courteous behavior and manners, and his struggle and
                    effort to call forth the appreciation of both sides became visible, while his attention
                    in the direction of increasing the mutual confidence and his benevolence were obvious 
                    and evident. Consequently, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">he</rs> was respected and revered more than his predecessors and
                    he was treated pleasantly and shown respect with permission to more favors than he requested
                    and [previously] agreed.
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">He</rs> performed and completed his ambassadorial affairs as before.
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">He</rs> observed and accomplished the rituals of friendship and sincerity that were commissioned 
                    to his care in a way worthy of the reputation of both states and in accordance with the 
                    treaty. Thus, as he requested permission and license to return and go back, one more time,
                    he earned honor with customary laudable protocol at <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14984">the lofty imperial council</rs> 
                    and the brilliant royal presence. And, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">he</rs> was granted
                    and found worthy of permission and license from the side of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">his exalted
                    and great majesties</rs> who rules the world to return and go back along with an affectionate
                    and reconciliatory sultanic letter that is [dispatched] by <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">his sublime excellency the
                        ruler of the world</rs> to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">his excellency the majestic, dignified caesar</rs>. [Thus], the affectionate
                    letter was penned and sent to you with the aforementioned ambassador.</ab>
                    
                    <ab type="Dispositio/Hüküm">With the arrival [of the letter], with thanks to Almighty God and through
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">our</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">your</rs> 
                    effort and diligence, security accrued to the subjects of both sides with utmost firmness via 
                    the peace and reconciliation that was reinforced and fortified between these two states,
                    including a relaxation of the troops of both sides.
                    Just as <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">you</rs> pay attention and care on your side, as per the treaty and without any changes to it,
                    the observation and respect of the conditions of this auspicious reconciliation, friendship, and the law of
                    having adjacent borders and, in particular, the conditions of the matters of commerce over land, 
                    sea, and rivers which is a fruit of the peace and reconciliation, on this side too, as before, 
                    we sent monitions and firm orders of the sublime <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">ruler</rs> - who is obeyed by the whole
                    world - to the officers in the well-protected dominions and the frontiers of Islam to
                    obey [the conditions of the treaty] and avoid contradicting actions; <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">you</rs> already know that.
                        And in particular, there shall be no doubt in <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">our</rs> 
                        interest in and appreciation for friendly correspondence,
                    mutual sending of messengers, cultivating intimacy, and growth of friendship out of love for your
                    upright conduct. In case your men come to this direction, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">we</rs> wish that they shall not be devoid of
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">your</rs> heartfelt letter, which is a means of increasing friendship, and news and reports about your good state of
                    health and welfare.</ab>
                
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>