<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                
                <title xml:lang="de">Memorandum des Privatsekretärs (Driesch?) des 
                    österreichischen Großbotschafters Virmont am osmanischen Hof
                    über die damaligen europäischen Angelegenheiten, Istanbul, 26. Jänner 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">A memorandum written by the private secretary (Driesch?)
                    of the Austrian ambassador for the Ottoman court, concerning
                    the European affairs at the time, Istanbul, January 26, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Nemçe büyükelçisi Virmont'un sırkatibinin (Driesch?)
                    OSmanlı sarayına Avrupa ahvali hakkında yazdığı takrir, Istanbul, 26 Ocak 1720</title>
                
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.misc.osm.17200126</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>IE.HR</collection>
                        <idno>10-961-001</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1720-01-26"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.misc" type="context"> Urkunde </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Memorandum des Privatsekretärs (Driesch?) des 
                    österreichischen Großbotschafters Virmont am osmanischen Hof
                    über die damaligen europäischen Angelegenheiten, Istanbul, 26. Jänner 1720,  
                    bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), 
                    hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="İE_HR___00010_00961_001_001.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        


    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.misc.osm.17200126">
            
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <ab>Hüve</ab>
                <metamark function="archivalnumbering">961</metamark>                           
            
                
                
                <ab><cb/>
                <lb/>Ḥālā der devlet-i ʿaliyyede iḳāmet üzere olan <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe çāsārınuñ</rs>
                <lb/>sır kātibiniñ taḳrīridür. 
                <lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1720-01-26">15 Rā[<supplied resp="#yy">Rebiülevvel</supplied>] 1132</date></ab>
                
                <ab>
                <lb/><date when="1719-09-12">Māh-ı Eylülüñ on ikinci günle</date> müverraḫ
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Beçden</rs> mektūblarum gelüb 
                <lb/>devletlü ve ʿināyetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib-i devlet efendimüz ḥażretlerine</rs>
                <lb/>daḫı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">başvekīlden</rs> başḳa mektūb gelüb cenāb-ı ʿālīlerine 
                <lb/>selām ve duʿāların tebliġinden ṣoñra bu bendelerini bi-nefsihī 
                <lb/>teslīmine meʾmūr eylemişlerdür.</ab>
                
                <ab>Şevketlü ve ʿaẓametlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">şehinşāh-ı 
                <lb/>muʿaẓẓam efendimüz</rs> ḥażretleriniñ cenāb-ı hümāyūnlarına ve müşārün               
                    <lb/>ileyḥ <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">devletlü efendimüz</rs> ḥażretlerine
                    ḥaşmetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">çāsār 
                <lb/>efendimüñ</rs> ṭarafından nāmeler daḫı bi-lā-teʾḫīr ṭaraf-ı bendelerine 
                <lb/>irsāl olunmak üzeredürler.</ab>
                    
                <ab>Lākin şimdik<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>i</corr></choice> ḥālde işbu 
                <lb/>mektūb-ı meveddet-üslūbıyla bi-lā resm-i tekellüf ḫākipāy-ı ʿaliyyelerinde 
                <lb/>şeref-yāb buyurılmaḳ mercū ve müteżarriʿdür.</ab> 
                    
                <ab>Ve bundan māʿadā
                    <lb/>bundan aḳdem ilçi <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Virmond</rs> dāʿīlerine taḥrīr buyurılan
                <lb/>mektūbdan ḳānevizler makbūl-ı şerīfleri olacaġına müşārün ileyh
                    <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">çāsār efendim</rs> ḫaber almaġla dostluḳ ve muvādaʿaya bināʾen
                <lb/>merḳūm ḳānevizleri örnekleri ve taḥrīr buyurılan miḳdārı 
                <lb/>mūcebince tedārük itdirüb bu bendelerine irsāl eylediler.
                <lb/>Maḳbūl-ı ʿaliyyeleri olduḳda ne vech-ile fermān buyurılur
                <lb/>ise ḥāẓır ve āmādedirler.</ab>
                
                <ab>Ḥavādis olmaḳ üzere
                <lb/>taḥrīr eyledikleri budur ki Mosḳov çārınuñ donanması İsveç
                <lb/>ḳrālınuñ donanmasıyla Baḥr-i Balṭıḳda muḳābil olub Mosḳovlunuñ
                <lb/>ince donanması ziyāde olub ḳıyıda bulunmaġla ve İsveçlünüñ
                <lb/>ḳalın donanması ḳıyıya yaḳlaşmaḳ mümkün olmamaġla bir miḳdār cenk
                <lb/>ve cidālden ṣoñra İsveçlünüñ dört pāre fırkaṭeleri
                <lb/>Mosḳovludan aḫz olunub küṣūrı çekilüb gitmişlerdür.
                <lb/>Bundan ġayri ol ṭaraflarda bir şey vāḳiʿ olduġını
                <lb/>yazmıyorlar.</ab>
                
                
                <ab>Şimālde vāḳiʿ ḳrāllaruñ ʿumūmen muṣālaḥaları 
                <cb/>
                <lb/>içün maḥall-i mükāleme taʿyīn olunan Brūvunçuvk(?) nām mahalde
                <lb/>egerçe henüz mükālemeye şürūʿ olunmamışdur; lākin Mosḳov
                <lb/>çārı maḥall-i mezbūreye muraḫḫaṣ gönderüb mükālemeye aġāz 
                <lb/>olunmaḳ üzere idi. Beçde olan ilçisi daḫı çārı
                <lb/>ṭarafından çāsār efendime kemāl-i dostluḳ iẓhār
                <lb/>idüb tecdīd-i muṣālaḥaya mübāşeret olunmaḳ üzeredir.
                <lb/>Ve Leh cumhūrınun kadīmī istiḳlāli ve serbestiyeti ḥusūsı-çün
                <lb/>başḳa mādde ʿaḳd olunmaḳ üzere karār virmüşlerdür.</ab>
                
                <ab><lb/>İspanya ḳrālı ile olan muṣālaḥa mükālemesi ḳuvvet-i ḳurbiyyeye
                <lb/>gelüb Nemçe çāsārı ve Françe ḳrālı ve İspānya ḳrālı
                <lb/>ve İngiltere ḳrālı ve Nederlande Estātı cānerālleri bu cümle
                <lb/>ʿale’l-ittifāḳ muṣālaḥa eylemek üzeredürler. Lākin Françede
                <lb/>beyne’l-ricāl ve’n-nās ʿazīm iḫtilāl olub ḳrāllıḳ vekīli
                <lb/>olan Düḳa de Orliyens kemāl mertebede intibāh ve ġāile
                <lb/>üzeredür. Zīrā İspānya ḳrālı yine gendü ḥālinde olmayub
                <lb/>Françe ricālinden baʿżılarını el altından iżlāl idüb
                <lb/>ṭarafına cezb itmekdedür. Bu aḥvāliñ niḥāyeti neye varacaġı
                <lb/>maʿlūm deġildür diyü ḫatm-ı kelām eyledi.
            
            </ab>
                
                <metamark function="archivalcode">
                    <lb/>Osmanlı Arşivi
                    <lb/>İ.E. HR
                    <lb/>10-961
                    <lb/>2 urk
                </metamark>
            </div> 
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.misc.osm.17200126-transl">
            
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                
                <ab><cb/>
                    <lb/>An official note by the <rs type="person">Austrian emperor</rs>'s private secretary
                    who resides in the Sublime State at the moment.<date when="1720-02-25">25 February 1720</date></ab>
                    
                <ab><lb/>My letters dated <date when="1719-09-12">September 12</date> have arrived from
                    <rs ana="MPRautomatched" ref="#mpr1761 mpr13416" type="place">Vienna</rs>. A seperate letter has also come 
                    to our excellency, the most excellent and gracious 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">holder of state [grand vizier]</rs>,
                    from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10441">chief minister</rs>, who,  
                    after declaration of greetings and good wishes, appointed this humble servant
                    to deliver his letter in person.</ab> 
                    
                    <ab>The letters from my majestic lord, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">caesar</rs>,
                    addressed to the imperial excellency of our lord his highness, the majestic, august,
                    esteemed king of kings, and to the exalted personage of 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the aforementioned most excellent lord</rs>
                    are also about to be dispatched without delay to this humble 
                    servant of yours.</ab>
                    
                                       
                    <ab>However, for now, it is requested and expected to be honored at
                    the exalted noble dust of your presence, along with the current affectionately
                    written letter [by the chief minister Prince Eugene],
                    without the observance of official ceremonial formalities.</ab> 
                    
                <ab>In addition, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">my aforementioned lord caesar</rs>,
                    having been informed through the letter that was previously written to your
                    well-wisher <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Virmond</rs> 
                    that the canovaccios(?) will be deemed acceptable, had the 
                    canovaccio(?) samples procured in the amount specified in writing and,
                    as per friendship and reconciliation, dispatched
                    to this servant of yours. As soon as the sublime permission is granted,
                    in whichever fashion it is decreed, they are ready and available.</ab> 
                    
                    
                <ab>The following have been written as news: The fleet of the Russian tsar
                    came accross the fleet of the Swedish king in the Baltic Sea. 
                    As the light fleet of the Muscovites was bigger in size and docked 
                    by the coast, the major fleet of the Swedish was not able to 
                    approach to the coast. After a little bit of combat and fighting,
                    four Swedish frigates were captured by the Muscovites and the 
                    rest of the fleet retreated and left. Other than this, they are not reporting
                    anything else that took place in those quarters.
                    Nothing else has been written in addition to these news.</ab>
                
                <ab>Even though negotiations have not yet begun in Brūvunçuvk, the place that
                    had been designated as the location of negotiations for the conclusion
                    of a peace among the kings quartered in the north, nonetheless,
                    the Muscovite tsar dispatched a plenipotentiary to that said location
                    and the talks were about to begin. [The tsar's] envoy in Vienna
                    also displayed a perfect friendliness from his tsar to my lord caesar,
                    and the peace negotiations are set to begin. 
                    And they decided that a separate article will be concluded
                    concerning the ancient freedom and independence of the Polish nation.</ab>
                    
                    
                    <ab>The peace talks with the Spanish king is close to the 
                    moment of conclusion. The Austrian emperor, the French king, the Spanish
                    king, the English King, and the state general of the Netherlands
                    are all about to sign a peace unanimously. However, there is a
                    great unrest in France among the aristocracy and people; the Duke of
                    Orléans, the deputy of kingship, is fully vigilent and in great anxiety.
                    
                    <note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                        The dukes of Orleans were not "deputies of kingship" 
                        (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳrāllıḳ vekīli</foreign>)
                        as the Turkish text implies; they only stood next in the order of succession
                        to the throne if members of the senior branch ceased to exist.</note>
                    
                    
                    Likewise, the Spanish king is also not standing still; he secretly corrupts
                    some of the French noblemen and attracts them to his own side. 
                    The letter ended stating that it is unknown where the
                    fate of these affairs will lead to.</ab>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>