<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsaudienz beim Großwesir İbrahim
                    Pascha, Istanbul, 21. April 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of Damian Hugo von Virmont’s farewell audience with the Grand Vizier
                    İbrahim Pasha, Istanbul, April 21, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un Veziriazam İbrahim Paşa’ya veda
                    ziyareti, İstanbul, 21 Nisan 1720</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName>Teşrifati Salman Efendi</persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200421b</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 91</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1720-04-21"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsaudienz beim Großwesir İbrahim Pascha, Istanbul, 21. April 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00044b.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200421b">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
            <ab>
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisinüñ</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlete</rs> vedāʿ içün geldigini müşʿirdür.
                <lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-21">Fī 12 C<supplied resp="#yy">emaziyülahir</supplied> 1132</date>
                <lb/>Yevm-i mezbūrda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisi</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlete</rs> vedāʿ içün gelmekle ẕikr olunur.</ab>
                
                <note type="footnote" resp="#yy" xml:id="ftn1">
                    See C. Driesch <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_421">page 421 and beyond for a description of the meeting.</ref></note>
                
                
                <ab>
                    <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">İlçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs> rükūbı içün kemer raḫtlı bir at ve begzādegān <supplied resp="#yy">ve</supplied> etbāʿı içün daḥı seksen 
                <lb/>reʾs atlar bāġ çe ḳapusına irsāl ve çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve ilçinüñ üzerinde olan 
                <lb/>çavuşlardan ġ ayrı on ḳadar telli çavuş daḥı irsāl ve sāʿat ikiye bāliġ  olduġ ı
                <lb/>es̠nāda ṣadr-ı ʿālīye gelüb vācibüʾl-riʿāya aġ aları dīvānḫānede rūz-merre
                <lb/>es̠ vāblarıyla dizilüb vezīr ḳapucıbaşı aġ aları erkān kürk ve ṣarıḳlarıyla ʿarż 
                    <lb/>odası ḳapusına dizilüb ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14722">reʾīs efendi</rs> ve teẕkireci efendiler ve mektūbī efendi ve bu ḥaḳīr 
                <lb/>daḥı erkān ferāce ve ṣarıḳlar ile ṣadruñ ṣaġ  ṭarafında durub ḥāżır olduḳ ları
                <lb/>ḥālde</ab>
                
                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> gelüb ṣadruñ öñine vażʿ olunmış iskemleye oturub baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>
                <lb/>süd māvīsi çuḳa ferāce semūr kürk ve rūz-merre giydükleri destār ile ketḫüdā beg 
                    <lb/>koltuġ ında teşrīf eyledüklerinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ḳıyām idüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> çavuşbaşı ṭarafına
                <lb/>selām-dāde olduḳ da selām aġ ası ṣavt-ı bülend ile selām alub maḳāmlarına kuʿūd
                <lb/>eyledikde çāvuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī alḳış eylediler.</ab>
                
                <ab>Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiye</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> sīm <unclear reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="char"/> ile
                <lb/>maʿcūn virilüb ḳahveler içildükden ṣoñra ḳışḳış olub çār-yek sāʿat miḳdārı
                    <lb/>mürūrdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi bege</rs> serāser ferāce semūr ve ḳapıcubaşıya ve yeñiçeri ḥāṣekisine
                <lb/>ve çorbacıya ve üzerine meʾmūr çavuşlara ve dīvān tercümānına ve ser-kātibine ve begzādegāna
                <lb/>ve sāʾire yetmiş dört ṭob ḫilʿat ilbās olunmışdur. Ḫattā ser-kātibine ḳapu ketḥüdālıġ ı içün
                    <lb/>bir ḫilʿat daḥı elbās olunmışdur. Baʿdehū şerbet ve buḥūr virilüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> gitmişdür.</ab>
                
            <ab>
                <lb/>Ve bugünde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi bege</rs> kemer raḫt ve sīm rikāb ve Şām kesmesiyle ve ṣırma işleme 
                <choice><sic>egerlü</sic> <corr>eyerlü</corr></choice> bir ḳır at
                <lb/>virilmişdür. Meẕkūr atuñ ̇gırrāresi var idi lakin debbūsı
                ʾādet olunmamaġ la vażʿ
                <lb/>olunmamışdı. ʿAvdetinde daḥı çavuşlar kātibi ile emīn aġ a gitmişdür.</ab>
                
                <note type="footnote" resp="#yy" xml:id="ftn2">
                    Following this official farewell ceremony, the grand vizier wanted to see Graf Virmont one more time.
                    However, this time the grand vizier wanted to avoid the official solemnities and only
                    wanted to spend friendly time together with Virmont. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_423">Eventually, Virmont came along with his band of musicians
                    whom the grand vizier tipped generously.</ref></note>
                
                
        </div> 
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200421b-transl">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
            <ab>The following relates <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the Austrian ambassador’s</rs> farewell visit to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> on April 21, 1720.
                On that day, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the Austrian ambassador</rs> visited <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> to bid farewell. It is
                reported here.<ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/></ab>
                
               <!-- <note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                    See C. Driesch <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_421">page 421 and beyond for a description of the meeting.</ref></note>
-->                
                <ab>For <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador’s</rs> ride a horse equipped with a leather-strap harness was dispatched 
                to the garden gate, while for his noblemen eighty horses were dispatched. 
                In addition to palace ushers, the secretary and the intendant of the ushers – who were 
                commissioned to escort the ambassador – ten other ushers, wearing aigrettes, were dispatched. 
                As the clock hit two o’clock, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador</rs> arrived at <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier’s</rs> palace.
                The aghas of the palace guardsmen (<foreign xml:lang="tr">vācibü’r-riʿāya aġ aları</foreign>), wearing their daily garments,
                set up their ranks at the reception room. The aghas of the vizier’s chief steward,
                wearing their ceremonial furs and turbans, were disposed in order in front of the audience room. 
                The chief of the scribes, the secretary of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> (<foreign xml:lang="tr">teẕkireci efendi</foreign>),
                the scribe of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> (<foreign xml:lang="tr">mektūbī efendī</foreign>), and this humble servant, wearing
                ceremonial cloaks and turbans, were disposed in order on the right side of the gate.</ab>
                
                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs> came and sit down on the stool arranged in front of the gate.
                When <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> entered the room wearing a sable fur on a milk-blue broadcloth ceremonial
                cloak and the <foreign xml:lang="tr">dastar</foreign> that he daily puts on [his head], accompanied arm-in-arm by the
                chief steward, the ambassador rose to his feet. When <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> made a salutation
                in the direction of the agha of the palace ushers, the master of ceremonies received the salutation 
                and responded with a loud voice. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">the grand vizier</rs> then sat on his post and all of the palace ushers applauded.</ab>
                
                <ab>Thereafter, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador</rs> was presented with taffy which was served on silver <foreign xml:lang="tr">?</foreign>                
                and, after coffee was drunk, a conversation session took place. After a hiatus for quarter of an hour,
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador</rs> was presented with a sable fur on an embroidered ceremonial cloak. 
                A total of seventy-four robes of honor were presented to the chief steward, the janissary lieutenant,
                the janissary captain, the ushers commissioned to escort the ambassador, the imperial council
                interpreter, the chief secretary of the ambassador as well as his noblemen and others.
                His chief secretary was presented with a second robe of honor for his function as <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador’s</rs>
                chief steward. Afterwards, sorbet and frankincense were served and the ambassador left.</ab>
                
            <ab>
                On this day, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador</rs> was presented a gray horse equipped with a leather-strap harness,
                silver stirrups, a Damascene-work horse blanket. The saddle seat was worked with gold and silver threads.
                The horse had a haircloth sack but its mace (<foreign xml:lang="tr">debbūs</foreign>?) was not provided, since that was not the custom.
                During <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador’s</rs> return to his residence, the secretary and the intendant of the ushers escorted him.<ref target="#ftn2" type="note_reference"/>
                
                <!--<note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                    Following this official farewell ceremony, the grand vizier wanted to see Graf Virmont one more time.
                    However, this time the grand vizier wanted to avoid the official solemnities and only
                    wanted to spend friendly time together with Virmont. <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_423">Eventually, Virmont came along with his band of musicians
                        whom the grand vizier tipped generously.</ref></note>
                -->
            
        
        </ab>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>