<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Ankunft, Istanbul, 3. August 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of Damian Hugo von Virmont’s arrival, Istanbul, August 3, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un varışı, İstanbul, 3 Ağustos 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName> Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi </persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>

                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17190803</idno>
                <!-- PID: o:[context].[genre].[language].[date-iso](.[nr])
    # context: 
        vipa for Virmont/Ibrahim Paşa 1719-1720
        qhod ıs outdated, it's only used for the meta context that aggregates the different edition subparts.
# genres:
ad. administrative document
ch. chronicle
in. instruction
l. letter
mh. mühimme
np. newspaper
pr. protocol register
pp. pamphlet
pt. petition
rc. record (Urkunde)
re. receipt
rp. report (Bericht, Relation)
tr. travelogue
# languages:
osm. ottoman source
hbg. habsburg source
# date:
yyyy-mm-dd or yyyy
we use the first known date of creation for handwritten texts 
and for printed ones the date of publication
# nr:
ONLY if a PID would duplicate (e.g. two habsburg letters on the same date) -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <!-- Archive, Library,… -->
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 53-54</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="scribe1">
                                <persName ref="#mpr13114">Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi</persName>
                                <desc><!-- e.g. Written in red ink --></desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1719-08-03"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Encoding guidelines -->
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Ankunft, Istanbul, 3. August 1719, Istanbul, 19. April 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG01">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00025b.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG02">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00026a.jpg" xml:id="IMG02"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190803">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
                <!--Ḫḫ -->
            <head><lb/><hi rend="#red"><rs type="person">Nemçe Çāsārı</rs> ṭarafından ṣulḥnāme ile
                    gelen <rs type="person">kebīr ilçiniñ</rs> istiḳbāli <lb/>keyfiyetidür ki z̠ ikr
                    olunur</hi>. Der sene <date type="Hijri" when="1719-08-03">1131, 17
                        [Ramaza]n</date></head>
            <ab><lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1719">Biñ yüz otuz bir senesi Ramażān-ı Şerīfinde</date> <rs type="person">Nemçe
                    Çāsārı</rs> ṭarafından <lb/>ṣulḥnāme ile rikāb-ı müsteṭāba yüz sürmek üzere
                gelen büyükilçi 
                <lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr14573">Küçükçekmece’den</rs> ḳalḳub <rs type="place">Ḥazīnedār Çiftligi</rs> dimekle maʿrūf maḥalliñ <lb/>alt ṭarafına kendi
                çadırı ile ḳonmaġ la <date type="Hijri" when="1719-07-28">māh-i mezbūruñ on birinci
                    <lb/>güni</date> istiḳbāl ve alayı içün gidilmekle bu sibāḳ üzeredür ki
                <lb/>z̠ikr olunur.</ab>
                
                <note type="footnote" resp="#yy" xml:id="ftn1"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page151">
                    The Austrian mission</ref> arrived in Küçükçekmece on July 31
                    where they were met by Mehmed Agha, whose rank Driesch 
                    described as <foreign xml:lang="de">kaiserlicher Kämmerling</foreign>,
                    that is <foreign xml:lang="tr">kapı kethüdası</foreign> or the chief steward.
                    <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page155">The next day, on August 1</ref>
                    the palace dragoman, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14575">Grigore II Ghica</rs>, met the Austrian grand ambassador
                    to discuss the details the audience with the sultan.</note>
                
                <ab><date type="Hijri" when="1719-08-03">Yevm-i mezbūrda</date> ilçinüñ rükūbū içün dīvān raḫtı ve ʿabāyī ile <lb/>müzeyyen bir at
                begzādegān ve etbāʿı içün daḫi yüz otuz atlar <choice><corr>eyerlenüb</corr><sic>egerlenüb</sic></choice>
                <lb/>ʿale l-seḥer maḥall-i mezbūra getirilmişdür. 
                Z̠ ikr olunan atlaruñ cümlesi devletlü ṣadr-ı ʿālī 
                <lb/>ṭarafından gitmek muʿtād idi. Lākin ol miḳdār at mevcūd olmadıġ ından
                <lb/>mez̠ kūr olan atlaruñ seksen ruʾūsı
                ıṣṭabl-ı ʿāmire ṭarafından <choice><corr>berāṭsız</corr><sic>berāṭasız</sic></choice>
                <lb/>yedekciler ile ḳuṣūrı daḫi <rs type="person">ṣāhib-i devlet</rs> ṭarafından
                gönderilmişdi.</ab>
                
            <ab>Ve Edirne <lb/>Ḳapusı ḫāricinde Bayrāmpaşa Bostānına muṭṭaṣıl Ḳara
                İbrāhīm Paşa <lb/>Çiftligi dimekle maʿrūf <choice><corr>Ḫadīce</corr><sic>Ḥadīce</sic></choice> Sulṭān Çiftliginde <rs type="person">ilçi-yi mezbūra</rs>
                <lb/>żiyāfet içün <rs type="person">ṣadr-ı ʿālī</rs> ṭarafından bir gün muḳaddem
                maṭbaḫ gönderilüb ve baġ çe-i <lb/>mezbūrda olan ḳaṣr daḫi mehterḫāne-i ʿāmireden 
                ferş olunmuş-idi. <lb/>Ve ḫidmet içün daḫī yirmi beş ḳadar mülebbes
                Enderūn aġ aları gelmiş-idi. <lb/>Vekīl-i ḫarc bi-nefsihī gelmiş-idi.</ab>
                
                <note type="footnote" resp="#yy" xml:id="ftn2"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page160">
                According to the travelogue of Driesch,</ref> on August 3, the Austrian delegation
                    had a breakfast at the Ḥadīce Sulṭān Farm before the official entry
                    parade to the city.</note>  
                
            <ab>Çavuşbaşı aġ a ve sipāh ve silāḥdār aġ aları <lb/>ve sipāh ve silaḥdār kātibleri ve
                ketḫüdāları ve çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve ḳırḳ <lb/>elli nefer dergāh-ı ʿālī
                çavuşları ve otuz ḳırk nefer sipāh ve silāḥdār çavuşları <lb/>bi’l-cümle bāġ çe-i
                mezbūrda müctemiʿ olub ilçi-yi mezbūr maḥall-i merḳūma ḳarīb geldigi <lb/>ḫaber
                virilmekle ḥāżır olan ṣarıḳlar ile süvār olub çeyrek sāʿat <lb/>miḳdārı yirde
                istiḳbāl idüb alay ile çiftlige getürilüb ḳaṣr-ı mezbūr <lb/>üzerine çıḳ arılduḳda
                ḳapuya nāẓır ṣadr öninde olan iskemleye oturdulub <lb/>yemīn ü yesārına çavuşbaşı
                ve sipāh ve silāḥdār ve aşaġı bölük aġaları <lb/>oturub ṭatlu ve ḳahve virildükden
                ṣoñra ṭaʿām döşenmekle</ab> <ab> aġalar ḳalḳub <lb/>tenāvül-i ṭaʿāmdan ṣoñra çavuşbaşı ve
                sipāh ve silāḥdār aġ aları selīmī ve ṣarıḳ <lb/>ferāce ile dīvān bisāṭlu atlara süvār
                ve sā<supplied>ʾ</supplied>irleri daḫi mücevvezeleriyle süvār <lb/>olub</ab>
            
            <ab>alay ile trompetesin çalaraḳ  <add place="margin">Edirne Ḳapusından duḫūl</add> ve
                Sulṭān Ḥammāmı öñinden <lb/>mürūr ve Fenār Ḳapusından ṭaşra 
                çıḳ ılub Yā Vedūd İskelesine varılub <lb/>andan Emīr Buḫārīye
                varılduḳda cümlenüñ ʿavdeti içün ilçi iz̠n virmekle <lb/>herkes girü ʿavdet
                olmışlardur. <rs type="place">İstanbula</rs> Edirne Ḳapusından girilmişdür. Ve
                ilçi çıḳ ub <lb/>yine <supplied>Ḫ</supplied>azīnedār Çiftliginde çadırlarına gitmişdır. Bu es̠nāda <rs type="place">Āsitānede </rs>
                vebā <sic>ḫastaligi</sic> <add place="margin">olmaġla anda
                    oturmışdur.</add></ab>
                
                <note type="footnote" resp="#yy" xml:id="ftn3"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page160">
                    In Driesch’s travelogue, in the first chapter of the second book,</ref> 
                    there is a detailed description of the etnry to the city. See especially
                    pages 160-162.</note> 
                
            <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>
            <ab/>
            <list>
                <item rend="column1"><lb/>İlçi için vażʿ olunan sofrada yalñız dīvān tercümānı
                    oturmışdır</item>
                <item rend="column2">Ve köşküñ orta yirine daḫi begzādegānı içün bir <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium">bütgūn</unclear>(?) ḳonmışdur</item>
                <item rend="column1">Ve köşküñ bir ṭarafına daḫi meşīn sofra ile bir simāṭ vażʿ
                    olunmışdur</item>
                <item rend="column2">Ve ḥavā līde daḫi hācegānı içün ṭaʿām
                    virilmişdür</item>
                </list>
           </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190803-transl">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/> 
                
             <head>Mentions the circumstances at the arrival of the grand ambassador dispatched with a peace settlement
                 by the Austrian Emperor, the year <date type="Hijri" when="1719-08-03">1131, 17 [Ramada]n </date></head>
                
             <ab><date type="Hijri" when="1719">In the month of Ramadan of the year one thousand and thirty-one</date>, 
                 a grand ambassador from the Austrian Emperor came to prostrate himself in front of the pleasant stirrups [of the sultan]
                 with a peace settlement. He departed from <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14573">Küçükçekmece</rs>
                 and settled in his own tent at the lower side of the location known as Hazinedar Çiftliği.<ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/>
                 
                 
                 
                 <date type="Hijri" when="1719-07-28">On the eleventh day of the aforesaid month</date>, 
                 we went for his reception and parade. Here is a description of what preceded that reception.</ab>
                
             <ab>On that day, a horse [had been] adorned with an imperial ceremonial harness and a silk cover for the ambassador
                 and one hundred and thirty horses had been tacked up for the ambassador’s inner circle
                 and [the horses] had been brought to the aforesaid location at dawn.
                 It was a routine to send all of these horses from [the stables of] the grand vizier. Yet, 
                 there not being a sufficient number of horses [in the grand vizier’s stables],
                 eighty horses had been sent from the imperial stables without
                 the issuance of a sultanic permission and the rest were dispatched by the grand vizier.</ab>
                
             <ab>The previous day, the grand vizier had sent a [portable] cookery to Hatice Sultan Farm, known as Kara İbrahim Paşa Farm,
                 located outside the Edirne Gate next to Bayrampaşa Orchard, and the pavilion inside the garden had been furnished
                 by the sultan’s tent pitchers (<foreign xml:lang="tr">meḥ terḫāne-i ʿāmire</foreign>). Twenty-five aghas from the inner court 
                 had come with their uniforms on them to serve. The major-domo (<foreign xml:lang="tr">vekīl-i ḫarc</foreign>) himself was there too.
                 <ref target="#ftn2" type="note_reference"/></ab>
                
                <!--><note resp="#yy" place="paragraph"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page160">
                    According to the travelogue of Driesch,</ref> on August 3, the Austrian delegation
                    had a breakfast at the Ḥadīce Sulṭān Farm before the official entry
                    parade to the city.</note> !--> 
                
             <ab>The agha of the palace ushers, the aghas of the palace cavalry and sword-bearers,
                 the secretaries of the palace cavalry and sword-bearers, the secretary of the palace ushers
                 and the intendant of the palace ushers, forty to fifty palace ushers and thirty to forty
                 ushers from the palace cavalry units and sword-bearers, all gathered at the aforesaid garden. 
                 As it was reported that the ambassador approached the location, those who were present mounted on their horses 
                 with their turbans [on their heads] and the ambassador was met at a quarter-hour distance.
                 He was then paraded to the farm, brought on the pavilion, and made to sit on the stool that was 
                 in front of the sofa next to the door. The agha of the palace ushers,
                 the aghas of the palace cavalry units, sword-bearers, and lower cavalry units sat down on his right and left.
                 After coffee and sweets had been served, a meal was spread out. </ab>
                 
             <ab>After eating the meal, the agha of the palace ushers and the aghas of the palace cavalry
                 and sword-bearers, with their ceremonial turbans (<foreign xml:lang="tr">selīmī</foreign>),
                 regular turbans (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ṣarıḳ</foreign>), and cloaks on them, 
                 mounted horses equipped with ceremonial imperial saddles. Others, with <foreign xml:lang="tr">mücevveze</foreign>s 
                 (a turban of many plaited folds) on their heads, also mounted horses.</ab>
                
             <ab>They paraded playing their trumpets and entered (the city) through the Edirne Gate.
                 They passed by Sultan Hamamı and exited the city via the Phanar Gate. They arrived at Ya Vedud Pier
                 and advanced to the lodge of Emīr Buhari, where the ambassador allowed everyone’s return.
                 Upon which everyone returned and entered the city through the Edirne Gate. 
                 The ambassador returned to his tent at Hazinedar Farm. At this time,
                 there was the plague in Istanbul. Therefore, the ambassador settled at that location.
                 <ref target="#ftn3" type="note_reference"/>                  
                 <!--<note resp="#yy" place="paragraph"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#page160">
                    In Driesch’s travelogue, in the first chapter of the second book,</ref> 
                    there is a detailed description of the entry to the city. See especially
                pages 160-162.</note> !--> </ab>
                
                
                
                <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>   
             <ab>Only the imperial council interpreter sat around the meal that was spread out for the ambassador.
                 For the ambassador’s inner circle, a <unclear reason="illegible">bütgūn</unclear>(bench?) had been set up 
                 in the middle of the mansion. In another part of the mansion, a meal was prepared
                 on a leather spread. Moreover, a meal had been served for the elders of that quarter.</ab>
           
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>