<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Verwalter von Bihać, den in
                    seiner Hand befindlichen kroatischen Gefangenen namens Plasnić (Jellachich)
                    gegen einen angemessenen Preis, wie im kaiserlichen Vertragsschreiben (ahidname)
                    vorgeschrieben, freizulassen; Istanbul, 3. Januar – 12. Januar 1720</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree addressed to the district commander of Bihać to
                    release the Croatian captive in his possession named Plasnić (Jellachich) in
                    return for a reasonable price as prescribed in the imperial letter of agreement
                    (ahidname); Istanbul, January 3 – January 12, 1720</title>



                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Bihke (Bihać) sancak beyine hitaben yazılmış,
                    elindeki Plasniç isimli Hırvat esiri, ahidname şartlarına uygun bir şekilde
                    makul bir ücret karşılığında serbest bırakması hakkında hükmü; İstanbul, 3 Ocak
                    – 12 Ocak, 1720</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17200103-17200112.2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 74, entry 159</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1720-01-03" notAfter="1720-01-12"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p> Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Verwalter von Bihać, den in seinem Besitz
                    befindlichen kroatischen Gefangenen namens Plasnič (Jellachich) gegen einen
                    angemessenen Preis, wie im kaiserlichen Vertragsschreiben (ahidname)
                    vorgeschrieben, freizulassen; Istanbul, 3. Januar – 12. Januar 1720; Istanbul,
                    3. Januar – 12. Januar 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu,
                    Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften
                    Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer
                    und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>Decree to the judge of Bihać about the release of the Croatian captive
                        named Plasnić (Jellachich) according to the conditions of the imperial
                        letter of agreement</item>
                    <item>Bihać</item>
                    <item>Bihke</item>
                    <item>captive</item>
                    <item>esir</item>
                    <item>Plasnić</item>
                    <item>Jellachich</item>
                    <item>Croatian</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00036_Page_74_Entry_159.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <!--<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı vezīre</rs>Abdullah Pasha
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Wien</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Buda</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9372">Erdel</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">Ottoman Empire</rs>-->


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17200103-17200112.2">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">159</metamark>

                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr15461">Bihke</rs> sancaġı begine ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile der-i devlet-medāruma gelen <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                    <lb/>ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü ʿarż-ı ḥāl
                    gönderüb</ab>

                <ab>nās yedinde bulunan esīrler daḫī münāsib vecihle mümkin olan maʿḳūl <lb/>ve
                    muʿtedil bahā ile ıṭlāḳları cāʾiz ola esīr ṣāḥibi ile uzlaşılmayub nizāʿ vāḳiʿ
                    olduḳda ḥākimü’l-vaḳt olanlar <lb/>mābeynlerin tevfīk eyleye diyü ʿahdnāme-i
                    hümāyūnda mesṭūr ve muḳayyed olmaḳla</ab>

                <ab>müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> reʿāyāsında
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr1690">Ḫırvāt</rs>
                    <lb/>memleketi sākininden <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15669">Plāsnīç</rs><note
                        xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">The Austrian ambassador Hugo von
                        Virmond reported to Vienna in two different letters, dated <ref
                            target="/o:vipa.l.hbg.17200103">Januar 3, 1720</ref> and <ref
                            target="/o:vipa.l.hbg.17200121">January 21, 1720</ref>, his initiatives
                        to free this Croatian captive whom he referred to as a nobleman
                            (<foreign>Edelmann</foreign>). As an attachment to the second letter
                        dated January 21, Virmond also dispatched to Vienna the Latin copies of the
                        orders issued by the Ottoman court and sent to <rs type="person"
                            ref="#mpr16088">Osman Pasha</rs> of Bosnia and the district
                        administrator of Bihać.</note> nām kimesne esnā-yı cengde esīr düşüb ve sen
                    ki mīr-i mūmā ileyhsin ḥālā senüñ yanuñda esīrüñ <lb/>olub ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn
                    muḳteżāsınca maʿḳūl bahā ile ḫalāṣ olmaḳ lāzım iken müşārün ileyhimüñ
                    serḥaddinde(?) olan <lb/>cenerāl <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15669">esīr-i
                        mesfūr</rs>ı mübādele içün ṭarafıña bir müselmān esīri ile yüz altmış altun
                    gönderüb alıḳodıġuñdan ṣoñra <lb/>ḥadden birūn aḳça muṭālebesiyle <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr15669">esīr-i mesfūr</rs>ı ṣalıvirmeyüb ḫilāf-ı
                    ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn teʿaddī eyledügiñ bildürüb</ab>

                <ab>vech-i meşrūḥ <lb/>üzere muḳaddemā ṭarafıña gönderilen müselmān esīri ve ol
                    miḳdār altun ile esīr-i mezbūr mübādele ve vilāyetine irsāl <lb/>olunmaḳ bābında
                    ḥükm-i hümāyūnum ricā eyledügi ecilden</ab>

                <ab>sen ki mīr-i mūmā ileyhsin nās yedinde bulunan esīrlerüñ muʿtedil <lb/>bahā ile
                    ıṭlāḳları cāʾiz olmaḳ ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnda mesṭūr ve esīr-i mesfūruñ
                    muḳābelesinde bir müselmān esīri ile <lb/>meblaġ-ı mezbūr virilmişken ḳanāʿat
                    olunmayub daḫī ziyāde aḳça muṭālebesiyle ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn şürūṭına muġāyir
                    <lb/>ḥareket ile ḥadd-i iʿtidāl tecāvüz olunmaġın iʿlām olundıġı üzere meblaġ-ı
                    meẕḳūrı ve esīri aldıḳdan ṣoñra <lb/>ziyāde ṭalebiyle taʿcīz olunmayub teslīm
                    eylemek bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr14244">buyurdum ki</rs>.</ab>


                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1720-01-03" notAfter="1720-01-12">fī evāḫir-i
                            Ṣ<supplied resp="#yy">afer</supplied> sene 1132</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17200103-17200112.2.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>Decree to the district administrator of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15461"
                        >Bihać</rs>:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as
                    grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>,
                    the paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my threshold of felicity [about the following matter]:</ab>

                <ab>It is written and recorded in the imperial letter of agreement
                        (<foreign>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn</foreign>) that it shall be lawful to free the
                    captives who are found in possession of people in an appropriate way with the
                    payment of a potential price that is acceptable and reasonable; in case no
                    agreement is reached with the owner of a captive and a disagreement occurs, the
                    notables shall intermediate between the two parties.</ab>

                <ab>[<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>] reported that a person
                    named <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15669">Plasnič</rs><ref type="note_reference"
                        target="#ftn1"/>, a resident of the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr1690"
                        >Croatian</rs> land from among the subjects of the aforesaid <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, fell prisoner during the
                    war. You are the aforesaid [administrator]: <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr15669">Plasnič</rs> is by you and your captive. Although his
                    liberation was required in return for a reasonable price according to the
                    imperial letter of agreement, you not only withheld the Muslim prisoner and
                    one-hundred sixty golden pieces that were sent to you in exchange for the
                    aforesaid prisoner, but you also demanded an excessive amount of money and did
                    not release the captive. You transgressed in this way in violation of the
                    imperial letter of agreement.</ab>

                <ab>[<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>] requested my imperial
                    decree for you to exchange, in the described way, the Muslim prisoner and the
                    gold previously sent to you for the <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr15669">aforesaid captive</rs> and dispatch the captive to his land.</ab>

                <ab>You are the aforementioned commander! It is written in the imperial letter of
                    agreement that the release of the captives in possession of the people in return
                    for a moderate price is lawful. The limit of moderation was breached by not
                    being content when a Muslim prisoner and the aforesaid amount [of gold] were delivered [to you] in
                    exchange and by demanding additional money. In this way, the conditions of the
                    imperial letter of agreement have been breached. My illustrious
                    edict has been issued that, as declared, after receiving the aforesaid amount of
                    money and the [Muslim] prisoner, no violation shall be committed by demanding
                    more, and [the captive] shall be delivered. So have <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> commanded! </ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1720-01-03" notAfter="1720-01-12">January 3 to
                        January 12, 1720</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
