<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den obersten Richter von Edirne
                    und Russe, den Fall zweier österreichischer Kaufleute zu lösen, die unter
                    Verletzung des kaiserlichen Vertragsschreibens (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>) vom
                    osmanischen Zollbeamten in Russe gezwungen wurden, wiederkehrende Zölle zu
                    zahlen und ihre beschlagnahmten Waren zurückzugeben; Istanbul, 26. August – 5.
                    September 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree addressed to the chief judge of Edirne and the
                    judge of Ruse to settle the case of two Austrian merchants who were forced to
                    pay recurrent customs duty in violation of the imperial letter of agreement
                        (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>) and to return their confiscated goods;
                    Istanbul, August 26 – September 5, 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Edirne mollasına ve Ruscuk kadısına hitaben yazılmış,
                    ahidnameye aykırı olarak mükerreren gümrük vergisi ödemeye zorlanan iki
                    Avusturyalı tüccarın sorununu çözmeleri ve alıkonulan mallarını iade etmeleri
                    hakkında hükmü; İstanbul, 26 Ağustos - 5 Eylül, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190826-17190905</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 67, entry 127</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-08-26" notAfter="1719-09-05"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den obersten Richter von Edirne und Russe, den
                    Fall zweier österreichischer Kaufleute zu lösen, die unter Verletzung des
                    ahidname vom osmanischen Zollbeamten in Russe gezwungen wurden, wiederkehrende
                    Zölle zu zahlen, und ihre beschlagnahmten Waren zurückzugeben; Istanbul, 26.
                    August – 5. September 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu,
                    Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften
                    Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer
                    und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>treatment of Austrian merchants according to the conditions of the
                        imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>returning of confiscated goods to merchants</item>
                    <item>Edirne</item>
                    <item>Russe</item>
                    <item>merchnats</item>
                    <item>trade</item>
                    
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00033_Page_67_Entry_127.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190826-17190905">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">127</metamark>


                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr14060">Edirne</rs>
                    <rs type="person">mollāsı</rs>na ve <rs type="person"><rs type="place"
                            ref="#mpr15657">Ruscuḳ</rs> ḳāḍīsı</rs>na ḥüküm ki</ab>

                <ab><lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından
                    büyükilçilik ile ḥālā der-i devlet-medāruma gelen ḳıdvetü
                    ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye Cenerāl <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Ġrūf de
                        Virmond</rs>
                    <lb/>ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü ʿarż-ı ḥāl gönderüb
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs> tüccārı sefīneleriyle
                    getürdükleri eşyānuñ bir defʿa gümrüklerin <lb/>virdüklerinden ṣoñra emtiʿası
                    fürūḫt olunmayub āḫar iskeleye gitmek iḳtiżā ider ise tekrār gümrük ṭaleb
                    olunmaya diyü ʿahdnāme-i <lb/>ḥumāyūnda mesṭūr ve muḳayyed</ab>
                <ab>iken ḥālā <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs> tüccārlarından <rs
                        type="person">Görgī Ḳravus</rs> ve şerīki <rs type="person">Barġa</rs> nām
                    tācirler sefīneleriyle nehr-i Ṭūna üzerinden <lb/>götürdükleri billūruñ <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr14929">Vidīn</rs>
                    <rs type="person">gümrükçisine</rs> gümrügin bi-t-temām edā ve teslīm ve
                    yedlerine edā teẕkeresi almışlar iken <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657"
                        >Rūscuḳ</rs>’a geldüklerinde <lb/>ẕikr olunan billūrı sefīnelerinden iḫrāc
                    ve ʿarabalara taḥmīl ve <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">İstanbul</rs>’a
                    götürmek üzere iken <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Rūscuḳ</rs> gümrükçisi <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr15836">İsmāʿīl</rs> nām kimesne yedlerinde <lb/>olan
                    edā teẕkeresine iʿtibār itmeyüb ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i ḫumāyūn tekrār bir defʿa daḫī
                    merḳūm tācirlerden gümrük alub ġadr <lb/>ve taʿaddī eyledügin ve ẕikr olunan
                    billūruñ bir miḳdārın <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Edirne</rs>’de
                    alıḳoduḳların bildürüb</ab>
                <ab>ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i ḫumāyūn alınan aḳçaları <lb/>girü aṣḥāb-ı meẕkūrlara redd ve
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Edirne</rs>’de alıḳoduḳları eşyādan daḫī
                    ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i ḫumāyūn tekrār gümrük müṭālebesiyle rencīde <lb/>olmamaları
                    bābında emr-i şerīfüm ricā eylemegin</ab>
                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i ḫümāyūnuma mürācaʿat olunduḳda vech-i meşrūḥ üzere mesṭūr ve muḳayyed
                    bulunmaġın ʿahdnāme-i <lb/>ḫumāyun mūcebince bir defʿa <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14929">Vidīn</rs>’de gümrüklerin edā eyledüklerinden ṣoñra āḫar
                    gümrükde daḫī olunmaḳ iḳtiżā idilmez iken <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657"
                        >Rūscuḳ</rs>
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15836">gümrükçisi</rs>
                    <lb/>ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i ḫumāyūn tekrār gümrük almaġla aldıġı aḳça girü redd ve
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Edirne</rs> gümrüginde alıḳoduḳları eşyānuñ
                    gümrügi ṭaleb olunmayub <lb/>gendülere teslīm olunmaḳ emrüm olmışdur <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr14244">buyurdum ki</rs>. <date type="Hijri"
                        notBefore="1719-08-26" notAfter="1719-09-05">fī evāsıṭ-ı <supplied
                            resp="#yy">Şevvā</supplied>l sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190826-17190905.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>Decree to the <rs type="person">chief judge</rs> of <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14060">Edirne</rs> and the <rs type="person">judge</rs> of <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Russe</rs>:</ab>

                <ab>General <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Graf von Virmont</rs>, the paragon of
                    the great commanders of the community of the Messiah—may God end his days
                    propitiously—who is currently at my gate that is the center of state as grand ambassador from
                    the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, sent a sealed petition
                    to my threshold of felicity. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">He</rs> reported
                    [the following] in that petition: It is written and recorded in the imperial
                    letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>) that
                    no customs duty shall be claimed in case <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718"
                        >Austrian</rs> merchants, having brought their commodities with their ships
                    and paid their customs duties, are not able to sell their commodities and,
                    therefore, are required to move on to another pier.</ab>

                <ab>The <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Austrian</rs> merchants <rs
                        type="person">Görgi Kravus</rs>(?) and his associate <rs type="person"
                        >Barga</rs>(?), having paid and delivered fully to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14929"
                        >Vidin</rs>’s customs superintendent the customs for the crystals they
                    transported over the Danube on their ships and after receiving in their hands the
                    certificate of payment, when they arrived in <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657"
                        >Russe</rs>, as they were about to load off the aforesaid crystal from their
                    ships, transfer to carts, and take it to Istanbul, the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657"
                        >Russe</rs> customs superintendent, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15836"
                        >İsmail</rs>, did not take into consideration the receipt of payment they had
                    in their possession. In violation of the imperial letter of agreement, [<rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr15836">Ismail</rs>] received customs duty again one
                    more time from the aforesaid merchants, thus acting unjustly and oppressing
                    them. Some part of the aforesaid crystal was also withheld in <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14060">Edirne</rs>.</ab>
                <ab>[<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>] requested <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr14244">my</rs> command that the money that has been
                    collected in violation of the imperial letter of agreement shall be returned to
                    the aforementioned merchants and that they shall not be injured again in
                    violation of the imperial letter of agreement by the demand of customs duty for
                    the goods withheld in <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14060">Edirne</rs>.</ab>

                <ab>When my imperial letter of agreement is consulted, it is indeed written and
                    recorded in the way described above. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">I</rs>
                    decree that: While, per the imperial agreement, no customs duty is required at
                    other customs once the customs duties are paid at <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14929">Vidin</rs>, the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15657">Russe</rs>
                    customs superintendent collected customs duties one more time in violation of
                    the imperial letter of agreement. Therefore: the money he collected shall be
                    returned and no customs duty shall be demanded for the goods withheld in <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr14060">Edirne</rs> and the goods shall be delivered
                    back to them. <date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-08-26" notAfter="1719-09-05"
                        >August 26 to September 5, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
