<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über das Treffen von Damian Hugo von Virmont mit Großwesir Ibrahim Pascha 
                    im Vidos Garten, Istanbul, 4. August 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of the meeting of Damian Hugo von Virmont with Grand Vizier Ibrahim Pasha at
                    Vidos Garden, Istanbul, August 4, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un Veziriazam İbrahim Paşa ile Vidos Bahçesi’nde
                    buluşması, İstanbul, 4 Aġustos 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName> Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi </persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>

                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17190904</idno>
                <!-- PID: o:[context].[genre].[language].[date-iso](.[nr])
    # context: 
        vipa for Virmont/Ibrahim Paşa 1719-1720
        qhod ıs outdated, it's only used for the meta context that aggregates the different edition subparts.
# genres:
ad. administrative document
ch. chronicle
in. instruction
l. letter
mh. mühimme
np. newspaper
pr. protocol register
pp. pamphlet
pt. petition
rc. record (Urkunde)
re. receipt
rp. report (Bericht, Relation)
tr. travelogue
# languages:
osm. ottoman source
hbg. habsburg source
# date:
yyyy-mm-dd or yyyy
we use the first known date of creation for handwritten texts 
and for printed ones the date of publication
# nr:
ONLY if a PID would duplicate (e.g. two habsburg letters on the same date) -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <!-- Archive, Library,… -->
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 59-60</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="scribe1">
                                <persName ref="#mpr13114">Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi</persName>
                                <desc><!-- e.g. Written in red ink --></desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1719-09-04"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Encoding guidelines -->
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister über das Treffen von Damian Hugo von Virmont mit Großwesir Ibrahim Pascha im Vidos Garten, Istanbul, 4. August 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG01">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00028b.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG02">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00029a1.jpg" xml:id="IMG02"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190904">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
            <ab>
                <lb/><hi rend="#red">Vidoş Bāġ çesinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisinüñ</rs>
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlete</rs> geldigini
                müşʿirdür. Fī <date type="Hijri" when="1719-09-04">19 <supplied resp="#yy">Şevva</supplied>l sene 1131</date>.</hi></ab>
            <ab><lb/>Yevm-i mezbūrdan bir gün evvel Vidoş Bāġ çesi ḳurbında vāḳiʿ baġ lar kenārına
                <lb/>mehterḫāne-yi ḫāṣṣadan <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> içün iki direklü oṭaḳ ve bir ʿaraba
                <lb/>ve oṭaġ ıñ ṣol ṭarafına bir sāyebān ḳurılub irtesi yevm-i mezbūrda 
                <lb/>ṣāḥib devlet biniş ṭarīḳiyle maḥall-i mezbūra gitmişdür ki ẕikr olunur.</ab>
                
            <ab>Yevm-i mezbūrda
                <lb/>aġ ayān-ı ṣadr-ı ʿālī ve müteferri̇ ḳagān ve çavuşbaşı aġ a ve çavuşlar emīni ve kātibi
                <lb/>ve çavuşān-ı dergāh-ı ʿālī ve binişe meʾmūr olan ricāl biʾl-cümle
                <lb/>ʿaleʾl-seḥer Yedikuleniñ ṭaşrasında deryā kenārında Ḳumluḳ taʿbīr olunan
                <lb/>maḥallde müctemiʿ olmalarıyla <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓ am</rs>ṣandal
                ile ve <rs type="person">nişāncı paşa</rs> daḫı
                <lb/>ardınca ḳayıḳ ile gelüb maḥall-i mezbūra çıḳduḳda </ab>
                
             <ab>herkes süvār olub
                <lb/>tertībleri üzere yürüdükde ṣāhib devletüñ öñince yigirmi bir ʿaded
                <lb/>müzeyyen yedekler yürüyüb alay ile <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>nüñ olduġ ı Ḥazīnedār Çiftliġ iniñ
                <lb/>derūnından mürūr olunub oṭaḳ olan maḥalle nüzūl olunduḳda 
                <lb/><rs type="person">nişāncı paşa</rs> oṭaġ a bile inüb ḳahveler içildükden ṣoñra muḥżır aġ a
                <lb/>ṭāʾifesinden yüz nefer ādem başlarında elvān reng şāl ve dīvān 
                <lb/>dolam<supplied resp="#yy">a</supplied>larıyla müsellaḥ mevcūd olanlarıyla bir defʿa ṭaḳ ımları tamām olunca nişāna
                <lb/>tüfeng atub baʿdehū iç aġ aları süvāren cirīd oynayub ve mehterḫāne <lb/>çalınur idi.</ab> 
                 
                <ab>Bu es̠ nāda  <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisinüñ</rs> sākin olduġ ı maḥall cāy-ı mez̠ kūra
                <lb/>ḳarīb oldıġ ından "<choice resp="#yy"><corr>māniʿleri</corr><sic>maʿnīleri</sic></choice> 
                    yoġ sa gelsin bir miḳdār ṣoḥbet idelim" diyü
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs>  ṭarafından bir aġ a irsāl olunub baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> daḫı
                <lb/>on beş yigirmi ḳadar atlu ādemleriyle geldükde 
                    
                    <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">
                        The difference between the accounts of this meeting here in the Ottoman 
                        protocol register and in the travelogue of the Austrian secretary C. Driesch 
                        is remarkable. According to the Ottoman version, the organization of a festive
                        event nearby the location where the Austrian ambassador was residing was just a coincidence.
                        According to C. Driesch's account, however,  
                        the festive gathering was intentionally organized at a location approximately one-thousand steps
                        away from the Austrian ambassador's residence, that is, at a location extremely close to 
                        where Virmont resided with his entourage. Driesch claimed that the Grand Vizier Nevşehirli Ibrahim Pasha's
                        intention was to meet the Austrian ambassador, but since an Ottoman grand vizier's visit
                        to a European ambassador was unheard of, the grand vizier pretended the occasion to be
                        a coincidence. Based on this assumption, Driesch noted in his travelogue that
                        such a compliment by the grand vizier to Virmont was "quite an extraordinary honor."
                        For a detailed description of this gathering by
                        <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_234">C. Driesch, see pages 234-243.</ref></note>
                        
                    
                    
                    muhżır aġ a ṭāyifesi oṭaḳ zuḳāḳınuñ 
                <lb/>ṭaşrasında dizilüb ve çavuşān ve müteferriḳagān ve aġ ayān oṭaġ uñ
                <lb/>iç ṭarafında ṣaff-beste olduḳları ḥālde zuḳāk ḳapusınuñ iç ṭarafında
                <lb/>oṭaġ a ḳarīb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>nüñ nüzūli içün bir iskemle vażʿ olunmaġ la nüzūl itdürildikden-ṣoñra
                <lb/>çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni öñine düşüb oṭāġ uñ içerüsine götürüb
                <lb/>muk̇ ābele-i ṣadr-ı ʿālīde ḥāżır olan iskemleye oturdılub</ab>
                
            <ab>baʿdehū ṣ adr-ı aʿżam <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>
                <lb/>çavuşbaşı aġ a öñince içerü obadan çıḳub ḥāżirūna selām-dāde olduḳda
                <lb/>selām aġ ası ṣavt-ı bülend ile selām olub ṣadra ḳuʿūd eyledüklerinde çavuşān 
                <lb/>alḳış idüb</ab> 
                
            <ab>baʿdehū ḳahveler içildikden ṣoñra ḳışḳış olub bir sāʿat
                <lb/>miḳdārı maḥfīce ol ḥāl üzere müṣāḥabet eylemişlerdür. Bu es̠snāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> 
                <lb/>ḳırmıżı ṣof ferāceye ḳaplu semūr kürk giymiş ve yed-i şerīflerinde bir incü tesbīḥ 
                <lb/>var idi. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> ḳalḳub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı ārdınca sāyebāna
                <lb/>çıḳduḳlarında <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> yaṣdıḳ üzerine oturdub iç aġ aları cirīd
                <lb/>oynadılar. Ve bu aralıḳda sāde naḳḳāre faṣlı oldu. Cerīdden ṣoñra
                <lb/>nişancı paşa daḫı sāyebāna daʿvet olundı. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devletiñ</rs> yedek
                <lb/>atlarına birer aġ a binüb aşaġ ı ve yuḳaru gezdürdiler. İçlerinden zülfü siyāh
                <lb/>bir ḳula atı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye irkāb içün ihdā olundı.</ab>
                
                <note xml:id="ftn2" type="editorial" resp="#yy">
                    The horse that the grand vizier presented to Virmont as a gift was fully equipped
                    with a horse tack, including a bridle, saddle, stirrups, and an armor gilded with 
                    siver. Driesch noted that <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_240">
                    "the gear was so heavy that the horse had enough weight to carry on it."</ref>
                    As mentioned in the next passage of this protocol entry, Virmont mounted on this horse when
                    leaving.</note>
                
            <ab>Baʿdehū vezīr-i aʿżam ābdest 
                <lb/>içün içerü obaya girüb baʿdehū oṭaġ ıñ içine sofra döşenmekle <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ve nişāncı 
                <lb/>paşa varub oturduḳlarından ṣoñra saʿādetlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezir-i aʿżam</rs> ḳırmıżı ṣof ferāce ile 
                <lb/>içerüden geldükde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>
                ve <rs type="person">nişāncı paşa</rs> ḳıyām eylediler. Ṭāʿām tenāvülinden ṣoñra 
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> ikindi nemāzı içün ḳalḳub içerü gidüb baʿdehū çıḳduḳda 
                <lb/>ḳırmızı ṣofa ḳaplu ḳāḳūm kürk ile gelüb oturdı. ̣Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>ye gidecek 
                <lb/>zamān ḳırmızı ṣofa ḳaplu bir ḳāḳūm kürk ilbās olunub ve ihdāʾ-i ṣadr-ı ʿālī 
                <lb/>olan ḳula āta süvār olub gitdi. Derʿaḳab ṣāhib devlet daḫī süvār 
                <lb/>olmaġ la <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi beg</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devleti</rs> selāmlayub baʿdehū vezīr-i aʿżam ḥażretleri yine 
                <lb/>Yedikullede çıḳduḳları maḥallden ḳayıġ a binüb ʿavdet eylemişlerdür. Ṭaḳıma Dāvud
                <lb/>Paşa’ya gelindükde iz̠ in virilmişdür.</ab>
                
                </div>
                
                <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190808-transl">
                    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>     
              <ab>Report indicating the arrival of the Austrian <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> for a meeting with the 
                  <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> at Vidos Garden on August 4, 1719</ab>
                    
              <ab>A day before the meeting day, a large two-poled tent was supplied from the inventory of the sultan’s tent pitchers 
                  (<foreign xml:lang="tr">mehterḫāne-yi ḫāṣṣa</foreign>) and was erected next to the vineyards in the vicinity of Vidos Garden.
                  A carriage was prepared at the same location and a canopy was set up on the
                  left-hand side of the tent. On the day of the meeting, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> rode to the said location 
                  as will be described here.</ab>

                    <ab>On that day, the aghas of the office of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, court officals (<foreign xml:lang="tr">müteferri̇ḳagān</foreign>), 
                  the agha, the secretary, and the intendant of the palace ushers along with court ushers
                  and others, who had been commissioned to join the convoy, gathered together at dawn
                  next to the sea in the environs of <rs type="place">Yedikule</rs> (Seven Towers) at the location called Ḳumluk. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>
                        came by a <foreign xml:lang="tr">sandal</foreign> (a European style row-boat) and the <rs type="person">chancellor</rs> followed him with a caique
                  and landed at the aforesaid location.</ab>
                    
              <ab>Everyone mounted their horses and advanced in accordance with their customary order.
                  Twenty-one uniformed reserve militiamen preceded the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and [they] paraded through 
                  the interior precincts of the Hazinedar Farm where the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was stationed – and, 
                  when they arrived [to the] place where the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s tent was situated, the
                  Ottoman <rs type="person">chancellor</rs> [dismounted and] entered the tent as well and coffee was served.
                  Next, one-hundred men from among the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s guard (<foreign xml:lang="tr">muḥżır aġ a ṭāʾifesi</foreign>),
                  who were present [at that location] equipped with their weapons and adorned with multi-colored scarfs
                  and long robes they wear when attending the imperial council, 
                  they performed the target practice exercise with 
                  their muskets. Thereafter, the aghas of the inner court pages 
                  performed javelin exercises on their horses while the military band played.</ab> 
                  
              <ab>At this moment, since [the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>] had arrived close by
                  the location where the Austrian <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was located, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> 
                  sent an agha to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> asking him to join the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> 
                  for a brief friendly conversation if the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> saw no obstacle to doing so.
                  Next, when the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came along with his fifteen to twenty mounted attendants,<ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/> 
                  
                  <!--<note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                      The difference between the accounts of this meeting here in the Ottoman 
                      protocol register and in the travelogue of the Austrian secretary C. Driesch 
                      is remarkable. According to the Ottoman version, the organization of a festive
                      event nearby where the Austrian ambassador was residing was just a coincidence.
                      <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_234">According to C. Driesch's account</ref>, 
                      the festive gathering was intentionally organized at a location one-thousand steps
                      away from the Austrian ambassador's residence. Driesch claimed that Nevşehirli Ibrahim Pasha's
                      intention was to visit the Austrian ambassador, but since an Ottoman grand vizier's visit
                      to a European ambassador was unheard of, Ibrahim Pasha pretended the occasion to be
                      a coincidence. Based on this assumption, Driesch noted in his travelogue that
                      such a compliment by the grand vizier to Virmont was a "quite an extraordinary honor."
                      For a detailed description of this gathering, see C. Driesch, pages 234-243.</note>-->
                  
                  the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s guard set up ranks outside the passageway to the tent, while the palace ushers,
                  court officials (<foreign xml:lang="tr">müteferri̇ ḳagān</foreign>), and aghas stood in line inside the passageway.
                  In addition, inside the gate of the passageway, a stool was positioned close to the entrance 
                  to the tent for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> to sit down. After the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> arrived [and dismounted from his horse], 
                  the secretary and the intendant of the palace ushers went ahead of him and brought him into the tent, 
                  and made him sit down on the stool that was ready opposite the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>.</ab>
              
              
             <ab>Next, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> <pb n="2" facs="#IMG02"/>
                  came out of the inner room ahead of the agha of the palace ushers and saluted
                  those who were present, upon which the master of ceremonies saluted with a loud voice.
                  When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> took his place on the prime ministerial seat, the palace ushers applauded.</ab>
                    
             <ab>After coffee was drunk, a confidential conversation continued for the better part of about 
                 an hour. During this time, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> was wearing
                 a sable fur on a fine red cloak, and in his honorable hand, he had a pearl rosary.
                 Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> stood up and went outside to the canopy, followed by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>.
                 The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat on a pillow and the pages of the inner court played javelins.
                 Meanwhile, a single kettle-drum performance took place. After the javelin game was over,
                 the <rs type="person">chancellor</rs> was invited to join them. Next, each of the aghas mounted on
                 one of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>’s reserve horses and rode them back and forth. From among these horses,
                 a buckskin colored horse with black locks was presented as a gift to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> 
                 for him to ride.<ref target="#ftn2" type="note_reference"/></ab>
                    
                    <!--<note type="footnote" resp="#yy">
                        The horse that the grand vizier presented to Virmont as a gift was fully equipped
                        with a horse tack, including a bridle, saddle, stirrups, and an armor gilded with 
                        siver. Driesch noted that <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_240">
                            "the gear was so heavy that the horse had enough weight to carry on it."</ref>
                        As mentioned in the next passage of the current protocol entry, Virmont mounted on this horse when
                        leaving.</note>-->
                 
             <ab>Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> entered the inner room for ablution. Afterwards, a meal was spread out
                 inside the tent. After the <rs type="person">chancellor</rs> had come in and sat down, his excellency, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>
                 came inside with a red camlet cloak, upon which the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                 and the <rs type="person">chancellor</rs> stood up
                 to salute him. After eating the meal, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> stood up to perform the afternoon prayer
                 and went inside. Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> came out wearing an ermine fur on
                 red mohair and sat down. As the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was about to leave,
                 the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> had [the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>] 
                 dressed with an ermine fur on red mohair. The ambassador then mounted the buckskin horse
                 presented to him by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and departed.
                 After that, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> himself also
                 mounted [a horse]. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> saluted the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and thereafter the grand
                 vizier again embarked on a caique at Yedikule (Seven Towers) from the same location where he had landed
                 and [he] returned. The commissioned officials were given leave to return to their
                 posts when the vizier’s retinue arrived at Davud Paşa.</ab> 
       
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>