<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über die Abschiedsaudienz von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Sultan, Istanbul,
                    2. April, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of the departure audience of Damian Hugo von Virmont with the Sultan, Istanbul, 
                    Istanbul, April 2, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defter kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un veda töreni için Sultan’ın
                    huzuruna kabulü, İstanbul, 2 Nisan 1720</title>
                
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName> Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi </persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>

                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200402</idno>
                <!-- PID: o:[context].[genre].[language].[date-iso](.[nr])
    # context: 
        vipa for Virmont/Ibrahim Paşa 1719-1720
        qhod ıs outdated, it's only used for the meta context that aggregates the different edition subparts.
# genres:
ad. administrative document
ch. chronicle
in. instruction
l. letter
mh. mühimme
np. newspaper
pr. protocol register
pp. pamphlet
pt. petition
rc. record (Urkunde)
re. receipt
rp. report (Bericht, Relation)
tr. travelogue
# languages:
osm. ottoman source
hbg. habsburg source
# date:
yyyy-mm-dd or yyyy
we use the first known date of creation for handwritten texts 
and for printed ones the date of publication
# nr:
ONLY if a PID would duplicate (e.g. two habsburg letters on the same date) -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> 
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <!-- Archive, Library,… -->
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 78</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="scribe1">
                                <persName ref="#mpr13114">Teşrifatçıbaşı Selman Efendi</persName>
                                <desc><!-- e.g. Written in red ink --></desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1720-04-02"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Encoding guidelines -->
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Protokollregister über die Abschiedsaudienz von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Sultan, Istanbul, 2. April, 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG01">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00038a.jpg" xml:id="IMG01"/>
        </surface>
        
    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200402">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
                      
            <ab><lb/><hi rend="#red"><date type="#Hijri" notBefore="1719" notAfter="1720">Biñ yüz otuz bir senesinde</date> ṣulḥnāme <add place="superlinear">ile</add>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe çāsārı</rs> ṭarafından
                <lb/>Āsitāneye gelen <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">kebīr ilçinüñ</rs> ʿavdete meʾẕūn olub nāme-i hümāyūnı aldıġ ı gün
                <lb/>vāḳiʿ olan keyfiyetdir. Der sene</hi> <date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-02">1132
                    fī 23 C<supplied resp="#yy">emaziyülevvel</supplied></date></ab>
                
                <ab><lb/><date type="#Hijri" when="1720-04-02">Māh-ı mezbūruñ yigirmi üçünci Ṣalı güni</date> 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe çāsārı</rs> ṭarafından ṣulḥnāme ile gelen
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">kebīr ilçi</rs> ʿavdete meʾẕūn olub dīvān-ı hümāyūnda nāmesin almaġ la ẕikr olunur.</ab>
                
                <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy"><ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_397">The Austrian secretary C. Driesch noted the date of the 
                audience as April 3, 1720.</ref></note>
                
            <ab><lb/>Yevm-i mezbūrda ġ alebe dīvān olub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> içün muʿtād üzere dīvān 
                <lb/>bisāṭı ile müzeyyen at ve begzādegān ve etbāʿı içün daḫı yüz otuz ḳadar 
                <choice><corr>eyerlenmiş</corr><sic>egerlenmiş</sic></choice>
                <lb/>atlar iskeleye irsāl ve çavuşbaşı aġ a ve kātib ve emīn ve ḳırḳ elli miḳdārı
                <lb/>çavuşān iskeleye varub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūrı</rs> alay ile sarāy-ı hümāyūna getürüb</ab>
                
            <ab><lb/>dergāh-ı ʿālī yeñiçerileri çorbaya segirdecekleri zemān içerü ḳonub seyr
                <lb/>ve temāşā iderek ḳubbeye ḳarīb geldükde devletlü <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣadr-ı ʿālī ḥażretleri</rs> ḳoltuḳ
                <lb/>oṭasına gidüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> derūn-i ḳubbeye dāḫıl oldıġ ı gibi
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> daḫı içerüden berü gelüb vüzerāʾ-i iʿżām ve ahālī-yi dīvān 
                <lb/>ḳıyām eyledüklerinde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> ḥażretlerine ḳarşudan temennī idüb
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> daḫı muʿāmele-i nevāziş göstererek ḳuʿūd eyledüklerinde</ab>
                
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi                
                <lb/>mezbūr</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">Nişāncı vezīr-i mükerrem Muṣṭafā Paşa</rs> ḥażretlerinüñ altında ṭūlānī 
                <lb/>ṣofanuñ üzerine oturub baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> baştercümānı çaġ ırub
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiniñ</rs> ḥāl-i ḫaṭırın suʾāl itdürdi. Baʿdehū dīvān ḳurılub meṣāliḥ-i 
                <lb/>ʿibād görüldükden ṣoñra ṭaʿām gelüb <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> ile begzādegānı vüzerāʾ-i
                <lb/>iʿẓām ve defterdārān ile iṭʿām olunub</ab>
                
            <ab>baʿde’l-ṭaʿām ʿarż olmaḳ üzere
                <lb/>ḥużūr-i hümāyūna <corr>telḫīṣ</corr><sic>telḥīṣ</sic> olunub ḫaṭt-ı hümāyūn ile müşerref 
                    <corr>telḫīṣi</corr><sic>telḥīṣi</sic> ḳapucılar ketḫüdāsı
                <lb/>getürdükde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓ am</rs> ḥażretleri derūn-i ḳubbenüñ vasaṭını tecāvüz iderek
                <lb/>istiḳbāl idüb baʿdehū gelüb yerine oturduḳda işāret-i ʿaliyye mūcebince
                <lb/>çavuşbaşı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiyi</rs> ḥazīne öñine götürüb gendüye ferāce yeñlü serāsere ḳablu semūr kürk
                <lb/>ve begzādegān ve etbāʿına daḫı rūznāmçede ḳayd olunduġ u miḳdār ḫilʿatler ilbās
                <lb/>olunub</ab>
                
            <ab>baʿdehū <rs type="person">yeñiçeri aġ ası</rs> ʿarża girüb baʿdehū ḳażʿasker efendiler ʿarża
                <lb/>girüb çıḳduḳdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">vezīr-i aʿẓam</rs> ve sāʾir vüzerā ḥużūr-i hümāyūna girüb baʿdehū 
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> daḫı kendi ile on altı nefer ʿarż a ḳonub ḥuẓūr-i hümāyūnda nāmesin <unclear>alub</unclear>
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçinüñ</rs> sırkātibi elleri üzerinde ṭaşra çıḳarmışdur.
                <note xml:id="ftn2" type="editorial" resp="#yy">For the speech Virmont delivered in the presence of the sultan,
                    <ref target="/o:vipa.tr.hbg.1723#facs_400">see the travelogue of C. Driesch.</ref></note></ab>
                
                
                
            <ab>Bu günde ḳapucıbaşılardan
                <lb/>baʿżıları meʾmūren ṭaşralarda bulunmaġ la müteferriḳagāndan altı yedi nefer ḳapucı
                <lb/>başılar ṭaḳımı ile Bābüʾl-saʿādede mevcūd itdürilmiş-idi. Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ṭaşra
                <lb/>çıḳub orta ḳapunuñ <choice><corr>ḫāricinde</corr><sic>ḥāricinde</sic></choice> ṭaraf-ı ciḥ āndārīden iʿṭā ve iḥsān 
                <lb/>olunan dīvān bisāṭlu ata süvār olub</ab>
            
            <ab>ḫāṣṣ fırūn dīvārı cānibinde
                <lb/>at üzerinde ṭurub erbāb-ı dīvān biʾl-cümle mürūr idince temāşā
                <lb/>itdürilüb baʿdehū çavuşlar kātibi ve emīni ve çavuşān ile iskeleye <unclear reason="illegible">degin</unclear>
                <lb/>alay ile götürilmişdür. Ancaḳ çavuşbaşı ʿavdetde gitmek ḳānūn olmamaġ la gitmemişdür.</ab>
                </div>
                
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17190402-transl">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG01"/>
                <ab>The circumstances on the day when the Austrian <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">grand ambassador</rs>, who had been
                    dispatched by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Austrian emperor</rs> to Istanbul with a peace settlement <date notBefore="1718-11-24" notAfter="1719-11-13">in the
                    year 1131 (November 24, 1718–November 13, 1719)</date>, was given permission to return
                    [to Austria] and received the sultanic letter [addressed to the emperor]; April 2, 1720.
                    <ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/></ab>
                
                
                
                <ab>The following relates what happened on <date type="#Hijri" when="1720-04-02">the twenty-third day of the said month, a
                    Tuesday</date>, when the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">grand ambassador</rs> – 
                    who had been dispatched by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Austrian emperor</rs> 
                    with a peace settlement – was given permission to return [to Austria] and
                    received his [sultanic] letter inside the imperial council room.</ab>
                
                <ab>On that day, a festive imperial council meeting took place (for the payment of
                    janissary salaries). As per custom, a horse adorned with an imperial ceremonial
                    saddle was prepared for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, while one-hundred-and-thirty saddled horses
                    were prepared for his noblemen and attendants, which were dispatched to the
                    pier. The agha of the palace ushers, the secretary, and the intendant [of the palace ushers], along with
                    another forty to fifty palace ushers, went to the pier and paraded with the
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> back to the palace.</ab>
                
                <ab>As the janissaries of the court were about <q>“to dash to the soup,”</q>
                    (<foreign xml:lang="tr">çorbaya segirdecekleri zemān</foreign>)
                    the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was brought in and advanced to the imperial
                    council room watching [the janissaries]. Meanwhile, his highness the grand
                    vizier advanced to the antechamber (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳoltuḳ oṭası</foreign>). As soon as the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                    was brought inside the imperial council room, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> also came inside.
                    The viziers of the imperial council and other functionaries of the council had
                    all risen to their feet. From across the room, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> expressed his good
                    wishes to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, who returned the gesture by showing courtesy to the
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and sat down.</ab>
                
                <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat on the long bench below the revered
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">Chancellor Vizier Mustafa Pasha</rs>. After that, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> summoned the chief interpreter and
                    had him enquire about the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s well-being. Next, the imperial council
                    began and the usual affairs of [the] people were addressed. Then the meal came. During
                    the meal, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat together with the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs>, while his noblemen
                    ate together with the viziers of the imperial council and the chief
                    treasurer.</ab>
                
                <ab>After the meal, a grand vizieral report was submitted [to the sultan 
                    asking for permission to be accepted] to the imperial presence.
                    The agha of palace gatekeepers then brought back the
                    grand vizieral report, which now contained the imperial rescript on it, upon
                    which the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> moved forward, walked past the middle of the room, and then came
                    back and sat down on his place. Then, as per the instruction by the sultan,
                    the agha of palace ushers brought the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> in front of the treasury room. The
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> himself was dressed with a sable fur on a brocade cloak with
                    mohair sleeves and his noblemen and attendants were dressed with robes of
                    honor in the amount that has been registered in the registry of daily
                    expenses.</ab>
                
                <ab>Then, the agha of the janissaries entered the presence of the sultan. Next, the
                    military judges [of Rumelia and Anatolia] entered the sultan’s presence and came
                    outside. Then, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier</rs> and the viziers of the imperial council entered
                    the presence of the sultan. Next, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was taken into the presence of
                    the sultan along with his sixteen attendants. He took his letter in
                    the presence of the sultan and, as the letter was on the hands of the
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s private secretary, they came back outside.
                    <ref target="#ftn2" type="note_reference"/></ab>
                
                
                
                <ab>On this day, some of the court gatekeepers (<foreign xml:lang="tr">ḳapucıbaşılar</foreign>) were assigned duties outside the
                    court. Therefore, six to seven head gatekeepers from among the court officials
                    (<foreign xml:lang="tr">müteferriḳagān</foreign>) were deployed with their units at the Gate of Felicity. After
                    that, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> went outside and, outside of the middle gate, he mounted a
                    horse gifted by the sultan and saddled with an imperial ceremonial saddle.</ab>
                
                <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> stood remained mounted on the horse by the imperial bakery and watched all the
                    members of the imperial council walk by. After that, was paraded
                    to the pier accompanied by the secretary and the intendant of the palace ushers
                    and some palace ushers. Since it was not customary for the agha
                    of the palace ushers to accompany the return [convoy] he did not go.</ab>
            </div>    
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>