<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://qhod.acdh-dev.oeaw.ac.at/gamsdev/qhod/schema/qhod_volledition.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Letter of Ahmed III to the Austrian Emperor Charles VI, Istanbul, March 20 to 30, 1720 (Istanbul copy)</title>
                <title xml:lang="de">Ahmed III. an Karl VI., Istanbul, 20. bis 30. März (Kopie aus Istanbul)</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">3. Ahmed’in Avusturya İmparatoru 6. Karl’a mektubu, 20 ila 30 Mart 1720, (İstanbul kopyası)</title>
                <author><persName>Ahmed III</persName></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Jakob</forename>
                        <surname>Sonnberger</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan
                    Studies</publisher>
                <distributor>Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan
                    Studies</distributor>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>CC-BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.l.osm.17200320.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title> <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title> <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Nāme-i Hümayūn Defterleri</collection>
                        <idno>Register no. 6, letter no. 284</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 Seiten</p>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/101094108">Ahmed III</persName>
                    <date when="1720-03-20">1720-03-20</date>
                    <placeName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://sws.geonames.org/745044/">Istanbul</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118560107">Karl VI</persName>
                    <placeName ana="MPRautomatched" ref="https://sws.geonames.org/2761369/ https://sws.geonames.org/2761369/">Vienna</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Osmanisches Türkisch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Once we have a serious documentation of our encoding guidelines, we have to
                    reference them here.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.l" type="context"> Briefe </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Online Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie (1500-1918) </ref>
                </ab>
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Ahmed III. an Karl VI., Istanbul, 20. bis 30. März (Kopie aus Istanbul), bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSNMH_d_00006_00241.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div type="transcription" xml:id="vipa.l.osm.17200320.1">
            <pb facs="#IMG1" n="1"/>
                
                <metamark function="archival"><lb/>468</metamark>
            
                <ab><lb/><hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Ṭaraf-ı humāyūndan</rs>
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Nemçe çāsārına</rs> gönderilen
                <lb/>nāme-i humāyūndur.</hi></ab>
                
            <ab type="Inscriptio/Unvân"><lb/>İftiḫārü’l-ümerāʾi’l-ʿiẓāmi’l-ʿĪseviyye, muḫtārü’l-küberāʾi’l-fiḫāmi’l-mesīḥiyye,
                muṣliḥu maṣāliḥi cemāḥīri<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/>
                <lb/>’ṭ-ṭāʾifeti’n-̣̣̣Naṣrāniyye, sāḥibu eẕyāli’l-ḥaşmet ve’l-veḳār, ṣāḥibu
                delāʾili’l-mecd ve’l-ịʿtibār
                <lb/>ḥālā Roma İmparaṭorı ulu dostumuz <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Ḳārūlūs</rs></ab>
                
                <ab type="Salutatio/Duâ"><foreign xml:lang="ar">ḫatem allahu ʿavāḳıbehū bi’l-ḫayr ve’r-reşād ve elheme
                    <lb/>ileyhi sebīle’ṣ-ṣavāb ve’s-sedād</foreign></ab>
                
                <ab type="Notificatio">tevḳīʿ-i refīʿ-i hümāyūn vāṣıl
                        olıcaḳ maʿlūm ola ki:</ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"><foreign xml:lang="ar">Cenāb-ı
                    <lb/>vācibü’l-vücūd ve müfīż-i vücūd-i her mevcūd tenezzehe ẕātuhū ʿani’t-tenāhī
                    ve’l-ḥudūd</foreign> ḥażretlerinüñ
                <lb/>ʿināyet-i bī-gāyeti ve iki cihān sürūrı ḥabīb-i ḫüdā şefīʿ-i rūz-i cezā 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14853">Muḥammedü’l-Muṣṭafā</rs> <foreign xml:lang="ar">ṣallāllāhu
                    <lb/>ʿaleyhi ve sellem</foreign> ḥażretlerinüñ muʿcizāt-ı
                kes̠īretü’l-berekātiyle melceʾ-i şāhān-ı cihān ve melāẕ-ı ḫüsrevān-ı
                <lb/>ʿālīşān olan dergāh-ı maʿdelet-bünyān ve bārgāh-ı raṣīnü’l-erkānumuza mābeynde
                ʿaḳd olunan
                <lb/>ṣulḥ ve ṣalāḥı teʾkīd ve bünyān-ı muṣāfāt ve müsālemeti tarṣīn ü teşyīd içün
                ṭarafuñuzdan
                <lb/>baʿs̠ ve irsāl olunan muʿteber ve müsteşāruñuz ve munteḫab ve mümtāz
                büyük ilçiñiz ̣
                <lb/>ḳıdvetu ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye Cenerāl <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Ġrūf de
                    Virmond</rs> ḫutimet ʿavāḳıbuhu bi’l-ḫayr </ab> 
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"> maḳarr-ı serīr-i
                <lb/>salṭanat-ı ʿos̠mānī ve taḫtgāh-ı saʿādet-destgāh-ı ciḥānbānī olan maḥmiyye-i
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">Ḳosṭanṭıniyyeye</rs>
                <lb/>vuṣūl buldukda muʿtād-ı ḳadīm-i ebā-i bülend-evṣāf ve deʾb-i müstedīm-i
                    eslāf-ı saʿādet-<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/>
                <lb/>ittiṣāfumuz üzere ṣudūr-i iz̠n-i hümāyūn-i şāhāne ve ẓuhūr-ı ruḫṣat-ı
                ʿināyet-maḳrūn-i
                <lb/>padişāhānemüz ile pīşgāh-ı serīr-i aʿlāmuza cebīn-sā ve rikāb-ı kāmyāb-ı
                mülūkānemüze
                <lb/>teblīġine meʾmūr olduġı pīşkeş ve hedāyā ile nāme-i muṣādaḳat-nümā ve
                muṣālahat-intimāñuzı
                <lb/>iblāġ ve teslīm ve şol ki mā-beynde teʾkīd ve teʾsīs olan dostluḳ ve ḳoñşuluḳ
                muḳteżāsıdır</ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil"><lb/>resm-i ḳadīm üzere ke-mā yenbaġī tatmīm eyledükden ṣoñra ayīn-i güzīn-i dūdmān-ı
                şevket-āşiyān-ı ḫāḳānī
                <lb/>ve ̣̣kānūn-ı dīrīn-i ḫāndān-ı saʿādet-nişān-ı ʿos̠mānī üzere 
                düstūr-i ekrem, müşīr-i efḫam                 
                <cb/>
                <metamark function="archival"><lb/>469</metamark>
                
                <lb/>niẓāmü’l-ʿālem, nāẓımu menāẓımi’l-ümem, müdebbirü umūri’l-cumhūr bi’l-fikri’s̠-s̠āḳıb 
                mütemmimu mehāmmi’l-enām bi’r-reʾyi<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/> 
                <lb/>’ṣ-ṣāʾib, mümehhidu bünyān-ı devlet ve’l-iḳbāl, müşeyyid-i erkān-ı saʾādet ve’l-iclāl,  
                mükemmilu nāmūsi<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/> 
                <lb/>’s-saltaneti’l-ʿuẓmā, mürettibu merātibi’l-ḫilāfeti’l-kübrā, 
                el-maḥfūfu bi-sunūfi ʿavāṭıfi’l-meliki<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/> 
                <lb/>’l-aʿlā, vezir-i aʿẓam-ı sütūde-şiyem ve vekīl-i muṭlaḳ-ı ̣̣kaviyyü’l-himem ve 
                dāmād-ı muḥteremim <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">İbrāhīm Paşa</rs>
                <lb/><foreign xml:lang="ar">edāma llahu teʿālā iclālehū ve żāʿafa bi’l-teʾyīd
                    iḳtidārehu</foreign> vesāṭetiyle gerek nāme-i muḫālaṣat-<lb break="no" rend="#shy"/>
                <lb/>ʿalāmeñüz terceme-i mef̣hūm-i meveddet-mersūmı ve gerek 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiñüz-i mūmā ileyhiñ</rs>
                dostluḳ teʾyīdine
                <lb/>müteʿallıḳ taḳrīrāt-ı ṣadāḳat-mevsūmı bārgāh-ı şevket-penāh-ı ḫusrevānemüze
                ʿarż ve telḫīṣ
                <lb/>olunub</ab>                
                
                <ab type="Manifestatio">ḫulūṣ ve meveddetüñüze ʿilm-i cihān-ārāy-ı mülūkānemiz şāmil ve 
                    ṭaraf-ı salṭanat-ı seniyyemüzden
                <lb/>daḫi müvālāt ve muṣādaḳatuñuza muvāfaḳat olunmaġla dostluḳ ve müsālemet ve
                ḳoñşuluḳ
                <lb/>ḥuḳūḳına ṭarafeynden riʿāyet ve ḥürmetüñ ās̠ārı ḥāṣıl olmaġın
                    eyyām-ı muṣālaḥa ve hengām-ı
                <lb/>müsālemede ebāʾ-ı kirām ve ecdād-ı ʿiẓām-ı ʿālī-maḳāmımızıñ ʿādet-i müstemirre
                ve ḫaṣlet-i müstaḳarreleri
                    <lb/>olan üslūb-ı merġūb üzere <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">ṭaraf-ı eşref-i ḫüsrevānemizden</rs> merāsim-i vedād ve
                vifāḳ ve maʿāḳıd-ı
                <lb/>ʿaḥd ve mīs̠āḳ-ı ḳaviyyu’l-vis̠āḳa ke-mā yenbagī mürāʿāt ve żavābıṭ ve revābıṭ-ı
                muṣālaḥāt ḥıfẓ
                <lb/>u ṣıyānet olunmaḳ muḳarrer ve muḥaḳḳaḳdur.</ab>
                
                <ab type="Dispositio/Hüküm">Ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiñiz</rs> mūmā ileyh merāsim-i risālet ve levāzım-ı sefāreti
                <lb/>ḥüsn-i ādāb ile tekmīl ve edā ve ʿavdet ve inṣirāfa iẕn-i hümāyūn-ı
                pādişāhānemüzi istidʿā
                <lb/>itmekle tekrār <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14984">dīvān-ı şāmihü’l-bünyān-ı ḫüsrevāne</rs>
                ve <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14841">ḥużūr-ı lāmiʿu’n-nūr-ı mülūkānemüzde</rs>
                <lb/>teşrīfāt-ı muʿtebere-i şāhānemüz ile şeref-yāb ve iḥrāz-ı mufāḫaret ve mübāhāt
                eyledükden ṣoñra
                <lb/>ʿaḳd ve teşyīd olunan musāleme ve muvādeʿanun kemāl-i istiḥkām ve istiḳrārını müşʿir
                <lb/>nāme-i humāyūn-i şevket-maḳrūnumuz ile ṭarafuñuza munṣarıf ve müteveccih
                olmışdur.</ab>
            
                <ab type="Sanctio/Teʾyid"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Lede’l-vüṣūl</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">nāme-i
                <lb/>hümāyunumuzuñ</rs> mażmūn-ı meveddet-nişān ve mefḥūm-ı muṣālaḥat-ʿünvānına 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">ʿilmüñüz</rs> lāḥiḳ olduḳda
                <lb/>merāsim-i dostī ve vifāḳ ve revābıṭ-ı ʿahd ve mīs̠āḳ ṭarafuñuzdan daḫi ʿalā
                vechi’l-etemm ve’l-ekmel
                <lb/>mürāʿāt olunmaḳ melḥūẓ-ı hümāyūnumuzdur. <foreign xml:lang="ar">Ve’s̠-s̠elāmu ʿalā
                    men ittebeʿa’l-<choice><sic>h</sic><corr>ḫ</corr></choice>üdā</foreign>.</ab>
                <ab type="Datatio/Tarih"><lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1720-03-20">Fī evāsıṭı C<supplied resp="#yy">emaziyyülevvel</supplied> sene <supplied resp="#yy">1</supplied>132</date></ab>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.l.osm.17200320.1-transl">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                
                <ab>The sultanic letter dispatched by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">sultan</rs>
                    to the Austrian <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">caesar</rs>: </ab>
                
                <ab type="Inscriptio/Unvân">Laudable pride of the great commanders of Christendom, the elite of
                    illustrious magnates in the community of the Messiah, arbiter of
                    the universal affairs of the community of Nazarene, possessor of the lineage of
                    majesty and glory, possessor of manifestation of splendor and reverence, currently
                    the Roman emperor, our exalted friend <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Karl</rs></ab>
                
                <ab type="Salutatio/Duâ"> — may God end his days propitiously
                    on the right path and inspire him to the path of righteousness and good deed.</ab>
                
                <ab type="Notificatio"> May it be known as my sublime sultanic signature arrives: </ab>
                    
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">Your esteemed councilor and chosen and distinguished grand ambassador,
                        paragon of the great commanders of the community of the Messiah,
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Graf von Virmont</rs> —
                    may God end his days propitiously — who, in order to reinforce the peace
                    and amity that was concluded between the two sides and to consolidate
                    and make firmer the structure of true friendship and reconciliation, is sent
                    and dispatched from you to my court - which is the shelter of the kings of
                    the world and the refuge of the illustrious monarchs, the edifice of equity
                    and a chamber for the firm pillars of state by virtue of the endless grace
                    of his majesties the necessity being whose being showers down abundantly
                    on everything that exists and whose essence surpasses limits
                    and boundaries and [by virtue of] the abundant and bountiful miracles
                    of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14853">Muhammad Mustafa</rs>, the joy of the two worlds, the beloved of God,
                    the intercessor on the day of judgment, may Allah's peace and blessings be upon him. </ab>
                    
                    
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">As [<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the ambassador</rs>] 
                    arrived in the protected [city of] <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">Constantinople</rs> - the seat
                    of the sultanic throne of the Ottomans and the capital of the felicitous
                    court of the keeper of the world - he rubbed his forehead in prostration in the presence of
                    our exalted throne as per the ancient habit of [our] fathers
                    of exalted ranks and the continuous custom of fortunate predecessors, upon the
                    issuance of a splendid imperial allowance and the occurrence of our favorable 
                    sultanic permission, and he, as a requirement of the friendship and
                    neighborliness strengthened and established between the two sides, 
                    conveyed and delivered the offerings, gifts, and the letter of sincere
                    friendship and reconciliation that <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">he</rs>
                    was charged with communicating to our prosperous royal stirrup. </ab>
                
                <ab type="Narratio/Nakil">After that has been accomplished, as before according to the time-honored practice, 
                    both the translation of the affectionate content of 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">your</rs> letter of sincere friendship
                    and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">your</rs> 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">aforementioned envoy</rs>’s written notification of faithfulness for
                    the affirmation of friendship are submitted and summarized to our majestic, royal court
                    as per the majestic, imperial, distinguished ceremonies of [our] household and
                    the felicitous, cheerful, old Ottoman custom, through the intermediation of the 
                    most noble vizier, illustrious field marshal, order of the world, 
                    arranger of order of mankind, prudent manager of the affairs of the community with decisive reasoning,
                    consummator of the important affairs of the mankind with proper judgement,
                    arranger of the pillars of prosperity and felicity, edifice of the pillars of felicity and glory,                    
                    completer of the honor of the great sultanate, orderer of the ranks of the greatest caliphate,
                    invested by arrays of favors of the supreme Lord, my laudable grand vizier,
                    my absolute deputy and firm helper, my respected son-in-law, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">İbrahim Pasha</rs>
                    - my God almighty make his glory lasting and may strengthen his government with his help.
                    </ab>
                
                <ab type="Manifestatio"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Your</rs> sincerity and friendship
                    are thus grasped by <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">our</rs> world-adorning royal
                    knowledge and from our lofty sultanate consent is given to
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">your</rs> friendship and mutual
                    confidence. Thus, as signs of observance of and respect for the law of friendship,
                    reconciliation, and neighborliness have been achieved, as per the continuous
                    custom and consistent habit that became the agreeable practice of our high-ranked,
                    great ancestors and noble forefathers during the days of peace and times of reconciliation,                     
                    as before, from <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">our noblest royal side</rs>,
                    the observation of friendly ceremonies and concord 
                    and [the observation of] being a party to an agreement and abidance by that
                    firm treaty is definite and certain, as well as the protection and guarding
                    of the propriety and regulations of reconciliation.
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Dispositio/Hüküm">And <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">your aforementioned ambassador</rs>
                    accomplished and performed the ceremonies of messengership and 
                    the necessities of an ambassadorship with good manners and appealed for our imperial sultanic 
                    permission. Thereupon, he was again dignified and attained honor and a reason for just pride
                    through our majestic, solid ceremonial at 
                    <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14984"> our royal, lofty edifice of the imperial council</rs>
                    and <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14841">kingly, brilliant presence</rs>. 
                    Thereafter, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">he</rs> departed and set out
                    on the road in <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">your</rs> direction
                    with <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">our</rs> royal sultanic letter that reports the perfect firmness and permanence 
                    of the peace and reconciliation that was concluded and reinforced.
                </ab>
                
                <ab type="Sanctio/Teʾyid">When <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">he</rs> arrives and as the affectionate purview of 
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">our</rs> sultanic letter and its
                    reconciliatory conception becomes known to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">you</rs>, it is our imperial expectation that
                    on your side too, the friendly ceremonies, harmony, regulations of agreement, and the treaty
                    will be observed in a complete and perfect manner.Peace be unto whomever obeys God.</ab>
                    <ab type="Datatio/Tarih"> <date when="1720-03-20">March 20, 1720</date>.</ab>                                     

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>