<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Abschrift des sultanischen Dekrets (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) über die Ernennung von Vincenzo
                    Moroni als Dolmetscher für die Insel Chios; Istanbul, 14. Dezember – 23.
                    Dezember 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Copy of the sultan’s imperial charter (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) appointing Vincenzo Moroni as
                    interpreter to the island of Chios; Istanbul, December 14 – December 23,
                    1719</title>


                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Sakız adasına Vincenzo Moroni’nin tercüman olarak
                    atanması hakkında beratı (nīşān-ı hümāyūn); İstanbul, 14 Aralık – 24 Aralık,
                    1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17191214-17191223.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 73, entry 148</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-12-14" notAfter="1719-12-23"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p> Abschrift des Sultans Dekret (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) über die Ernennung von Vincenzo
                    Moroni als Dolmetscher für die Insel Chios; Istanbul, 14. Dezember – 23.
                    Dezember 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung:
                    Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts
                    und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale
                    Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>imperial charter about the appointment of Vincenzo Moroni as a dragoman
                        for the Austrian affairs on the island of Chios</item>
                    <item>nīşān-ı hümāyūn</item>
                    <item>berat</item>
                    <item>dragoman</item>
                    <item>tercüman</item>
                    <item>Chios</item>
                    <item>Sakız</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00036_Page_73_Entry_148.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <!--<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı vezīre</rs>Abdullah Pasha
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Wien</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Buda</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9372">Erdel</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">Ottoman Empire</rs>-->


    </facsimile>

    <text type="charter">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191214-17191223.1">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">148</metamark>

                <ab><lb/>Nīşān-ı hümāyūn oldur ki:</ab>

                <ab>
                    <lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile der-i devlet-medāruma gelen <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū
                    bi-l-ḫayr <lb/>südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü ʿarż-ı ḥāl gönderüb</ab>

                <ab><rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">devlet-i ʿaliyye</rs>m ile müşārün ileyh <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> beyninde vāḳiʿ olan ṣulḥ
                    ve ṣalāḥ muḳteżāsınca <lb/>memālik-i maḥrūsemde <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15308"
                        >Sāḳız</rs> cezīresine <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">müşārün ileyh</rs>üñ
                    bayraġıyla gelüb gidüb reʿāyāsınuñ vāḳiʿ olan umūr ve ḥuṣūṣlarını görmek üzere
                        <lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr15308">cezīre-i mezbūre</rs>ye bir tercümān
                    naṣbı iḳtiżā eylemekle rāfiʿ-i tevḳīʿi refʿīʿü ş-şān-ı ḫāḳānī <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr15452">Vincāco (Vincenzo) Moroni</rs> veled-i Kurūmī tercümān naṣb
                    ve taʿyīn <lb/>olunub ʿahdnāme mūcebince olıgeldügi üzere berāt-ı şerīfüm
                    virilmek bābında ʿināyet ricā eylemegin bu nīşān-ı hümāyūn virdüm.</ab>

                <ab>Ve buyurdum ki mesfūr <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr15452">Vincāo (Vincenzo)
                        Moroni</rs><note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy">The Austrian
                        ambassador Virmont reported the appointment of Vincenzo Moroni to Vienna
                            <ref target="/o:vipa.l.hbg.17200129">in his letter dated January 29,
                            1720</ref>. The purpose of the appointment was to help with the
                        commercial matters and monitor the implementation of the newly granted
                        religious privileges to the Catholics.</note> veled-i Kurūmī vech-i meşrūḥ
                    üzere <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15308">cezīre-i mezbūre</rs>de tercümān olub
                    tercümānlıḳ ḫidmetinde olanlar ve oġulları ve ḫidmetkārları <lb/>ve cāriyeleri
                    ḫarāc ve ʿavārıż ve ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası ve resm-i üsārā ve sāʾir tekālīf-i ʿörfiyye
                    ṭalebiyle rencīde ve remīde olunmayub ve ḳul <lb/>ve cāriye istiḫdām idermişsün
                    diyü kimesne ḫarāc ve rüsūm ve bāc ṭalebiyle daḫl ve rencīde eylemeye ve
                    gendünüñ maṣraf ve hedāyāsına <lb/>ve ḳadīmden geydügi melbūsāt ve mefrūşāt ve
                    meʾkūlāt ve meşrūbātına kimesne daḫl ve rencīde eylemeyüb ḳadīmden olıgeldügi
                    üzere ʿafv <lb/>olunub ve rüsūm-ı gümrük ve bāc ṭaleb olunmaya ve evlerine
                    ʿasākir-i ḳonak ḳonulmaġa rencīde olunmaya ve gendü bāġında ḥāṣıl olan şırādan
                    <lb/>ḫamr emīni ve voyvodaları ve sāʾirlerden olıgeldügi üzere foçi aḳçası ṭaleb
                    eylemeyüb gendüsi ve evlādı ve taṣarrufında olan <lb/>cāriyeleri ḫarāc ve
                    ʿavārıżdan ve ve ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası ve resm-i maṣdariyyeden ve tekālīf-i ʿörfiyyenüñ
                    cümlesinden muʿāf ve müsellem olub</ab>

                <ab><lb/>ve mezbūr ile her kimüñ daʿvāsı olur ise ellerinde olan ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn
                    mūcebince āsitāne-i saʿādetüme ḥavāle olunub ġayrı yirde istimāʿ <lb/>olunmaya
                    baʿżı zamānda bir yire gitmek istedükde gidişde ve gelişde ḳaradan ve deryādan
                    menāzil ve merāḥilde gendüye ve esvāb <lb/>ve ṭavarlarına ve emvāl ve erzāḳına
                    ve yanında olan ādamlarına ulaḳ ve ulaḳ aḳçasından ve ġayrı cānibden kimesne
                    daḫl ve taʿarruż olunmayub <lb/>ve her ḳanda dāḫıl olur ise zād u zevād ve sāʾir
                    ẕaḫīresi narḫ-ı rūzī üzere aḳçasıyla virilüb bir ferd taʿallül ve nizāʿ
                    eylemeye</ab>

                <ab><lb/>ve maḫūf ve muḫāṭara olan yirlerde başına aḳ ṣarınub<note xml:id="ftn2"
                        resp="#yy">Wrapping white or putting a white cap on head was a practice of
                        janissaries. What is likely meant here was that the dragomans were allowed
                        to put on a janissary attire when they traveled through places that were
                        known to be dangerous and insecure for travelers.</note> ve ḳılıç ve oḳ ve
                    yay ve sāʾir ālāt-ı ḥarb götürdükde ḳāḍīlar <lb/>ve beglerbegiler ve ġayrıden
                    bir ferd rencīde eylemeyüb olıgeldügi üzere ḥimāyet ve ṣiyānet ve anuñ gibi
                    teʿaddī ve tecāvüz üzere olanlar menʿ ve defʿ <lb/>olunub dāʾimā işbu nīşān-ı
                    hümāyūnumuñ mażmūn-ı münīfiyle ʿamel olunub ḫilāfına rıżā ve cevāz gösterilmeye
                    şöyle bileler.</ab>



                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-12-14" notAfter="1719-12-23">fī evāil-i
                            Ṣ<supplied resp="#yy">afer</supplied> sene 1132</date></ab>



            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191214-17191223.1.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>So is the imperial sign (<foreign xml:lang="tur">nīşān-ı
                    hümāyūn</foreign>):</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as
                    grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>,
                    the paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my threshold of felicity [about the following matter]:</ab>


                <ab>In accordance with the peace and reconciliation that occurred between my <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs> and the aforesaid <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, it is required to appoint
                    to the island of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15308">Chios</rs> in my
                    well-protected domains an interpreter who may travel there under the flag of the
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> in order to take care of
                    matters and issues that may arise concerning [the Roman emperor’s] subjects.
                    Thus, the ambassador requested my favor, as it has been the practice in
                    accordance with the imperial letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota"
                        >ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>), to issue my most noble charter to appoint
                    and designate <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15452">Vincenzo Moroni</rs>,<ref
                        target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/> son of Kurumi, the bearer of the
                    imperial sign of exalted fame. </ab>

                <ab>[Upon his request,] I issued this charter and I order that <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr15452">Vincenzo Moroni</rs>, son of Kurumi (?) shall be an
                    interpreter on the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15308">aforementioned island</rs>
                    in the described way. Those who are interpreters, their sons, servants, and
                    women in their household shall not be injured and disturbed with the claims of
                    tribute, levies, dues for goods in transit (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ḳaṣṣāb
                        aḳçasi</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s fee'), or other extraordinary taxes. No
                    one shall interfere with or injure – claiming tribute, fees, and toll – under
                    the pretext that he employs slaves and women. No one shall interfere with and
                    injure him due to his expenses and gifts, the garments that he wears since a
                    long time ago, his fabrics, his provisions, and his drinks. He shall be excused
                    as it has been the practice since a long time ago. No customs duty and toll
                    shall be claimed. He shall not be injured through the appointment of a military
                    officer at their house. For the must that is produced from his own vineyard, the
                    wine superintendent and voivodes shall not claim barrel money as it has been the
                    practice for others. Himself, his children, and the women under his authority
                    shall be exempt and delivered from tribute, extraordinary tax, dues for goods in
                    transit (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s fee'),
                    export fee (<foreign xml:lang="ota">maṣdariyye</foreign>), wine tax, and all the
                    extraordinary levies.</ab>

                <ab>When someone has a case against him, the case shall be referred to my threshold
                    of felicity as per the imperial letter of agreement in his posession and the
                    case shall not be heard elsewhere. At certain times, when he wishes to go
                    somewhere, as he comes and goes on land and sea, at stations on the road, and
                    during stages of the journey, no one from among couriers or [those claiming]
                    courier fees - or [others] based on other excuses - shall interfere and attack
                    him, his clothes, his flock of animals, his properties, and his provisions. In
                    whichever location he enters, his victuals, provisions for the journey, and
                    cereals shall be given in return for the fixed price. No one shall seek an
                    excuse to avoid or dispute it.</ab>

                <ab>Neiter judges nor provincial governors nor a single person from among the rest
                    shall disturb him when he, at dangerous and insecure places, puts on a white cap
                    on his head (<foreign xml:lang="ota">başına aḳ ṣarınub</foreign>, lit. ‘wraps
                    white on his head’) and takes with him a sword, an arrow, a bow, and other
                    equipment; they shall guard and protect as it has been the practice. Those who
                    do wrong and attack shall be prevented and repelled. At all times, [you] should
                    act as required by the exalted purview of our imperial charter/sign (<foreign
                        xml:lang="ota">nīşān-ı hümāyūn</foreign>)<ref target="#ftn2" type="notenote_reference"/>. No consent or
                    permission shall be shown to the contrary. So shall you know and [have
                    confidence] in the noble mark!</ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-12-14" notAfter="1719-12-23">December 14 to
                        December 23, 1719</date></ab>



            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
