<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den kommandierenden Vezier von
                    Nissa (Niš) und andere osmanische Verwalter entlang der Route von Istanbul zur
                    österreichischen Grenze über den Schutz und die rechtmäßige Behandlung eines
                    österreichischen Kaufmanns namens Johannes während seiner Reise nach Belgrad
                    gemäß den Bedingungen des kaiserlichen Vertragsschreibens
                        (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>); Istanbul, 5. Oktober – 14. Oktober
                    1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree addressed to the commander vizier of Nissa
                    (Niš) and other Ottoman administrators along the route from Istanbul to the
                    Austrian border, concerning the protection and rightful treatment of an Austrian
                    merchant named Johannes during his journey to Belgrade in accordance with the
                    conditions of the imperial letter of agreement (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>);
                    Istanbul, October 5 – October 14, 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Niş muhafızı vezire ve İstanbul’dan Avusturya
                    sınırına kadar yol üzerindeki idarecilere hitaben yazılmış, Avusturya
                    tebaasından Johannes isimli bir tüccarın Belgrad’a seyahati esnasında korunması
                    ve kendisine ahidname hükümleri gereğince adil muamele edilmesi hakkında hükmü;
                    İstanbul, 5 Ekim – 14 Ekim, 1719</title>

                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17191005-17191014.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 70, entry 133</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-10-05" notAfter="1719-10-14"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Kommandanten von Nissa (Niš) und andere
                    osmanische Verwalter entlang der Route von Istanbul zur österreichischen Grenze
                    über den Schutz und die rechtmäßige Behandlung eines österreichischen Kaufmanns
                    namens Johannes während seiner Rückreise nach Belgrad; Istanbul, 5. Oktober –
                    14. Oktober 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung:
                    Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts
                    und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale
                    Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>treatment of Austrian merchants according to the conditions of the
                        imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>Asitane-i saadet (Istanbul)</item>
                    <item>Nissa (Niš)</item>
                    <item>Austrian border</item>
                    <item>Johannes</item>
                    <item>merchants</item>
                    <item>Belgrade</item>
                    <item>protection</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00034_Page_70_Entry_133.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>



    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191005-17191014.1">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">133</metamark>
                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                    <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı</rs> ve āsitāne-i saʿādetümden <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>e ve andan <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs> ḥudūduna varınca yol üzerinde vāḳiʿolan ḳāḍīlar
                    <lb/>ve gümrük emīnlerine ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından ḥālā der-i devlet-medāruma büyükilçilik ile gelen
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl <lb/>Ġrūf de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḥāl gönderüb</ab>

                <ab>müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                    <lb/>reʿāyāsından <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Būdīm</rs> tüccarından <rs type="person" ref="#mpr16023">Yoḫānes</rs> nām tācir <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrāddan</rs> ticāret ṭarīkīyle āsitāne-i saʿādetüme gelüb
                    ve ḥālā yine <lb/>ticāret ṭarīḳiyle <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>a revāne olmaġla yedinde olan emtiʿa ve eşyāsınuñ ʿahdnāme-i
                    hümāyūnum şurūtı mūcebince <lb/>gümrügin edā ve yedine edā teẕkiresin alduḳdan
                    ṣoñra tekrār gümrük ṭalebiyle ve āḫar bahāne ile teʿaddī ve rencīde olmamaḳ
                    <lb/>bābında emr-i şerīfüm virilmek ricāsına istidʿā-yı ʿināyet itmegin</ab>

                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnuma mürācaʿat olunduḳda ṭarafeynüñ <lb/>tüccārı gerek berren
                    ve gerek baḥren ve nehren getürdükleri emtiʿadan bir defʿa bir maḥallde ve yine
                    ḥudūd-ı islāmiyyeden iştirā <lb/>idüb vilāyetlerine götürdükleri emtiʿadan bir
                    defʿa bir maḥallde yüzde üç aḳça ḥesābı üzere resm-i gümrüklerin <lb/>edā
                    eyledüklerinden ṣoñra yüzde üçden ziyāde muṭālebe ve sāʾir müsteʾminlere
                    müsāʿade olduġı üzere <lb/>üç yüz aḳça selāmet aḳçasından māʿadā maṣdariyye ve
                    żarar-ı ḳaṣṣābiyye ve rüsūmāt-ı sāʾire muṭālebesiyle ḳaṭʿā <lb/>rencīde
                    olunmayalar diyü ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnumda mesṭūr ve muḳayyed bulunmaġın</ab>

                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn şürūṭı üzere bir defʿa <lb/>gümrügin edā eyledüklerinden
                    ṣoñra tekrār gümrük ve ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn āḫar vecihle teʿaddī olunmamaḳ
                    bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur buyurdum ki.</ab>


                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-10-05" notAfter="1719-10-14">fī evāḫir-i
                            Ẕā<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied> sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191005-17191014.1.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>
                <ab>Decree to the commander of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nissa (Niš)</rs> and
                    to the judges and customs intendants situated on the road from my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">felicitous threshold</rs>
                    to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nissa (Niš)</rs> and
                    from there to the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Austrian</rs> border:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>
                    —may God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a petition to
                    my threshold of felicity:</ab>

                <ab>A merchant from <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Buda</rs> named <rs type="person" ref="#mpr16023">Johannes</rs>, a subject of the aforementioned Roman
                    emperor, came from <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belgrade</rs> to my threshold
                    of felicity with the intention to trade and he is currently on his way to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belgrade</rs> again with the intention to trade.
                        [<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>] officially requested
                    my favor to issue my noble decree so that [the merchant], after he fulfills his
                    customs duty for the commodities and goods in his possession as per my imperial
                    letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>) and
                    receives in his hand the certificate of payment, he shall not be oppressed and
                    injured with additional customs duty claims or under other pretexts.</ab>

                <ab>Upon consultation to my imperial letter of agreement, it is written and recorded in
                    that agreement that after the merchants of both sides pay for their customs
                    duties at the rate of three percent at a single time at a single location for
                    the commodities they brought over land, sea, and rivers and again for the
                    commodities that they purchased from inside the borders of Islam and take to
                    their provinces, they shall absolutely not be injured with claims of more than
                    the three percent or with the claims of an export fee (<foreign xml:lang="ota">maṣdariyye</foreign>),
                    dues for goods in transit (<foreign xml:lang="ota">żarar-ı ḳaṣṣābiyye</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s damage'), and other taxes, except for the safety of 300 akçes,
                    collection of which is allowed to a variety of custodians.</ab>

                <ab>My illustrious edict has been issued that after the customs duty is paid for
                    once as per the conditions of my imperial letter of agreement, no customs duty
                    shall be claimed again and he shall not be oppressed in any other way in violation
                    of the imperial letter of agreement. So have I decreed!</ab>



                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-10-05" notAfter="1719-10-14">October 5 to
                        October 14, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>