<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den obersten Richter von
                    Istanbul namens Salih, an die Richter von Galata und anderen Vierteln der Stadt,
                    um sicherzustellen, dass die österreichischen Gefangenen gemäß den Bedingungen
                    des kaiserlichen Vertragsschreibens (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>) befreit
                    werden; Istanbul, 25. September – 4. Oktober 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the Chief Judge of Istanbul Salih, to the
                    judges of Galata and other quarters in the city, to ensure that the Austrian
                    captives are freed as per the conditions of the imperial letter of agreement
                        (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>); Istanbul, September 25 – October 4,
                    1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultan’ın, İstanbul Mollası Salih, Galata kadısı ve şehirdeki
                    bazı diğer kadılara hıtaben yazılmış, Avusturyalı savaş esirlerinin ahidname
                    şartlarına göre serbest bırakılması hakkında hükmü; İstanbul, 25 Eylül - 4 Ekim,
                    1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 68, entry 129</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den obersten Richter von Istanbul namens Salih,
                    an die Richter von Galata und anderen Vierteln der Stadt, um sicherzustellen,
                    dass die österreichischen Gefangenen gemäß den Bedingungen des des kaiserlichen
                    Vertragsschreibens befreit werden; Istanbul, 24. September – 4. Oktober 1719,
                    bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger,
                    Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim
                    Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von
                    Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno
                    Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>Release of Austrian captives and prisoners of war according to the
                        conditions of the imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>Chief judge of Istanbul</item>
                    <item>Judge of Galata</item>
                    <item>Galata</item>
                    <item>Üsküdar</item>
                    <item>Eyüp (Haslar)</item>
                    <item>captive</item>
                    <item>esir</item>
                    <item>prisoners of war</item>
                    <item>Judge of Üsküdar</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00033_Page_68_Entry_129.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.1">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">129</metamark>




                <ab><lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr15840">Anaṭolı</rs> ḳaḍīʿaskerligi pāyesiyle
                    ḥālā <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">İstanbul</rs> ḳāḍīsı olan <rs
                        type="person">Mevlānā Ṣāliḥ</rs> edāme’llāhu taʿālā fażāilehūya ve <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr14828">Ġalaṭa</rs> ḳāḍīsına <lb/>ve <gap unit="char"
                        extent="4"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="4"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="4"
                    /> ve <gap unit="char" extent="5"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="5"/> ḳāḍīlarına
                    ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15842">Üsküdār</rs> ve <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr15437">Ḫāṣlar</rs> ḳażāları nāʾiblerine ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile āsitāne-i saʿādetüme gelen <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Vir<lb break="no"/>
                        <lb/>mūnd</rs> ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḥāl
                    gönderüb</ab> 
                
                <ab>muḳaddemā ve bu defʿa ceng ü cidāl esnāsında ṭarafeynde <lb/>aḫẕ ve
                    nāsuñ yedlerinde bulunan esīr münāsib vechle mümkin olan maʿḳūl ve muʿtedil
                    bahālarıyla ıṭlāḳları <lb/>cāyiz ola esīr ṣāḥibi ile uzlaşılmayub nizāʿ vāḳiʿ
                    olduḳda ḥākimü l-vaḳt olanlar mābeynlerin <lb/>tevfīḳ ideler imkān olmaz ise
                    alduḳları bahāları isbāt ve yāḫūd ṣāḥiblerine yemīn teklīfiyle ẓāhir
                    <lb/>olduḳda edā olunub ıṭlāḳ olunalar ve ṣāḥibleri ziyāde aḳça ṭamaʿıyla üsārā
                    taḫlīṣine māniʿ olmayalar <lb/>ve lakin esīr aramaḳ ve ıṭlāḳlarına saʿy eylemek
                    içün devlet-i ʿaliyyem ṭarafından maḫṣūs ādamlar taʿyīn <lb/>olundıġı taḳdīrce
                    müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından
                    ḥākim olanlar üsārā fuḳarāsına ṣāḥib çıḳub ve bahāların <lb/>vech-i meşrūḥ üzere
                    iledilüb taḫlīṣine saʿy ve ihtimām ile ve bu vech üzere esīrlerüñ ḫalāṣına
                    ṭarafeynden <lb/>merḥamet oluna diyü ṭarafeynden alınub virilen ʿahdnāmelerde
                    mesṭūr ve muḳayyed bulunmaġın</ab>

                <ab>devlet-i ʿaliyyem ṭarafından <lb/>aḫẕ olunub nāsuñ yedlerinde bulunan esīrlerden
                    İslām’a gelmeyenler bulunduḳları maḥallerden ʿahdnāme-i ḥümāyūn şürūṭınuñ
                    <lb/>üzere taḫlīṣ olunub ve mābeynde tecdīd ve tevkīd olunan müsāleme ve
                    dostluġa riʿāyeten müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imparātorı</rs>nuñ <lb/>ṭarafından āsitāne-i saʿādetümde olan <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">vekīli</rs> tedbīri ile esīr istiḫlāṣıyçün
                    taʿyīn olunanlaruñ iḳāmetlerine <lb/>ve ṭarīḳlerine lāzım gelen sāʾir ḫıristiyān
                    esīrlerden daḫī aṣḥābı olub rıżālarıyla fürūḫt <lb/>murād idenlerden bahālarıyla
                    istiḫlāṣına ve berren ve baḥren diledükleri maḥallerden vilāyetlerine irsāl
                    mümānaʿat olunmamaḳ <lb/>bābında istidʿā-yı ʿināyet itmegin vech-i meşrūḥ üzere
                    ʿamel olunmaḳ bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur</ab>

                <ab><lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">buyurdum ki</rs>
                    <lb/>vuṣūl bulduḳda bu bābda ṣādır olan fermān-ı celīlü’l-ḳadrüm mūcebince ʿamel
                    daḫī siz ki mūmā ileyhümsiz taḥt-ı ḳażālarıñuzdan <lb/>nāsuñ yedlerinde bulunub
                    İslāma gelmeyen esīrleri ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūnum şürūṭı üzere taḫlīṣ ve vech-i
                    meşrūḥ üzere <lb/>müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorınuñ</rs> ṭarafından āsitāne-i saʿādetümde olan vekīl tedbīri ile
                    istiḫlāṣ içün <lb/>taʿyīn olunanlaruñ iḳāmetlerine mümānaʿat olunmayub
                    ṭarīḳlerine lāzım gelen sāʾir ḫıristiyān esīrlerden <lb/>daḫī aṣḥābı olub
                    rıżālarıyla fürūḫt murād idenler daḫī bahālarıyla istiḫlāṣ ve diledükleri
                    maḥallerden <lb/>vilāyetlerine irsāle bī-vech kimesneyi mümānaʿat itdürmeyesiz
                    şöyle bilesiz</ab>


                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">fī evāsıṭ-ı Ẕā
                            [<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied>] sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.1.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>


                <ab>Decree to Mevlana Salih, who is the judge of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14055">Istanbul</rs> with the honorific rank of
                    the chief judge of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr15840">Anatolia</rs>—may God the
                    exalted make his virtues lasting—and to the judge of <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr14828">Galata</rs>, and to the judges of <gap unit="char"
                        extent="4"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="4"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="4"
                    /> ve <gap unit="char" extent="5"/> ve <gap unit="char" extent="5"/>, and to the
                    deputy judges of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14828">Üsküdar</rs> and <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr15437">Ḫāṣlar</rs> (Eyüp).</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my threshold of felicity as grand
                    ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my court (threshold of felicity). He requested my favor about [the
                    following matter]:</ab> 
                    
                    <ab>It shall be lawful to free the captives, who have been
                    captured previously in the most recent war and conflict and are held in the
                    possession of people, in an appropriate way with the payment of a potential
                    price that is acceptable and reasonable. In case no agreement is reached with
                    the owner of a captive and a disagreement occurs, the notables [at a given
                    location] shall intermediate between the two parties. If that is not possible,
                    the value shall be proved [via documentation] or the value shall be disclosed
                    after taking an oath is proposed [to the owner of the captive]. The owner
                    shall not prevent the liberation of captives with greed for more money. 
                    
                    In addition, it was written and recorded in the letters of agreements exchanged
                    between the two sides that, just as men were appointed by my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs> for
                    the purpose of searching and working to liberate captives, arbiters [appointed]
                    by the aforementioned <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> shall
                    protect the poor captives—whose price shall be delivered in the way described—
                    and work for their liberation and take great care. In this way, both sides shall
                    show mercy for the liberation of the captives.</ab>

                <ab>Hence, from among the captives taken by my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs> and found in the
                    possession of people, those who have not converted to Islam shall be freed where
                    they are—as per the conditions of the imperial letter of agreement (<foreign
                        xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>). And, abiding by the renewed
                    and bolstered reconciliation and friendship between the two sides, those
                    Christian captives—whose [service] [will be] required at the residences and during the
                    journeys of those who are appointed for the liberation of those captives by the
                    aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>’s <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">agent</rs> who dwells in my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">threshold of
                    felicity</rs>—who have friends desiring with their own will to be purchased, shall be
                    freed against the payment of their price, and the sending [of those freed captives] to their lands over
                    sea and land from wherever they wish shall not be hindered. My illustrious edict
                    has been issued [for you] to act in the way described.</ab>

                <ab>When it arrives, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> order that you
                    act as required by my edict of glorious worth. Now, you are the aforementioned
                    [officers]! As per the conditions of my imperial letter of agreement, you shall
                    liberate the captives who are in the possession of people in your districts and
                    who did not convert to Islam. And, in the way described, you shall not hinder
                    the residence of those who have been appointed with the task of liberation [of
                    captives] by the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>’s agent who
                    is at my felicitious threshold. Among the Christian captives—whose [service] is
                    required [for the purpose of finding and collecting the captives], if there are
                    those who have companions that desire–with their own consent–to be purchased, they
                    too shall be freed with the payment of their fees, and you shall not allow
                    anyone to hinder their sending to their lands from wherever they wish shall not
                    be hindered. So shall you know!</ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">September 25 to
                        October 4, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
