<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den kommandierenden Vezier von
                    Nissa (Niš) und viele andere Verwalter zwischen Istanbul und der
                    österreichischen Grenze, um sicherzustellen, dass österreichische Kaufleute
                    gemäß dem kaiserlichen Vertragsschreiben (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>) behandelt
                    werden; Istanbul, 15. September – 24. September 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the commander vizier of Nissa (Niš) and many
                    other administrators situated between Istanbul and the Austrian border to ensure
                    that Austrian merchants are treated in accordance with the imperial letter of
                    agreement (<foreign>ahidname</foreign>); Istanbul, September 15 – September 24,
                    1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Niş muhafızı vezire ve İstanbul’dan Avusturya
                    sınırına varıncaya kadar yol üzerinde görev yapan birçok Osmanlı idarecisine
                    hitaben yazılmış, Avusturyalı tüccarlara ahidname şartlarına göre muamele
                    edilmesi hakkında hükmü; İstanbul, 15 Eylül - 24 Eylül, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 68, entry 128</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-09-15" notAfter="1719-09-24"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Kommandanten von Nissa (Niš) und viele andere
                    Verwalter zwischen Istanbul und der österreichischen Grenze, um sicherzustellen,
                    dass österreichische Kaufleute gemäß dem kaiserlichen Vertragsschreiben
                    (ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn) behandelt werden; Istanbul, 15. September – 24. September
                    1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung: Jakob
                    Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und
                    Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale
                    Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>treatment of Austrian merchants according to the conditions of the
                        imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>Asitane-i saadet</item>
                    <item>Istanbul</item>
                    <item>Thessaloniki</item>
                    <item>Selanik</item>
                    <item>Nissa</item>
                    <item>Niš</item>
                    <item>Austrian border</item>

                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00033_Page_68_Entry_128.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.1">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">127</metamark>
                <metamark place="margin">68</metamark>



                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs> muḥāfıẓı vezīre āsitāne-i
                    saʿādetümden <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15449">Selānik</rs> ve <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15838">Doyran</rs>’a ve andan Nemçe ḥudūdına varınca yol üzerinde
                    vāḳiʿ olan <lb/>beglerbegiler ve sancaḳbegleri ve ḳāḍīlar ketḫüdā yirleri ve
                    yeñiçeri serdārları ve aʿyān-ı vilāyet ve iş irlerine ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından ḥālā der-i devlet-medāruma büyükilçilik ile gelen
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf <lb/>de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü mektūb gönderüb müşārün ileyh
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ tüccārından
                        <lb/><rs type="person">Yorġimen</rs>(?) nām tācir baʿżı emtiʿa ve eşyā almaḳ
                    içün ticāret ārzūsıyla <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15449">Selānik</rs>e ve <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15838">Doyrān</rs>a ve andan <lb/><rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>a ʿazīmet üzere olduġın bildürüb ẕikr olunan
                    maḥallere varub aḳçasıyla iştirā itdügi emtiʿanuñ <lb/>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn
                    mūcebince yüzde üç gümrük bir defʿa bir maḥallde edā ve yirine edā teẕkiresi
                    alduḳdan ṣoñra āḫar maḥallerde <lb/>tekrār gümrük muṭālebesiyle ve sāʾir bahāne
                    ile rencīde ve remīde olunmayub ḥudūd nihāyetine varınca emīn ve sālim mürūr u
                    ʿubūrına <lb/>mümānaʿat olunmamaḳ bābında ḥükm-ü hümāyūnum ricā eyledügi
                    ecilden</ab>
                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnuma mürācaʿat olunduḳda ṭarafeynüñ tüccārı gerek berren
                    <lb/>ve gerek baḥren ve nehren getürdükleri emtiʿadan bir defʿa bir maḥallde ve
                    yine ḥudūd-u islāmiyyeden iştirā idüb vilāyetlerine <lb/>götürdükleri emtiʿadan
                    bir defʿa bir maḥallde yüzde üç ḥesābı üzere resm-i gümrüklerin edā
                    eyledüklerinden ṣoñra yüzde <lb/>üçden ziyāde muṭālebe ve sāʾir müsteʾmenlere
                    müsāʿade olduġı üzere üç yüz aḳça selāmet aḳçasından <lb/>māʿadā maṣdariyye ve
                    żarar-ı ḳaṣṣābiyye ve rusūmāt-ı sāʾire muṭālebesiyle ḳaṭʿā rencīde olunmaya diyü
                    mesṭūr ve muḳayyed <lb/>bulunmaġın ʿahdnāme-i ḥümāyūn mūcebince ʿamel olunmaḳ
                    bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur.</ab>
                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                    <lb/>vuṣūl bulduḳda bu bābda ṣādır olan fermān-ı celīlü’l-ḳadrüm ve ʿahdnāme-i
                    hümāyūnum mūcebince ʿamel idüb min baʿd ḫilāfına <lb/>rıżā ve cevāz
                    göstermeyesiz, şöyle bilesiz! <date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-15"
                        notAfter="1719-09-24">fī evāʾil-i Ẕā [<supplied resp="#yy"
                            >Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied>] sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.1.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>Decree to the commander vizier of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nissa
                        (Niš)</rs> and to all provincial governors, district administrators, judges,
                    aides-de-camp of janissary commanders, janissary commanders, provincial
                    notables, and functionaries that are located on the road from my threshold of
                    felicity (Istanbul) to Thessaloniki, <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15838"
                        >Doyran</rs> (Star Dojran), and from there to the Austrian border:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who is currently at my gate that is the center of state as grand
                    ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my threshold of felicity. He requested my imperial decree about the
                    [following] matter: A merchant named <rs type="person">Yorgimen</rs>(?) from
                    among the merchants of the aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman
                        emperor</rs> declared that he will go to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15449"
                        >Salonika</rs>, <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15838">Doyran</rs> (Star Dojran),
                    and from there to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belgrade</rs> to purchase some
                    commodities and goods and with the desire of commerce. As [the merchant] arrives
                    at the aforesaid locations, after he purchases commodities with [his own] money,
                    paying at each location once the three percent customs duty as per the imperial
                    letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>), and
                    receiving a receipt of payment, he shall not be oppressed and disturbed at other
                    locations through recurrent demand of customs duty or other excuses and he shall
                    not be prevented from passing along safely and soundly when he arrives at the
                    border.</ab>

                <ab>Upon consultation to my imperial letter of agreement, it is written and recorded
                    that after the merchants of both sides pay once at a location a three percent of
                    customs duty for the commodities that they bring along with them over land and
                    sea and for the commodities they bought from inside the frontiers of Islam to
                    take to their provinces, they absolutely shall not be oppressed through a claim
                    of an export fee (<foreign xml:lang="ota">maṣdariyye</foreign>), dues for goods
                    in transit (<foreign xml:lang="ota">żarar-ı ḳaṣṣābiyye</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s damage'), or other
                    duties, in addition to the claim of three percent [customs duty] and a safety
                    fee of 300 akçes as permitted to a variety of foreign individuals who applied
                    for safety. [Hence,] my illustrious decree was issued to act as stipulated by
                    the imperial letter of agreement.</ab>


                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> order that, when my decree arrives, you
                    shall act as stipulated by my edict of glorious worth and my imperial letter of
                    agreement; from now on, you shall not permit or show consent to the opposite. So
                    shall you know! <date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-15" notAfter="1719-09-24"
                        >September 15 to September 24, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
