<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Besuch von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Hauptbuchführer,
                    Istanbul, 21. April 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Visit of Damian Hugo von Virmont to the Chief Treasurer,
                    Istanbul, April 21, 1720</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Damian Hugo von Virmont’un Defterdar’ı Ziyareti,
                    İstanbul, 21 Nisan 1720</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName>Teşrifati Salman Efendi</persName>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200421a</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                        <idno>no. 347, p. 89</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1720-04-21"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context"> Protokollbücher </ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>
                    Besuch von Damian Hugo von Virmont beim Hauptbuchführer, Istanbul, 21. April 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
                </p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00043b.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="protocol">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200421a">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
            <ab>
                <hi rend="#red"><lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">İlçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs> Defterdār Efendiye geldigini müşʿirdür. </hi>
                <lb/><date when="1720-04-21">Yevm-i mezbūrda</date> Başdefterdār El-Ḥāc İbrāhīm Efendi ḥażretleri
                Beşikṭaş Mevlevīḫānesi
                <lb/>ittiṣālinde vākiʿ <rs type="person">Baş bāḳī Ḳulı Aḥmed Aġ anuñ</rs> yalısında <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Nemçe ilçisine</rs> żiyāfet 
                <lb/>eylemekle ẕikr olunur.</ab>
                
            <ab><date when="1720-04-20">Yevm-i mezbūrdan bir gün muḳaddem</date> bāġ çevān ḳolı ve on beş ḳadar
                <lb/>ḫānende ve sāzende yalı-yı mezbūra cemʿ olunub ve efendi ḥażretlerinün ketḫüdāsı daḫı bir gece 
                <lb/>muḳaddem gidüb mühimmāt-ı żiyāfeti görmişdür. Ḥattā begzādegān içün iḳtiżā iden peşgūnlar 
                <lb/><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">ṣāḥib devlet</rs> vekīl-i ḫarcında mevcūd olan peşgūnlar getürdilmişdür. Bu vechle mühimmāt müheyyā 
                <lb/>olduḳ dan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> sāʿat altıya varduḳda ẓuhūrı ḫaber virilmekle</ab>
                
            <ab>aġ ayān nezd-i bābıñ 
                <lb/>bālāsından deryāya nāẓır köşküñ ḳapısına gelince dizilüb ve Enderūn aġ aları daḫı derūn-i
                <lb/>ḳaṣrda birḳāç ḳat ṣaff-beste olub ve defterdār efendi daḫı köşküñ ḳurbında olan
                <lb/>oṭ aya gidüb baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> köşke duḫūl eyledigi gibi defterdār efendi daḫı oda-yı
                <lb/>mezbūrdan beri gelüb sūʾal-i ḥāṭır iderek maḳāmlarına ḳuʿūd eyledi.</ab>
                
                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">İlçi beg</rs> mümā ileyhiñ
                <lb/>ṣol ṭarafında yaṣdıḳ üzerinde oturdılub baʿdehū ṭatlu ve ḳahve virilüb baʿdehū ḫānende 
                <lb/>ve sāzende faṣla āġ āz eylemişlerdür. Baʿdehū köşk-i mezbūrdan ḥareket ve ḳurbında mevlevīḫāne
                <lb/>ṭarafında meydāna nāẓır oṭ aya varılub bāġ çe ḳolı muṭrıblarınıñ oyunları seyr olmışdur.
                <lb/>Baʿdehū maḥall-i mezbūrdan daḫı ḥareket ve üç ṣofalı köşke varılduḳda begzādegān dīvānḫānede 
                <lb/>peşgūn üzerinde iṭʿām olmışdur.</ab>
                
            <ab>Bu es̠nāda ḳaṣr-ı mezbūrda ḫānende ve sāzende faṣl eylemişlerdür.
                <lb/>Ḥattā muṭrıblarda bir küçük ḳızcaġ ız ḫātime-i faṣlda oynamaġ  ile ilçi beg şevḳe gelüb dāʾirenüñ
                <lb/>birisini eline alub ber ḳāʿide <choice><corr>uṣūl</corr><sic>ūṣūl</sic></choice> ṭutub
                ve mezbūr ḳızcaġ ız daḫı ilçinüñ yanında bu ḥālet
                <lb/>üzerine iken bir miḳdār oynaduḳda ḥaẓẓından cebinden ḳıza bir altun virmişdür. Baʿdehū ṭaʿām
                <lb/>çıḳub defterdār efendi ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">ilçi Dürrī Efendi</rs>
                ve baş bāḳī ḳulu ve māliyye teẕkirecisi 
                <lb/>ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">Ḳapucıbaşı Meḥmed Aġ a</rs> oturub baʿdeʾl-ṭaʿām yine faṣl eylemişlerdür.
                Baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiye</rs>:</ab>
                
                <list type="giftlist">
                <item rend="column1">telli çekme ʿaded 2 yaġ lıḳ ʿaded 2</item> 
                <item rend="column2">begzādegān ve sāʾire telli çekme ʿaded 30</item> 
                    <item rend="column3"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">ḳapucıbaşı aġ aya</rs> ṣof kerāke ʿaded 1</item>
                <item rend="column4">teşrīfātī efendiye çuḳa 1 ḳumāş 1 </item>
                <item rend="column5">yeñiçeri ḥāṣekisine çuḳa 1 ḳumāş 1</item>
                    <item rend="column1"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçiye</rs> kemer raḫt ve aġ ır kese ile donanmış kula at ʿaded 1</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200421a-transl">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <ab>The following relates the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> visit to <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the chief treasurer</rs>.
                    <date when="1720-04-21">On that day</date>, his excellency <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the Chief Treasurer
                    El-hac İbrahim Efendi</rs> organized a banquet for <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">the Austrian ambassador</rs> at 
                    the <rs type="person">Tax Inspector, Ahmed Agha</rs>’s waterfront mansion located next to the 
                    Beşiktaş Mevlevi Lodge. It is reported here.</ab>
                
            <ab>The previous day, the gardeners’ branch (<foreign xml:lang="ota">bāġ çevān ḳolı</foreign>)
                and ten to fifteen vocalists and musicians gathered at the mansion.
                The steward of his excellency <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the chief treasurer</rs> also went to the mansion 
                the previous evening and set about the task of overseeing the supplies for the banquet.
                The benches required for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> noblemen to sit were supplied from
                the inventory of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9441">grand vizier’s</rs> major-domo. After the required
                equipment had been provided in this way, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> arrival was
                reported at six o’clock.</ab>
                
            <ab>The aghas set up their ranks starting from the upper side of the gate and extending till the 
                door of the pavilion facing the see. The aghas of the inner court
                lined up forming several rows inside the mansion. Before the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                arrived, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the chief treasurer</rs> went to the room near the pavilion. 
                When the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> entered the pavilion, <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the chief treasurer</rs> also came out of
                the room, inquired after the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador’s</rs> condition, and sat on his post.</ab>
                
                <ab>The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> was seated on a cushion on the left-hand side of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">the chief treasurer</rs>. Sweets
                and coffee were served. Thereafter, the vocalists and musicians began their
                performance. Then, the party left the pavilion and advanced to the room 
                that is located near the Mevlevi lodge, overseeing the maidan where they 
                watched the the dances of the singers of the gardener’s branch. After that, they also left 
                that spot and went to the three-porched pavilion, where the noblemen of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                was served a meal on benches inside the reception room.</ab>
                
            <ab>Meanwhile, the vocalists and musicians performed at the mansion. 
                When, at the end of the performance a little girl danced among the singers, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, carried away 
                by the excitement of the moment, took one of the tambourines in his hand and tapped out 
                the rhythm as it should be done. The little girl danced in this manner with the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                for a while, upon which the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, out of his enjoyment of the moment, gave a gold coin to the girl.
                Then, a meal was served. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14614">The chief treasurer</rs>, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14240">Dürrī Efendi</rs>, the chief inspector, the 
                secretary of the treasury, and <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14717">the Chief Steward Mehmed Agha</rs>, sat together
                during the meal. After the meal, one more time there was a musical performance.
                Afterwards, [the following were presented] to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>:</ab>
                
                <list type="giftlist">
                    <item rend="column1">embroidered fabric 2 pieces; handkerchief 2 pieces</item> 
                    <item rend="column2">embroidered fabric for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>’s
                        noblemen and the rest of the group, 30 pieces</item> 
                    <item rend="column3">a fine camlet for the steward agha, 1 piece</item>
                    <item rend="column4">a broadcloth and a fabric for the protocol registerer, 1 each</item>
                    <item rend="column5">a broadcloth and a fabric for the janissary captain, 1 each</item>
                    <item rend="column1">for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> a buckskin horse equipped with a
                        leather-strap harness and a horse blanket made of heavy cloth, 1 piece</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>