<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Gouverneur des Sanjak von
                    Elbasan und an den Richter von Durrës (Drač), Kaufleute zu befreien, die
                    Untertanen des Heiligen Römischen Kaisers sind und von tunesischen Piraten
                    während einer Reise von Ναύπλιον/Náfplio nach Sizilien unter Verletzung des
                    kaiserlichen Vertragsschreibens (ahidname) gefangen genommen worden waren;
                    Istanbul, 24. November – 3. Dezember 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the governor of the Sanjak of Elbasan and to
                    the judge of Durrës (Drač) to free the merchants who are subjects of the Holy
                    Roman Emperor and have been captured during a journey from Ναύπλιον/Náfplio to
                    Sicily by Tunisian pirates in violation of the imperial letter of agreement
                    (ahidname); Istanbul, November 24 – December 3, 1719</title>


                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Elbasan sancağı beyine ve Drac kadısına hitaben
                    yazılmış olan, Kutsal Roma İmparatorluğu tebaasından olan ve Anabolı’dan
                    Sicilya’ya yaptıkları seyahat esnasında ahidname şartlarına aykırı olarak
                    Tunuslu korsanlarca tutsak edilen tüccarların serbest bırakılması hakkında
                    hükmü; İstanbul, 24 Kasım – 3 Aralık, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17191124-17191203.2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 73, entry 147</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-11-24" notAfter="1719-12-03"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p> Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Gouverneur des Sanjak von Elbasan und an den
                    Richter von Durrës (Drač), die Kaufleute zu befreien, die Untertanen des
                    Heiligen Römischen Kaisers sind und von tunesischen Piraten während einer Reise
                    von Ναύπλιον/Náfplio nach Sizilien unter Verletzung des kaiserlichen
                    Vertragsschreibens (ahidname) gefangen genommen wurden; Istanbul, 24. November –
                    3. Dezember 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung:
                    Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts
                    und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale
                    Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>decree to the governor of Elbasan and to the judge of Durrës (Drač) to
                        free, according to the conditions of the imperial letter of agreement
                        (ahidname), the captives who are subjects of the Holy Roman Emperor</item>
                    <item>Elbasan</item>
                    <item>Durrës (Drač)</item>
                    <item>Náfplio</item>
                    <item>Sicily</item>
                    <item>captive</item>
                    <item>esir</item>
                    <item>Holy Roman Emperor</item>

                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00036_Page_73_Entry_147.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <!--<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı vezīre</rs>Abdullah Pasha
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr13416">Wien</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7448">Buda</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9372">Erdel</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">Ottoman Empire</rs>-->


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191124-17191203.2">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">147</metamark>
                <ab><lb/>Ber-vech-i arpalıḳ <rs type="place" ref="#mpr16055">İlbaṣan</rs> (Elbasan)
                    sancaġı mutaṣarrıfına ve <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15610">Drāc</rs> ḳāḍīsına
                    ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile gelen <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr
                    <lb/>südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḥāl gönderüb</ab>

                <ab><rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">devlet-i ʿaliyyem</rs> ile <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> beyninde ʿaḳd-ı musālaḥa ve musāleme ile
                    ṭarafeynden aḫẕ ve iʿṭā <lb/>olunan ʿahdnāmelerde tüccār ṭāʾifesi ṭarafeynüñ
                    memālikinde selefde virilen ʿahdnāmeler mūcebince emnen ve sālimen gendü
                    ḥāllerinde ticāret <lb/>ideler müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Romā imperāṭorına</rs> tābiʿ vilāyetlerüñ tüccār ve reʿāyāları ḳanġı
                    milletden olursa olsunlar berren ve baḥren <lb/>bu ḫuṣūṣa meʾmūr olan vekīller
                    beyninde ḳarār virildügi vech üzere <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ bayraġı ve paṭentasıyla <lb/>memālik-i maḥrūseye gendü
                    ḥāllerinde gidüb gelüb alış viriş idüb lāzım gelen gümrükleri virdüklerinden
                    ṣoñra rencīde <lb/>olunmayub ḥimāyet ve ṣiyānet olunalar diyü mesṭūr ve muḳayyed
                    olmaġla</ab>

                <ab>daḫl olunmaḳ īcāb itmez iken ḥālā müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Romā <lb/>imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ bayraġıyla tüccār ve reʿāyālarından baʿżıları
                    ticāret ile iki ḳıṭʿā sefīneleriyle <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15727"
                        >Anabolı</rs>dan (Ναύπλιον/Náfplio) <rs type="place" ref="#mpr1912"
                        >Çeçeliye</rs> (Sicily) giderler iken <lb/>esnā-yı rāhde <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15616">Tūnus</rs> sefīnesine müṣādif olduḳlarında ẕikr olunan <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15616">Tūnus</rs> ricāli sālifü’ẕ-ẕikr iki ḳıṭʿā
                    <lb/>sefīneyi ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn aḫẕ ve içinde olan emvāl ve eşyāsını
                    alub ve tüccār ve reʿāyāların daḫī istirḳāḳ <lb/>idüb ẕikri mürūr iden <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15616">Tūnus</rs> sefīnesi <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15610">Drāc</rs> limanında olduḳların bildürüb ẕikr olunan iki
                    ḳıṭʿā sefīneleri <lb/>ve derūnında aḫẕ olunan emvāl ve eşyā ve istirḳāḳ olunan
                    tüccār ve reʿāyāları ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn şürūṭı mūcebince <lb/>müşārün ileyh <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imparaṭorı</rs>nuñ <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15610">Drāc</rs>da olan ādamlarına bi-t-temām redd ve teslīm
                    itdürilmek bābında emr-i şerīfüm ricā itmeġin <lb/>vech-i meşrūḥ üzere ʿamel
                    olunmaḳ bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum ṣādır olmışdur.</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                    <lb/>vuṣūl bulduḳda bu bābda ṣādır olan fermān-ı celīlü’l-ḳadrüm mūcebince ʿamel
                    idüb daḫī vech-i meşrūḥ üzere müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Romā <lb/>imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ tüccār ve reʿāyālarından ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i
                    hümāyūn aḫz olunan sālifü’ẕ-ẕikr iki ḳıṭʿā sefīnesini derūnında <lb/>olan emvāl
                    ve eşyā ve istirḳāḳ olunan tüccār ve reʿāyālarıyla girü ve <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9399">müşārün ileyh</rs>üñ <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15610"
                        >Drāc</rs>da olan ādamlarına <lb/>redd ve teslīm idüb min baʿd ʿahdnāme-i
                    hümāyūn ve emr-i hümāyūnuma muḫālif taʿallül ve tereddüd itdürmeyesin şöyle
                    bilesin.</ab>


                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-11-24" notAfter="1719-12-03">fī evāsıṭ-ı
                        Muḥarrem sene 1132</date></ab>



            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.1719124-17191203.2.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>Decree to the person who is the governor of the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr16055"
                        >Elbasan</rs> district as a sinecure (<foreign xml:lang="ota"
                        >arpalıḳ</foreign>) and to the judge of <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15610"
                        >Durrës</rs> (Drač):</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>
                    —may God end his days propitiously—who came as grand ambassador from the <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the paragon of the great
                    commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a petition to my threshold of
                    felicity [about the following matter]:</ab>

                <ab>In the letters of agreement that have been exchanged as a result of the mutual
                    signing of peace and reconciliation between my eternal <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Roman emperor</rs>, it is written and recorded that the merchant class
                    shall quietly, safely, and soundly trade on the lands of both sides as per the
                    letters of agreement previously exchanged; that the merchants and subjects of
                    the lands under the suzerainty of the aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Roman emperor</rs>, regardless of whichever nation they come from, shall
                    quietly come and go over land and sea to the well-protected domains under the
                    flag and patent of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> and
                    trade in accordance with how it was concluded among the delegations charged with
                    this matter. Once they pay the required customs duty, they shall be guarded and
                    protected and not be injured.</ab>

                <ab>Thus, interfering with [them] was not necessary. However, as some of the
                    merchants and subjects of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman
                        emperor</rs> were on their way from <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15727"
                        >Ναύπλιον/Náfplio (Anabolu)</rs> to <rs type="place" ref="#mpr1912">Sicily
                        (Çeçele)</rs> with their two ships, during the journey they came across a
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15616">Tunisian</rs> ship. The <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15616">Tunisians</rs>, in violation of the imperial letter of
                    agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i hümayun</foreign>), have captured
                    the two ships mentioned earlier and have taken the properties and goods on the
                    ship. They enslaved the merchants and subjects. The ambassador reported that the
                    aforesaid <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15616">Tunisian</rs> ship is at the <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15610">Durrës</rs> port. (<rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>) requested my imperial decree that the
                    aforesaid two ships, all of the captured properties and goods, and the enslaved
                    merchants and subjects shall be returned and delivered, as per the conditions of
                    the imperial letter of agreement, to the men of the aforementioned <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> located at <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15610">Durrës</rs>. My illustrious decree has been issued for [all]
                    to act in the described way.</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> order that, when [my decree] arrives,
                    you shall act in accordance with my edict of glorious worth that has been issued
                    about this matter. In the described way, you shall return and deliver the
                    aforesaid ships, the properties and goods on them that have been captured from
                    the merchants and subjects of the aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399"
                        >Roman emperor</rs> in violation of the imperial letter of agreement, the
                    enslaved merchants themselves, and their subjects back to the men [of the <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>] who are located in <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15610">Durrës</rs>. From now on, you shall [allow no
                    one] to make excuses in violation of my imperial letter of agreement and my
                    imperial edict, nor [shall you allow anyone] hesitate my orders. So shall you know!</ab>



                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-11-24" notAfter="1719-12-03">November 14 to
                        November 23, 1719</date></ab>



            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
