<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Kaiserliches Patent (<foreign>nişan-ı
                        Hümayun</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) über die Freizügigkeit von
                    trinitarischen Patres, Patres, die durch das Osmanische Reich reisen um
                    habsburgische Gefangene zu befreien (pater redemptor), Jesuiten, und den Schutz
                    der Katholiken vor Interventionen griechischer, serbischer und bulgarischer
                    Kirchen; Istanbul, 25. September – 4. Oktober 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Imperial charter (<foreign>nişan-ı
                        Hümayun</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) concerning the free movement of
                    Trinitarian fathers, who are traveling across the Ottoman empire to free
                    Habsburg captives (pater redemptor), and Jesuits, and the protection of
                    Catholics from the interventions of Greek, Serbian, and Bulgarian churches;
                    Istanbul, September 25 – October 4, 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Berat formunda yazılmış, Katolik mezhebine tâbi olup esirleri
                    azat etmek için imparatorluk içinde seyahat eden Teslis (Triniteryen) cemaati
                    rahipleri (pater redemptor) ve Cizvit rahiplerinin serbest dolaşımına izin
                    verilmesi ve Katolikler’e Rum, Sırp ve Bulgar kiliseleri tarafından müdahele
                    edilmesini yasaklayan nişan-ı hümayun; İstanbul, 25 Eylül – 4 Ekim, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.3</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 69-70, entry 132</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-09-24" notAfter="1719-10-04"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Kaiserliche Patent (nişan-ı Hümayun/berat) über die Freizügigkeit von
                    trinitarischen Vätern, Vätern die durch das Osmanische Reich reisen um
                    habsburgische Gefangene zu befreien (pater redemptor), Jesuiten, und den Schutz
                    der Katholiken vor den Eingriffen griechischer, serbischer und bulgarischer
                    Kirchen; Istanbul, 25. September – 4. Oktober 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und
                    Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die
                    Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                    habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt
                    1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>

                    <item>Protection of Catholics in the Ottoman empire</item>
                    <item>Katolik</item>
                    <item>Catholics</item>
                    <item>Jesuits</item>
                    <item>Redemptorists</item>
                    <item>Cizvit</item>
                    <item>nişan-ı hümayun</item>
                    <item>berat</item>
                    <item>imperial charter</item>
                    <item>protection</item>
                    <item>protection from the interventions of Greek, Serbian, and Bulgarian
                        churches</item>

                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00034_Page_69_Entry_132_Part1.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <surface start="#IMG2">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00034_Page_70_Entry_132_Part2.jpg" xml:id="IMG2"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="charter">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.3">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">132</metamark>


                <ab><lb/>Nīşān-ı hümāyūn oldur ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile āsitāne-i saʿādetüme gelen <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf <lb/>de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḥal gönderüb</ab>

                <ab><date when="1649">biñ elli ṭoḳuz senesi</date>nde virilen ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnda
                    <lb/>münderic olduġı üzere pāpişta meẕhebinden Trinitari ve <foreign><unclear cert="medium" reason="illegible">dellā redemeçīris</unclear></foreign>
                    <note xml:id="ftn1" type="editorial" resp="#yy"> What this particular term here
                        means or implies is confusing, but it must be the Turkish rendering of the
                        Trinitarian designation <foreign>pater redemptor</foreign> that was used for the
                        monks in the order who travelled to find and free captives. The process of
                        liberation itself was called <foreign>redemption</foreign>.</note> taʿbīr
                    olunur pāpāslar ve ruhbānlar <lb/>ve yezūvītelere ẓulm ve teʿaddī olunmamaḳ
                    üzere mesṭūr olub</ab>

                <ab>ve bundan māʿadā daḫī ḳaradan ve deryādan varub <lb/>gelüb sākin olduḳları
                    meskenlerine kimesne taʿarruż eylemeyüb ve evlerini taʿmīr eyledükde kimesne
                    daḫl eylemeye ve āyīn <lb/>ve ʿibādetlerini Lātīn dīni üzere eyledüklerinde
                    beglerbegiler ve ḳaḍīlar ve sāʾir ḥükkāmdan yollarda ve meskenlerde ve ḳadīmden
                    <lb/>żabṭ eyledükleri kelīsālarınde kimesne daḫl ve taʿarruż itmeyüb ve nāsuñ
                    ṣadaḳasından ġayrı geçinecekleri olmamaḳla ticāret içün <lb/>getürdükleri
                    eşyādan ġayrı gendülerüñ esbāblarından resm bāc u ḫarāc ve sāʾir tekālīfden bir
                    şeyʾ ṭaleb itmeyeler <lb/>ve aralarından birisi mürd olduḳda esvāb ve
                    eşḳāllerine beytü’l-māl emīni ṭarafından daḫl olunmaya ve mürd olduḳlarında
                    <lb/>ṣandūḳ aḳçası nāmıyla gendülerden bir şeyʾ ṭaleb itmeyeler ve sākin
                    olduḳları maḥallerde ḳan düşürülmeye kan <lb/>bahāsın edā eylemek bahānesiyle
                    ḥabs olunmayalar ve ẕikr olunan ruhbānlar ve yezūtīler ve sāʾir Lātīn pāpāsları
                    <lb/>Rūm ve Ṣırf ve Bulġār pisḳoposlarından daḫl olunmayub ḳadīmden berü ḥālā
                    żabṭlarında olan kilīselerinde <lb/>ve gendülere tābiʿ olan reʿāyānuñ ḫidmetinde
                    anlar gibi bunlardan daḫī gendü kilīselerinde Lātīn dīni üzere <pb n="1" facs="#IMG2"/>
                    <metamark>70</metamark>
                    <lb/>āyīn ve ʿibādetlerin idüb Rūmdan ve Ṣırfdan kimesne daḫl ü taʿaruż eylemeye
                    ve varub gendülerin ġamz <lb/>idüb aḳçaların almayalar diyü sene <date type="Hijri" notBefore="1665-11-29" notAfter="1665-12-08">sitte ve sebʿīn ve
                        elf cemāẕiye’l-ūlāsı evāḫirinde</date> baʿdehū sene <date type="Hijri" notBefore="1700-10-05" notAfter="1700-10-14">isnā ʿaşere <lb/>ve-miʾe ve elf
                        rebīʿü l-āḫirinüñ evāḫirinde</date> nīşān-ı hümāyūn virildügin bildürüb
                    tecdīdin ricā itmegin</ab>

                <ab><lb/>mūcebince tecdīd olunub bu nīşān-ı hümāyūnı virdüm ve buyurdum ki fī-mā
                    baʿd daḫī vech-i meşrūḥ üzere ʿamel olunub <lb/>ḫilāfına rıżā ve cevāz
                    gösterilmeyüb min baʿd şerʿ-i şerīfe ve muḳaddemā ve ḥālā virilen nīşān-ı
                    hümāyūna <lb/>muġāyir kimesneye iş itdürmeyeler şöyle bileler.</ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">fī evāsıṭ-ı
                            Ẕā[<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied>] sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190925-17191004.3.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>

                <ab>So is the imperial sign (nīşān-ı hümāyūn):</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>
                    —may God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a petition to
                    my threshold of felicity:</ab>

                <ab>As included in the imperial letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i
                        ḥumāyūn</foreign>) that was issued in <date type="Hijri" when="1649">1059</date>, the priests and clergy from the papal order of Trinitarians
                    and the priests and clergy who are called <foreign>redemptionist
                        fathers</foreign>(?) <ref target="#ftn1" type="note_reference"/> as well as
                    Jesuits shall not be wronged and oppressed.</ab>

                <ab>Besides, they shall travel to and from their residences over land and sea and no
                    one shall molest them. When they repair their houses, no one shall interfere. As
                    they conduct their rites and worship according to the Roman Catholic religion
                    (<foreign xml:lang="ota">Lātīn dīni üzere</foreign>), no one from among the provincial governors, judges,
                    and other administrators shall interfere and molest them on roads, houses, and
                    churches in their possession since old days. Since they do not have anything to
                    live on other than the charity of people, except for the commodities they
                    brought for trade, [the aforesaid officials] shall not demand tax, tribute and
                    contribution, and other levies from their own requisites. When someone among
                    them dies, the superintendent of the inheritance department at the public
                    treasury shall not interfere with the deceased person’s garments and personal
                    possessions (<foreign xml:lang="ota">eşḳāl</foreign>). When they die, nothing shall be demanded
                    from them on the pretext of treasury money (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ṣandūḳ aḳçası</foreign>). No
                    blood shall be shed in quarters where they live and they shall not be jailed on
                    the pretext of paying blood compensation. The Greek, Serbian, and Bulgarian
                    prelates shall not interfere with the aforesaid clergy, Jesuits, and other Roman
                    Catholic priests (<foreign xml:lang="ota">Lātīn pāpāsları</foreign>). Just as the Greek, Serbian, and Bulgarian
                    churches, the Roman Catholics too shall perform in their own churches, which they
                    have owned from the old days to the present, their rites and prayers as per the
                    Roman Catholic faith in the service of the subjects that follow them. <pb n="1" facs="#IMG2"/> 
                    No one from among the Greeks and Serbians shall interfere and
                    molest them or get their money by fraud. The ambassador reported that an
                    imperial sign (<foreign xml:lang="ota">nīşān-ı hümāyūn</foreign>) dated 
                    <date notBefore="1665-11-29" notAfter="1665-12-08">November 29 – December 8, 1665</date> and, after
                    that, another one dated <date notBefore="1700-10-05" notAfter="1700-10-14">October 5 – October 14, 1700</date> were issued. He requested a
                    renewal.</ab>

                <ab>It has been renewed and I issued the present imperial sign (charter). I order
                    that, from now on, [all] shall act in the described way and no consent or
                    permission shall be shown to the contrary. From now on, no one shall [be allowed
                    to] do a thing in violation of the canonical law of Islam and the imperial signs
                    that were issued formerly and the one issued now. So shall they know!</ab>

                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-25" notAfter="1719-10-04">September 25 to
                        October 4, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>