<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <!-- title of the source -->
            <title xml:lang="de">Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsbesuch beim Reichskanzler,
                Istanbul, 15. April 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Protocol register of Damian Hugo von Virmont’s farewell visit to the Chancellor,
                Istanbul, April 15, 1720</title>
            <title xml:lang="tr">Teşrifat defteri kaydı, Damian Hugo von Virmont’un Nişancı Paşa’ya veda ziyareti,
                İstanbul, 15 Nisan 1720</title>
            <!-- author of the source -->
            <author>
                <persName>Teşrifati Salman Efendi</persName>
            </author>
            <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
            <respStmt>
                <!-- editor -->
                <resp>Edition</resp>
                <persName xml:id="yy">
                    <forename>Yasir</forename>
                    <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <!-- data modelling-->
                <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Stephan</forename>
                    <surname>Kurz</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
                <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/">
                    Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Habsburg and Balkan Studies
                </orgName>
            </publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at">
                    GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset Management System
                </orgName>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
                    Creative Commons BY 4.0
                </licence>
            </availability>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            
            <idno type="PID">o:vipa.pr.osm.17200415</idno>
       </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic Sources 1500–1918</title>
            <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu 1500–1918</title>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                <persName>
                    <forename>Arno</forename>
                    <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                </persName>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                    <institution>BOA, İstanbul</institution>
                    <collection>Teşrifat Merasimi Kayıt Defteri</collection>
                    <idno>no. 347, p. 87</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                
                <physDesc>
                  
                </physDesc>
                <history>
                    <origin>
                        <origDate when="1720-04-15"/>
                    </origin>
                </history>
            </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document --> 
        </editorialDecl>
        <projectDesc>
            <ab>
                <ref target="context:vipa" type="context">
                    Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20)
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:vipa.pr" type="context">
                    Protokollbücher
                </ref>
                <ref target="context:qhod" type="context">
                    Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918
                </ref>
            </ab>
            <!-- Project description -->
            <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
            <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
        </projectDesc>
        <refsDecl>
            <p>
                Protokollregister über Damian Hugo von Virmonts Abschiedsbesuch beim Reichskanzler, Istanbul, 15. April 1720, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz unter Mitarbeit von Claudia Römer (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022.
            </p>
        </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
        </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
    
   <surface start="#IMG1">
        <graphic url="A_}d___00347_00042b2.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
    </surface>
    
</facsimile>
                   
<text type="protocol">
<body>
    <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200415">
    <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/> 
    <ab>
        <hi rend="#red"><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">İlçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">nişāncı paşaya</rs> vardıġ ını müşʿirdür.</hi>  
        <lb/><date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-15">Māh-ı mezbūruñ altıncı Bāzār güni</date> <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs>
        vezīr-i mükerrem <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">Nişāncı Muṣṭafā Paşa</rs> ḥażretlerine
        <lb/>gelmekle iskele-i mezbūr için vezīr-i müşārün ileyh yedi çifte ḳayıġ ını ġ arb ḳapusı iskelesine
        <lb/>irsāl ve bāġ çe ḳapusına daḫı <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ve begzādegānınuñ rükūbı içün yigirmi
        ruʾus <choice><sic>egerlenmiş</sic><corr>eyerlenmiş</corr></choice> atlar
        <lb/>irsāl olunub <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> ḳapucıbaşı ile meʿan irsāl olunan ḳayıġ a süvār olub 
        <lb/>etbāʿı daḫı medīden taʿyīn olunan otuz miḳdārı ḳayıḳlar ile bāġçe ḳapusına yanaşub
        <lb/>mevcūd olan atlar ile <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">vezīr-i müşārün ileyhüñ</rs> <choice><corr>Ḫ</corr><sic>Ḥ</sic></choice>ocaḫānı ḳurbında olan ḫānesine nüzūl 
        <lb/>idüb</ab>
        
    <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> yuḳarı çıḳmazdan muḳaddem paşa aġ aları biʾl-cümle ferāce semūr kürk ile
        <lb/>iki ṣofalı büyük odanuñ ḳapusı ḫāricinden tā ṣadra ḳarīb varılub ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūruñ</rs>
        <lb/>ḳuʿūdı içün ṣadra ḳarīb bir iki iḥrām ḳonub ve üzerine sūzenī maḳʿad pūşīde 
        <lb/>olunub baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> gelüb maḥall-i mezbūra
        oturduḳdan ṣoñra <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">saʿādetlü vezīr-i müşārün ileyh ḥażretleri</rs>
        <lb/>daḫı yeşil çuḳa ferāce semūr kürk ile gelüb</ab>
        
    <ab>içerü girdükde <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> ḳıyām idüb dostāne
        <lb/>muʿāmele iderek maḳāmlarına oturduḳdan ṣoñra ṭatlu yerine cevāhir maʿcūnu virilüb
        <lb/>baʿdehū ḳahveler virildikden ṣoñra bir miḳdār ṣoḥbet olunduḳdan ṣoñra on beş nefer ḳadar
        <lb/>intiḫāb olunmış ḫānende ve sāzende faṣl itmişlerdür. <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi-yi mezbūr</rs> sāʿat dörde gelmekle
        <lb/>ḫānende faṣlı tamām olduḳdan ṣoñra ẓuhr namāzın edā içün <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">vezīr-i müşārün ileyh ḥażretleri</rs> 
        <lb/>ḳalḳub bir sāʿatden ṣoñra gelüb oturduḳda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">imām-ı evvel-i şehriyārī efendi</rs> ḥażretleri gelüb
        <lb/>sāʿat yediye varduḳda ṭaʿām çıkub</ab>
        
        <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">paşa</rs>nıñ ṣaġ  ṭarafında <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">imām-ı evvel efendi</rs> 
        <lb/>ve mukālemeci başı <rs type="person">muḥāsebeci-i sābıḳ Meḥmed Efendi</rs> ve ḳapucıbaşı ve bu ḥaḳīr oturub ṣol
        <lb/>ṭarafında yalñız <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi beg</rs> oturub ve begzādegānı dīvānḫānede peşkūnlar üzerinde iṭʿām 
        <lb/>olunmuşdur. Baʿdeʾl-ṭaʿām ḫānendegān yine faṣl itmişlerdür. Bu esnāda <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> iḥrām üzerinden
        <lb/>minder üzerine oturub oda-ʾı mezbūr havādār olmaġ la sovuk teʾsīr itmesün diye zīrine
        <lb/>bir şāl yorġ an ḳonmışdur. Bu defʿa faṣl ziyāde olmaġ la sāʿat dokuz buçuġı tecāvüz iderek
        <lb/>şerbet ve buḫūr virilüb</ab>
        
    <ab>baʿdehū <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi</rs> bir aġ ır telli boyama ve bir yaġ lıḳ ve bir yemenī ve ḳapucı başı aġ aya
        <lb/>bir menevīş ṣof ferāce ve begzādegān tercümānına otuz ḳadar telli çekme ve bu ḥaḳīre bir çuḳa
        <lb/>ve bir ḳumāş ve yeñiçeri ḥāṣekisine daḫı bir çuḳa ve bir ḳumāş ve çorbacıya bir çuḳa ve bir ḳumāş virilüb 
        <lb/>ve <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi bege</rs> kemer raḫt ile sīm rikāblı Ḥaleb <unclear reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="char"/>
        taʿbīr olunan telli kesme ile mükemmel bir ḳır
        <lb/>ṭāy at çekilüb ve üzerine süvār olub gitmişdür. Ve oda-yi mezbūrda mevcūd olan şukūfe 
        <lb/>ve meyvenüñ cümlesi <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ilçi bege</rs> gönderilmişdür.</ab>
        
        </div>
    
    <div type="translation" xml:lang="en" xml:id="vipa.pr.osm.17200415-transl">
            <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
    <ab>
        <hi rend="#red">The following relates the visit of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> to the chancellor.</hi> 
        <date type="Hijri" when="1720-04-15">On the sixth day of the month, a Sunday</date>,
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came to visit the respected
        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">vizier chancellor pasha</rs>. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">vizier</rs> 
        dispatched his caique powered with seven pairs of oarsmen to the pier in front of the western gate.
        In addition, for the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> and his noblemen, twenty saddled horses were dispatched
        to the garden gate. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> embarked on the dispatched caique along with the
        chief of the gatekeepers and his entourage embarked on the thirty caiques following behind. 
        They all draw near to the garden gate. Mounting the horses present at the location,
        they rode to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">vizier</rs>’s house located in the vicinity of Hocahanı.</ab>
        
    <ab>Before the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> went upstairs [into the reception room], the aghas of the vizier, all wearing
        sable furs on ceremonial cloaks, came from outside the door of the two-benched large room
        and advanced to the front [of the meeting room]. For the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>, a few covers were spread 
        [on the ground] and on top of them an embroidered seat was placed. Afterwards, 
        the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> came and sat on that spot,
        followed by his highness <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">the prosperous vizier</rs>,
        who was wearing a sable fur on a green broadcloth ceremonial cloak.</ab>
        
        <ab>Upon the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">chancellor</rs>’s entry into the room,
            the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> rose to his feet and the two men 
        treated each other cordially and sat on their seat. After that, precious and costly opiates
        (<foreign xml:lang="tr">cevāhir maʿcūnu</foreign>) were served instead of a sweet. Afterwards, coffee was served.
        Following some conversation, around fifteen selected 
        vocalists and musicians performed. After the musical performance was over, 
        as it was getting close to four o’clock, his excellency <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">the vizier</rs> left [the room] 
        for afternoon prayer and he came back an hour later. Around seven o’clock, 
        his highness [the sultan’s] <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">senior private imam</rs> joined the group and a meal was served.</ab>
        
        <ab>During the meal, on the right-hand side of <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">the chancellor</rs>
            sat <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14716">the senior imam</rs>, the negotiator (<foreign xml:lang="tr">mukālemeci</foreign>),
        and the former chief accountant Mehmed Efendi, the chief gatekeeper, and this humble servant.
        On the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14715">chancellor</rs>’s left-hand side,
            only the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> sat, while his noblemen was served a meal
        on the benches inside the reception room. After the meal, the vocalists performed again.
        During the performance, the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> moved from the ground cover he was sitting on to a cushion. 
        As the room was airy, a shawl duvet was placed under him [so that the] cold could not affect him.
        This time, the musical performance lasted long. As it was past 
        half past nine, sorbet and frankincense were served.</ab>
        
    <ab>Afterwards, an embroidered, colored kerchief, a handkerchief, and a colored
        cotton handkerchief was given to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>. The gatekeeper agha was given
        a fine moiré ceremonial cloak. The noblemen of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs> were given around
        thirty embroidered [pieces of] fabrics. This humble servant, the janissary lieutenant,
        and the janissary captain each were given a broadcloth and a [piece of] fabric. The <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>
        was presented with a young grey horse equipped with a leather-strap harness, silver stirrups,
        and a horse blanket(?) worked with open-work embroideries called Aleppo cotton
        print(?); he mounted the horse and left. All of the fruit and flowers in the room were
        sent to the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">ambassador</rs>.</ab>            
            
                 
        
     </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>