<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->
                <title xml:lang="de">Befehlsschreiben des Sultans an den Obersten Richter
                    (monla/molla) von Nikosia und an den Zollpächter von Zypern zur Beilegung des
                    Falls eines Seekapitäns, eines Untertanen des heiligen römischen Kaisers, dessen
                    Güter von einem osmanischen Beamten unter Verletzung des kaiserlichen
                    Vertragsschreibens (ahidname) beschlagnahmt worden waren; Istanbul, 15. Oktober
                    – 24. Oktober 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Sultan’s decree to the chief judge of Nicosia and to the
                    revenue collector of Cyprus to settle the case of a sea captain, a subject of
                    the Roman emperor, whose goods were confiscated by an Ottoman official in
                    violation of the imperial letter of agreement (ahidname); Istanbul, October 15 –
                    October 24, 1719</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Lefkoşe mollası ve Kıbrıs muhassılına hitaben
                    yazılan, eşyası ahidname hükümlerine aykırı olarak alıkonulan ve Kutsal Roma
                    İmparatoru’nun tabaasından olan tüccarın durumunu çözmeleri hakkında hükmü;
                    İstanbul, 15 Ekim – 24 Ekim, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17191015-17191024.1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 71, entry 137</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-10-15" notAfter="1719-10-24"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>; Istanbul, 15. Oktober – 24. Oktober 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve
                    Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung: Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die
                    Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                    habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt
                    1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>treatment of Austrian merchants and travelers according to the conditions
                        of the imperial letter of agreement (ahidname)</item>
                    <item>judge of Nicosia</item>
                    <item>revenue collector of Cyprus</item>
                    <item>returning of confiscated goods</item>
                    <item>merchants</item>
                    <item>Nicosia</item>
                    <item>Cyprus</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00035_Page_71_Entry_137.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>
        <!--<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14602">Nīş</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14242">muḥāfıẓı vezīre</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr9425">Belġrād</rs>
                <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki</rs>
                <rs type="place" ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs>-->


    </facsimile>

    <text type="decree">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191015-17191024.1">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">137</metamark>

                <ab><lb/><rs type="place" ref="#mpr16041">Lefḳoşa</rs> monlāsına ve <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr15601">cezīre-i Ḳıbrıs</rs> muḥaṣṣılına ḥüküm ki:</ab>

                <ab><lb/>Ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik ile der-i devlet-medāruma gelen <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf <lb/>de Virmond</rs> ḫutimet
                    ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme mühürlü ʿarż-ı ḥāl gönderüb</ab>

                <ab>devlet-i ʿaliyyem ile ṣulḥ ve ṣalaḥ üzere <lb/>olan müşārün ileyh <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ tüccarından <gap
                        unit="char" extent="5"/> nām ḳapūdān bundan aḳdem sefīnesiyle <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15601">Ḳıbrıs <lb/>cezīresi</rs>ne varduḳda daḫl ve
                    taʿarruż īcāb itmez iken cezīre-i mezbūrede mütesellim olan <gap unit="char"
                        extent="5"/> nām kimesne <lb/>mücerred celb-i māl içün <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr6718">Nemçe</rs> sefīnelerinüñ rūy-ı deryāda ẕehāb u iyāblarına
                    ruḫṣat yoḳdur diyü ḫilāf-ı <lb/>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn ḳapūdān-ı merḳūm sefīnesinüñ
                    dümenin alub ve sefīnesin alıḳoyub ġadr ve teʿaddī <lb/>olunduġın bildürüb</ab>

                <ab>ḳapūdān-ı merḳūmuñ ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn alıḳonılan sefīnesi dümeniyle girü
                    redd <lb/>ve teslīm ve fī mā baʿd <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorı</rs> bayraġıyla varan sefīnelerine teʿaddī ve rencīde olunmamaḳ
                    bābında <lb/>emr-i şerīfüm ricā eylemegin</ab>

                <ab>ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnuma mürācaʿat olunduḳda tüccār ṭāʾifesi ṭarefeynüñ memālikinde
                    selefde virilen <lb/>ʿahdnāmeler mūcebince emnen ve sālimen gendü ḥāllerinde
                    ticāret ideler müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā
                        imperāṭorına</rs>
                    <lb/>tābiʿ olan vilāyetlerüñ ve bundan ṣoñra millet-i naṣārādan alacaḳları
                    yirlerüñ tüccār reʿāyāları her ḳanġı <lb/>milletden olur ise olsunlar berren ve
                    baḥren bu ḫuṣūṣa meʾmūr olan vekīller beyninde ḳarār virildügi <lb/>vech üzere
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ bayraġı ve
                    paṭentasıyla memālik-i maḥrūseye gendü ḥāllerinde gelüb <lb/>gidüb ve alış viriş
                    idüb lāzım gelen gümrükleri virdüklerinden ṣoñra rencīde ve remīde olunmamaḳ
                    <lb/>ḥimāyet ve ṣiyānet olunalar diyü mesṭūr ve muḳayyed olmaġın</ab>

                <ab>vech-i meşrūḥ üzere ḳapūdān-ı mesfūra bir <lb/>dürlü taʿarruż olunmayub ḫilāf-ı
                    ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn alıḳonılan sefīneye ruḫṣat ve fī-mā baʿd <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ <lb/>bayraġı ve paṭentası ile varan
                    sefīneye bir dürlü rencīde olunmayub ve ḫilāfıyla ḥareket idenleri ḥaḳḳlarından
                    <lb/>gelinecegini ifhām ve ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnumuñ mażmūn-ı münīfi üzere ʿamel ve
                    ḥareket olunmaḳ bābında fermān-ı ʿālī-şānum <lb/>ṣādır olmışdur.</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">Buyurdum ki:</rs>
                    <lb/>vuṣūl bulduḳda bu bābda ṣādır olan fermān-ı celīlü l-ḳadrüm mūcebince ʿamel
                    daḫī vech-i meşrūḥ üzere <lb/>ḳapūdān-ı merḳūmuñ bir dürlü taʿarruż olunmayub ve
                    ḫilāf-ı ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūn alıḳonılan sefīnesine <lb/>ruḫṣat ve fī mā baʿd <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>nuñ bayraġı ve paṭentasıyla
                    varan sefīneye bir dürlü rencīde <lb/>olunmayub ḫilāfıyla ḥareket idenlerüñ
                    ḥaḳḳlarından gelinecegini ifhām ve ʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnumuñ mażmūn-ı <lb/>münīfi
                    üzere ʿamel ve ḥareket eyleyüb mażmūn-ı emr-i şerīfümle ʿāmil olasın şöyle
                    bilesin.</ab>



                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-10-15" notAfter="1719-10-24">fī evāil-i
                            Ẕ<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕī’l-ḥicce</supplied> sene 1131</date></ab>


            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17191015-17191024.1.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>
                <ab>Decree to the chief judge (<foreign xml:lang="ota">monlā</foreign>) of <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr16041">Nicosia</rs> and the revenue collector of the <rs
                        type="place" ref="#mpr15601">Cyprus island</rs>:</ab>

                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>
                    —may God end his days propitiously—who came to my threshold of felicity as grand
                    ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, the
                    paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, sent a sealed
                    petition to my court (threshold of felicity) and requested my most noble order
                    about [the following matter]:</ab>

                <ab>Formerly, when a sea captain named <gap unit="char" extent="5"/> from among the
                    merchants of the aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>,
                    who is currently on friendly and amicable terms with my <rs type="place" ref="#mpr7118">sublime state</rs>, went on
                    his ship to the <rs type="place" ref="#mpr15601">island of Cyprus</rs>, although
                    interfering with him and attacking was not necessary, a person named <gap
                        unit="char" extent="5"/> who is a deputy governor on the island received in
                    violation of the imperial letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i
                        ḥumāyūn</foreign>) the helm of the aforesaid captain’s ship and detained the
                    ship, claiming—merely with the purpose of confiscating goods—that Austrian ships
                    have no permission to sail on sea. 
                    [<rs type="person" ref="#mpr9435">The ambassador</rs>] reported that [the sea captain]
                    was treated unjustly and oppressed.</ab>

                <ab>The helm and the ship of the aforesaid captain that are detained in violation of
                    the imperial letter of agreement shall be returned and delivered and, from
                    now on, ships carrying the flag of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman
                        emperor</rs> and arrive to [that location] shall not be oppressed and
                    injured.</ab>

                <ab>Upon consultation to my imperial letter of agreement (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i
                    ḥumāyūn</foreign>), it is written and recorded therein that—as per
                    previously issued letters of agreement—the merchant class shall trade quietly,
                    safely, and soundly within the territories of both parties. The merchant subjects from the
                    provinces that are under the suzerainty of the aforesaid <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> and those who come from the places that
                    [the emperor] may capture from other Christian nations — regardless of whichever
                    nation those merchants may belong to — they shall quietly come and go to the
                    well-protected domains over land and sea and they shall trade under the flag and
                    patent of the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> in the way
                    concluded by the delegations authorized on this matter. Once they pay the
                    required customs duty, they shall not be injured and disturbed and be guarded
                    and protected.</ab>

                <ab>My illustrious edict has been issued that, in the way described, the aforesaid
                    captain shall not be attacked in any means. The ship that has been detained in
                    violation of the imperial letter of agreement shall be granted permission. From
                    now on, ships that arrive carrying the flag and patent of the <rs type="person"
                        ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> shall not be injured in any way. It shall
                    be understood that those who act in opposition to it will be vanquished; [all]
                    shall act and behave as per the exalted purview of my imperial letter of
                    agreement.</ab>

                <ab>So have <rs type="person" ref="#mpr14244">I</rs> ordered: As my edict
                    of glorious worth that was issued about this matter arrives, you shall act
                    accordingly. In the way described, the aforesaid captain shall not be
                    attacked in any way. His ship, that has been detained in violation of the
                    imperial letter of agreement, shall be given permission. From now on, ships that
                    arrive carrying the flag and patent of the Roman emperor shall not be injured in
                    any means. [You] shall understand that those who act contrary to it will be
                    vanquished. You shall act and behave as per the exalted purview of my imperial
                    letter of agreement and shall act according to the purview of my noble command.
                    So shall you know!</ab>



                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-10-15" notAfter="1719-10-24">October 15 to
                        October 24, 1719</date></ab>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
