<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- title of the source -->

                <title xml:lang="de">Abschrift des sultanischen Dekrets (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) über die Ernennung eines neuen
                    Dolmetschers an der österreichischen Botschaft; Istanbul, 15. September – 24.
                    September 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="en">Copy of the sultan’s imperial charter (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) about the appointment of a new
                    interpreter (dragoman) to the Austrian embassy; Istanbul, September 15 –
                    September 24, 1719</title>

                <title xml:lang="tr">Sultanın, Avusturya elçiliğine yeni bir tercüman atanması
                    hakkında beratı (nīşān-ı hümāyūn); İstanbul, 15 Eylül - 24 Eylül, 1719</title>
                <!-- author of the source -->
                <author>
                    <persName/>
                </author>
                <!-- Responsibilities for the digital source -->
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- editor -->
                    <resp>Edition</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">
                        <forename>Merve</forename>
                        <surname>Kurkutlu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- translation -->
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName sameAs="#yy">
                        <forename>Yasir</forename>
                        <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <!-- data modelling-->
                    <resp>Datenmodellierung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Stephan</forename>
                        <surname>Kurz</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/"> Austrian Academy of Sciences, Institute
                        for Habsburg and Balkan Studies </orgName>
                </publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at"> GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                        Management System </orgName>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">Creative Commons
                        BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2022">2022</date>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>

                <idno type="PID">o:vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="de">Digitale Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen
                    Diplomatie 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Digital Scholarly Edition of Habsburg-Ottoman Diplomatic
                    Sources 1500–1918</title>
                <title xml:lang="tr">Habsburg-Osmanlı Diplomasisi Kaynakları Dijital Edisyonu
                    1500–1918</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Projektleitung</resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Strohmeyer</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>BOA, Istanbul</institution>
                        <collection>Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defterleri, Nemçelü Ahid Defteri, no.
                            57</collection>
                        <idno>Page 69, entry 131</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <physDesc> </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate notBefore="1719-09-15" notAfter="1719-09-24"/>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Editionsregeln und Kodierungsrichtlinien</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>Abschrift des Sultans Dekret (<foreign>nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>/<foreign>berat</foreign>) über die Ernennung eines neuen
                    Dolmetschers an der österreichischen Botschaft; Istanbul, 15. September – 24.
                    September 1719, bearb. von Yasir Yılmaz und Merve Kurkutlu, Datenmodellierung:
                    Jakob Sonnberger, Stephan Kurz, in: Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von Virmonts
                    und Ibrahim Pachas (1719/20), hg. von Arno Strohmeyer und Stephan Kurz (Digitale
                    Edition von Quellen zur habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500-1918, hg. von
                    Arno Strohmeyer, Projekt 1), Wien 2022. </p>
            </refsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <ab>
                    <ref target="context:vipa" type="context"> Die Großbotschaften Damian Hugo von
                        Virmonts und Ibrahim Paschas (1719/20) </ref>
                    <ref target="context:vipa.ded" type="context">Düvel-i Ecnebiye Defteri</ref>
                    <ref target="context:qhod" type="context"> Digitale Edition von Quellen zur
                        habsburgisch-osmanischen Diplomatie 1500–1918 </ref>
                </ab>
                <!-- Project description -->
                <p>Projektbeschreibung</p>
                <!-- this may be a pointer to the actual document -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract xmlns="">
                <list>
                    <item>freedoms and liberties granted to the dragoman of a European (in this case an Austrian) embassy in Istanbul</item>
                    <item>Austrian ambassador</item>
                    <item>Nemçe elçisi</item>
                    <item>Damian Hugo von Virmont</item>
                    <item>appointment of a new dragoman</item>
                    <item>dragoman</item>
                    <item>tercüman</item>
                    <item>Dolmetsch</item>
                    <item>translation</item>
                    <item>nişan-ı hümayun</item>
                    <item>berat</item>
                    <item>imperial charter</item>
                    <item>ahidname</item>
                </list>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ota">Ottoman Turkish</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <facsimile>

        <surface start="#IMG1">
            <graphic url="A_{DVNSDVE_d____00057_1_00034_Page_69_Entry_131.jpg" xml:id="IMG1"/>
        </surface>


    </facsimile>

    <text type="charter">
        <body>
            <div type="original" xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.2">
                <pb n="1" facs="#IMG1"/>
                <metamark place="margin">131</metamark>

                <ab><seg rend="#diagonal"><lb/>Mesfūr <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10485">Niḳolos</rs>
                        tercümān hālık olub <lb/>ḳaydı terḳīn buyurmaġla yirine papasın oġlı
                            <lb/><rs type="person">Arutin</rs> (Arvitin/Arvitre?) tercümān naṣb ve
                        berat-ı ʿālī-şān virilmişdür. <lb/><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1742-07-14"
                            notAfter="1742-07-23">fī evāṣıṭ-ı cā(Cemāẕiyye’l-evvel)
                        1155</date></seg><note resp="#yy" place="paragraph" xml:id="ftn1"> It
                        appears that this note was added on the record retrospectively when Nikolas
                        Theyls died in 1741.</note></ab>


                <ab><lb/>Nīşān-ı hümāyūn oldur ki</ab>

                <lb/>
                <ab><rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs> ṭarafından büyükilçilik
                    ile der-i devlet-medāruma gelen ḳıdvetü ümerāʾi’l-milleti’l-mesīḥiyye <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">Cenerāl Ġrūf de Virmond</rs>
                    <lb/>ḫutimet ʿavāḳibühū bi-l-ḫayr südde-i saʿādetüme ʿarż-ı ḫāl gönderüb</ab>

                <ab>bundan aḳdem müşārün ileyh <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Romā imperāṭorı</rs>
                    ṭarafından <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">āsitāne-i saʿādet</rs>ümde muḳīm
                    olan <lb/>ḳapu ketḫüdāsı yanına tercümān olan <rs type="person" ref="#mpr16117"
                        >Maderos</rs> nām tercümān mürd olmaġla yirine rāfiʿ-i tevḳīʿ-i refīʿü
                    ş-şān-ı ḫāḳāni <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10485">Niḳolos</rs><note resp="#yy"
                        place="paragraph" xml:id="ftn2">In the document, Nikolos is mentioned
                        without last name and who he was is not clear based on this charter.
                        However, we infer from the ambassador <ref target="/o:vipa.l.hbg.17190906"
                            >Virmont’s report dated September 6, 1719</ref> that the interpreter
                        whom this <foreign>berat</foreign> was addressed to was Nikolas
                        Theyls.</note>
                    <lb/>tercümān naṣb ve taʿyīn olunmaġlaʿahdnāme-i hümāyūnum mūcebince ola geldügi
                    üzere berāt-ı şerīfüm virilmek bābında ʿināyet ricā itmegin <lb/>bu nīşān-ı
                    hümāyūnı virdüm ve buyurdum ki:</ab>

                <ab>Mesfūr <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10485">Niḳolos</rs> vech-i meşrūḥ üzere
                    tercümān olub tercümānlıḳ ḫidmetinde olanlar <lb/>ve oġulları ve ḫizmetkārları
                    ve cāriyeleri ḫarāc ve ʿavārıż ve ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası ve resm-i üsārā ve sāʾir tekālīf-i
                    ʿörfiyye ṭalebiyle <lb/>rencīde ve remīde olunmayub ve ḳul ve cāriye istiḫdām
                    idermişsin diyü kimesne ḫarāc ve rüsūm ve bāc ṭalebiyle daḫl ve rencīde eylemeye
                    <lb/>ve gendünüñ maṣraf ve hedāyāsına ve ḳadīmden geydügi melbūsāt ve mefrūşāt
                    ve meʾkūlāt ve meşrūbātına kimesne daḫl ve rencīde <lb/>eylemeyüb ḳadīmden ola
                    geldügi üzere ʿafv olunub ve rüsūm-ı gümrük ve bāc ṭaleb olunmaya ve evlerine
                    ʿaskerīden ḳonaḳ ḳonulmaġıyla rencīde <lb/>olunmaya ve gendü bāġında ḥāṣıl olan
                    şīreden ḫamr emīni ve <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14828">Ġalaṭa</rs> voyvodaları
                    sāʾirlerden ola geldügi üzere fuçı aḳçasını <lb/>ṭaleb eylemeyüb gendüsi ve
                    evlādı ve taṣarrufında olan cāriyeleri ḫarāc ve ʿavārıż ve ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası ve
                    resm-i maṣdariyyeden <lb/>ve tekālīf-i ʿörfiyyenüñ cümlesinden muʿāf ve müsellem
                    olub ve mezbūr ile ve her kimüñ daʿvāsı olur ise ellerinde olan ʿahdnāme-i
                    <lb/>hümāyūn mūcebince āsitāne-i saʿādetüme ḥavāle olunub ġayr-ı yirde istimāʿ
                    olunmaya ve baʿżı zamānda bir yire gitmek istedükde gidişde <lb/>ve gelişde
                    ḳaradan ve deryādan menāzil ve merāḥilde gendüye ve esvāb ve ṭavarlarına ve
                    emvāl ve erzāḳına ve yanında olan <lb/>ādamlarına ulaḳ ve ulaḳ akçası ve ġayr-i
                    cānibde kimesne daḫl ve taʿarruż eylemeyüb ve her ḳanda dāḫıl olur ise <lb/>zād
                    ve zevāde ve sāʾir ẕaḫīresi narḫ-ı rūzī üzere aḳçasıyla virilüb bir ferd
                    taʿallül ve nizāʿ eylemeye ve maḫūf <lb/>ve muḫāṭara olan yirlerde başına aḳ
                    ṣarınub ve ḳılıç ve oḳ ve yay ve sāʾir levāzımāt götürdükde ḳāḍīlar <lb/>ve
                    beglerbegiler ve ġayrıdan bir ferd rencīde eylemeyüb ola geldügi üzere ḥimāyet
                    ve ṣiyānet ve anuñ gibi teʿaddī ve tecāvüz <lb/>üzere olanlar menʿ ve defʿolunub
                    dāʾimā işbu nīşān-ı hümāyūnumuñ mażmūn-ı münīfi ile ʿamel olunub ḫilāfına rıżā
                    ve cevāz gösterilmeye şöyle bileler ʿalāmet-i şerīfe. </ab>
                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-15" notAfter="1719-09-24">fī evāil-i Ẕā
                            [<supplied resp="#yy">Ẕi’l-ḳaʿide</supplied>] sene 1131</date></ab>



                <ab/>

            </div>


            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en"
                xml:id="vipa.ded.osm.17190915-17190924.2.translation">
                <pb n="1" facs="IMG01"/>
                <ab><seg rend="diagonal">The aforesaid interpreter Nikolos died. His record is
                        deleted. In his place, <rs type="person">Arutin</rs> (Arvitin/Arvitre?), the
                        son of a priest, has been assigned and a noblest imperial deed of grant
                            (<foreign xml:lang="ota">berāt</foreign>) is issued. <date type="Hijri"
                            notBefore="1742-07-14" notAfter="1742-07-23">July 14 to July 23,
                            1742.</date></seg><ref type="note_reference" target="#ftn1"/></ab>

                <ab>So is the imperial charter / sign(<foreign xml:lang="ota">nīşān-ı
                        hümāyūn</foreign>):</ab>

                <ab>The paragon of the great commanders of the community of Messiah, <rs
                        type="person" ref="#mpr9435">General [Damian Hugo] Count of Virmont</rs>—may
                    God end his days propitiously—who came to my gate that is the center of state as grand ambassador from the <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs>, sent a
                    petition to my threshold of felicity.</ab>
                <ab>The interpreter named Maderos, who was formerly the interpreter for the resident
                    envoy of the aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr9399">Roman emperor</rs> in my
                        <rs type="place" ref="#mpr14055">threshold of felicity</rs>, died. In his
                    place, the most glorious imperial sign [has been bestowed to announce that] the translator
                        <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10485">Nikolos</rs><ref type="note_reference"
                        target="#ftn2"/> has been assigned and appointed. For the grand ambassador
                    officially requested my favor to grant my noble charter (<foreign xml:lang="ota">berāt-ı şerīf</foreign>), as it
                    has been taking place to this day according to my imperial letter of agreement
                    (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ʿahdnāme-i ḥumāyūn</foreign>), I issue this imperial sign (<foreign xml:lang="ota">nīşān-ı hümayun</foreign>) and I command
                    that:</ab>
                <ab>The aforesaid <rs type="person" ref="#mpr10485">Nikolos</rs> has become an
                    interpreter in the way described. Those who work as interpreters, their sons,
                    servants, and the women in their household shall not be injured and disturbed
                    with claims of tribute, extraordinary tax, dues for goods in transit 
                    (<foreign xml:lang="ota">ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s fee'), captive tax, or other
                    levies. No one shall interfere with him demanding tribute, tax, or toll under
                    the pretext that he employs male and female slaves and oppress him. No one shall
                    interfere with his own expenses, gifts, garments, furniture, food, and drinks
                    and oppress him. He shall be forgiven as per the time-honored practice and no
                    customs duty or tolls shall be claimed. He shall not be oppressed through the
                    deployment of a military officer at their house. The voivode of <rs type="place"
                        ref="#mpr14828">Galata</rs> and the wine superintendent shall not claim
                    barrel money for the must produced from his own vineyard as they have been
                    claiming from others. Himself, his children, and the women under his authority
                    shall be exempt and delivered from tribute, extraordinary tax, dues for goods in
                    transit (<foreign xml:lang="tur">ḳaṣṣāb aḳçası</foreign>, lit. 'butcher’s fee'), export fee (<foreign
                        xml:lang="ota">maṣdariyye</foreign>), wine tax, and all of the extraordinary
                    levies. Whoever has a court case with the aforesaid [interpreter], as required
                    by the letter of agreement in their possession, the case shall be referred to my
                    threshold of felicity and a hearing shall not take place at another location. At
                    certain times, as he would like to go somewhere, as he comes and goes on land
                    and sea, at stations on the road, and during stages of the journey, no one shall
                    interfere and attack him, his clothes, flock of animals, properties, 
                    provisions, and his men accompanying him [claiming] messenger fees or on any
                    other excuses. In whichever location he enters, his victual, provisions for the
                    journey, and cereals shall be given in return for the fixed price. No one shall
                    seek an excuse to avoid or dispute it. Judges, provincial governors, and not
                    even a single person from among the rest shall disturb him when he, at dangerous
                    and insecure places, wraps his head in white (<foreign xml:lang="tur">başına aḳ
                        ṣarınub</foreign>) and takes with him a sword, an arrow, a bow, and other
                    equipment; they shall guard and protect [him] as it has been the practice. Those who
                    do wrong and attack shall be prevented and repelled. At all times, [all] should
                    act as required by the exalted purview of my imperial sign (<foreign
                        xml:lang="tur">nīşān-ı hümāyūn</foreign>); no consent or permission shall be
                    shown to the contrary. Thus shall they know and [have confidence] in the noble
                    mark!</ab>
                <ab><date type="Hijri" notBefore="1719-09-15" notAfter="1719-09-24">September 15 to
                        September 24, 1719</date></ab>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
